<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-allenby-1983">Allenby, R.B.J.T, Rings, Fields and Groups, Edward Arnold, 1983.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-appel-1976">Appel, K., and W. Haken, {``}Every Planar Map Is 4-colorable.{''} Bull, Am. Math. Soc. 82 (1976): 711-12.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-arbib-1981">Arbib, M. A., A. J. Kfoury, and R. N. Moll, A Basis for Theoretical Computer Science, New York: Springer-Verlag, 1981.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-austin-1983">Austin, A. Keith, {``}An Elementary Approach to NP-Completeness, {''} American Math. Monthly 90 (1983): 398-99.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-beardwood-1959">Beardwood, J., J. H. Halton, and J. M. Hammersley, {``}The Shortest Path Through Many Points.{''} Proc. Cambridge Phil. Soc. 55 (1959): 299-327.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-benari-1982">Ben-Ari, M, Principles of Concurrent Programming, Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice-Hall, 1982.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-berge-1962">Berge, C, The Theory of Graphs and Its Applications, New York: Wiley, 1962.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-bogart-2005">Bogart, Kenneth P, <title>Combinatorics Through Guided Discovery</title>,  2005.<note><p>This book may be freely downloaded and redestributed at <url src="http://www.math.dartmouth.edu/news-resources/electronic/kpbogart/"/>  under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License (FDL), { }as published by the Free Software Foundation.</p></note></biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-bronson-1969">Bronson, Richard, Matrix Methods, New York: Academic Press, 1969.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="busacker-1965">Busacker, Robert G., and Thomas L. Saaty, Finite Graphs and Networks, New York: McGraw-Hill, 1965.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-connell-1982">Connell, Ian, Modern Algebra, A Constructive Introduction, New York: North-Holland, 1982.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-denning-1978">Denning, Peter J., Jack B. Dennis, and Joseph L. Qualitz, Machines, Languages, and Computation, Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice-Hall, 1978.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-denning-1987">Denning, Peter J, <title>Multigrids and Hypercubes</title>. American Scientist 75 (1987): 234-238.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-dornhoff-1978">Dornhoff, L. L., and F. E. Hohn, Applied Modern Algebra, New York: Macmillan, 1978.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-even-1979">Even, S, Graph Algorithms, Potomac, MD: Computer Science Press, 1979.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-fisher-1977">Fisher, J. L, Application-Oriented Algebra, New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1977.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-ford-1962">Ford, L. R., Jr., and D. R. Fulkerson, Flows in Networks,  Princeton, NJ: Princeton Univesity Press, 1962.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-fraleigh-1982">Fraleigh, John B, A First Course in Abstract Algebra, 3rd ed. Reading, MA: Addison-Wesley, 1982.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-gallian-1986">Gallian, Joseph A, Contemporary Abstract Algebra, D.C. Heath, 1986.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-gallian-1977">Gallian, Joseph A, <title>Group Theory and the Design of a Letter-Facing Machine<title>, American Math. Monthly 84 (1977): 285-287.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-hamming-1980">Hamming, R. W, Coding and Information Theory, Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice-Hall, 1980.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-hill-1974">Hill, F. J., and G. R. Peterson, Switching Theory and Logical Design, 2nd ed. New York: Wiley, 1974.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-hofstadter-1979">Hofstadter, D. R, Godel, Escher, Bach: An Eternal Golden Braid, New York: Basic Books, 1979.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-hohn-1966">Hohn, F. E, Applied Boolean Algebra, 2nd ed. New York: Macmillan, 1966.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-hopcroft-1969">Hopcroft, J. E., and J. D. Ullman, Formal Languages and Their Relation to Automata, Reading, MA: Addison-Wesley, 1969.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-hu-1982">Hu, T. C, Combinatorial Algorithms, Reading, MA: Addison-Wesley, 1982.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-knuth-1978">Knuth, D. E, The Art of Computer Programming. Vol. 1, Fundamental Algorithms, 2nd ed. Reading, MA: Addison-Wesley, 1973.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-knuth-1981">Knuth, D. E, The Art of Computer Programming. Vol. 2, Seminumerical Algorithms, 2nd ed., Reading, MA: Addison-Wesley, 1981.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-knuth-1973">Knuth, D. E, The Art of Computer Programming. Vol. 3, Sorting and Searching, Reading, MA: Addison-Wesley, 1973.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-kulisch-1981">Kulisch, U. W., and Miranker, W. L, Computer Arithmetic in Theory and Practice, New York: Academic Press, 1981.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-lipson-1981">Lipson, J. D, Elements of Algebra and Algebraic Computing, Reading, MA: Addison-Wesley, 1981.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-liu-1977">Liu, C. L, Elements of Discrete Mathematics, New York: McGraw-Hill, 1977.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-odonnell-1963">O'Donnell, Analysis of Boolean Functions. <note>A book about Fourier analysis of boolean functions that is being developed online in a blog.</note></biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-ore-1963">Ore, O, Graphs and Their Uses, New York: Random House, 1963.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-parry-1981">Parry, R. T., and H. Pferrer, {``}The Infamous Traveling-Salesman Problem: A Practical Approach.{''} Byte 6 (July 1981): 252-90.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-pless-1982">Pless, V, Introduction to the Theory of Error-Correcting Codes, New York: Wiley-Interscience, 1982.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-purdom-1985">Purdom, P. W., and C. A. Brown, The Analysis of Algorithms, Holt, Rinehart, and Winston, 1985.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-quine-1966">Quine, W. V, The Ways of Paradox and Other Essays, New York: Random House, 1966.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-ralson-1984">Ralston, A, {``}The First Course in Computer Science Needs a Mathematics Corequisite.{''} Communications of the ACM 27-10 (1984): 1002-1005.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-solow-1982">Solow, Daniel, How to Read and Do Proofs, New York: Wiley, 1982.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-standish-1980">Standish, T. A, Data Structure Techniques, Reading, MA: Addison-Wesley, 1980.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-stoll-1961">Stoll, Robert R, Sets, Logic and Axiomatic Theories, San Francisco: W. H. Freeman, 1961.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-strang-1980">Strang, G, Linear Algebra and Its Applications, 2nd ed. New York: Academic Press, 1980.</biblio>
 <biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-tucker-1984">Tucker, Alan C, Applied Combinatorics, 2nd ed. New York: John Wiley and Sons, 1984.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-wand-1980">Wand, Mitchell, Induction, Recursion, and Programming, New York: North-Holland, 1980.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-warshall-1962">Warshall, S, {``}A Theorem on Boolean Matrices,{''}  Journal of the Association of Computing Machinery, 1962, 11-12.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-warshall-1962">Weisstein, Eric W. <title>Strassen Formulas</title>,  MathWorld--A Wolfram Web Resource, http://mathworld.wolfram.com/StrassenFormulas.html.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-wilf-1985">Wilf, Herbert S, {``}Some Examples of Combinatorial Averaging, American Math. Monthly 92 (1985).</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-wilf-1990">Wilf, Herbert S. <title>generatingfunctionology</title>, A K Peters/CRC Press, 2005<note>The 1990 edition of this book is available at <url href="http://www.math.upenn.edu/$\%$7Ewilf/DownldGF.html"/></note></biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-winograd-1965">Winograd, S, On the Time Required to Perform Addition, J. Assoc. Comp. Mach. 12 (1965): 277-85.</biblio> 
