




<section xml:id="s-Planarity and Colorings">
<title>Planarity and Colorings</title>
<index><main>Planarity and Colorings</main></index>



The topics in this section are related to how graphs are drawn.



\pmb{ Planarity:} Can a given graph be drawn in a plane so that no edges intersect? Certainly, it is natural to avoid intersections,
but up to now we haven't gone out of our way to do so.



\pmb{ Colorings:} Suppose that each vertex in an undirected graph is to be colored so that no two vertices that are connected by an edge have the
same color. How many colors are needed? This question is motivated by the problem of drawing a map so that no two bordering countries are colored
the same. A similar question can be asked for coloring edges.

<definition xml:id="def- Planar Graph/ Plane Graph/Planar Embedding."><title> Planar Graph/ Plane Graph/Planar Embedding.</title><index><main> Planar Graph/ Plane Graph/Planar Embedding.</main></index><notation><usage></usage><description></description></notation><statement><p></p></statement></definition>

 A graph is planar if it can be drawn in a plane so that no edges cross. If a
graph is drawn so that no edges intersect, it is a plane graph, and such a drawing is a planar embedding of the graph.



Example 9.6.1. The graph in Figure 9.6.1(a) is planar but not a plane graph. The same graph is drawn as a plane graph in Figure 9.6.1(b)


\begin{center}\(\)
\end{center}


\caption{\pmb{ Figure 9.6.1}\\
A planar graph and a planar embedding }



\pmb{ Notes:}


<ol label=“a”>
<li><p> In discussing planarity, we need only consider simple undirected graphs with no self-loops. All other graphs can be treated as such since
all of the edges that relate any two vertices can be considered as one <q>package</q> that clearly can be drawn in a plane.</p></li>
<li><p> Can you think of a graph that is not planar? How would you prove that it isn't planar? Proving the nonexistence of something is usually more
difficult than proving its existence. This case is no exception. Intuitively, we would expect that sparse graphs would be planar and dense graphs
would be nonplanar. Theorem 9.6.2 will verify that dense graphs are indeed nonplanar.</p></li>
<li><p> The topic of planarity is a result of trying to restrict a graph to two dimensions. Is there an analogous topic for three dimensions? What
graphs can be drawn in one dimension?



Answer to Note c: If a graph has only a finite number of vertices, it can always be drawn in three dimensions. This is not true for all graphs with
an infinite number of vertices. The only <q>one-dimensional</q> graphs are the ones that consist of a finite number of chains, as in Figure 9.6.2,
with one or more vertices in each chain.


\begin{center}\(\)
\end{center}


\caption{\pmb{ Figure 9.6.2}\\
Chains of length one, two and three}

\begin{doublespace}
\noindent\(\)
\end{doublespace}



<example xml:id="ex-9.6.2."><title>9.6.2.</title><p></p></example>
 A discussion of planarity is not complete without mentioning the famous Three Utilities Puzzle. The object
of the puzzle is to supply three houses, A, B, and C, with the three utilities, gas, electric, and water. The constraint that makes this puzzle impossible
to solve is that no utility lines may intersect i. e., a planar embedding of the graph in Figure 9.6.3, which is commonly denoted \(K_{3,3}\). {
}This graph is one of two fundamental nonplanar graphs. The Kuratowski Reduction Theorem states that if a graph is nonplanar then <q>contains</q>
either a \(K_{3,3}\) or a \(K_5\).  Containment is in the sense that if you start with a nonplanar graph you can always perform a sequence of
edge deletions and contractions (shrinking an edge so that the two vertices connecting it coincide) to produce one of the two graphs.





\begin{doublespace}
\noindent\(\)
\end{doublespace}


\caption{\pmb{ Figure 9.6.3}\\
The Three Utilities Puzzle.}



A planar graph divides the plane into one or more regions. Two points on the plane lie in the same region if you can draw a curve connecting the
two points that does not pass through an edge. One of these regions will be of infinite area. Each point on the plane is either a vertex, a point
on an edge, or a point in a region. A remarkable fact about the geography of planar graphs is the following theorem that is attributed to Euler.

<theorem xml:id="theorem-9.6.1: Euler's Formula."><title>9.6.1: Euler's Formula.</title><index><main>9.6.1: Euler's Formula.</main></index><statement></statement><proof></proof></theorem>
 If G = (V, E) is a connected planar graph with r regions, v vertices and e edges, then\\
$\quad \quad \quad $\(v + r - e = 2\)     (9.6a)



Experiment: Jot down a graph right now and count the number of vertices, regions, and edges that you have. If \(v + r - e\) is not 2, then your graph
is either nonplanar or not connected.

\pmb{  Proof: } We prove Euler's Formula by Induction on <m>e</m>, for \(e \geq  0\).

Basis: If \(e = 0\), then <m>G</m> must be a graph with one vertex, \(v = 1\); and there is one infinite region,\(\text{  }r = 1\).

Therefore, \(v + r-e= 1 + 1-0 = 2\), and the basis is true.

Induction: Suppose that <m>G</m> has <m>k</m> edges, \(k \geq  1\), and that all connected planar graphs with less than <m>k</m> edges satisfy
9.6a. Select any edge that is part of the boundary of the infinite region and call it \(e_1\). Let \(G'\) be the graph obtained from <m>G</m>
by deleting \(e_1\). Figure 9.6.4 illustrates the two different possibilities we need to consider: either \(G'\) is connected or it has two
connected components, \(G_1\) and \(G_2\).


\begin{center}\(\)
\end{center}


\caption{\pmb{ Figure 9.6.4}\\
Two case in the proof of Euler's Formula}

If \(G'\) is connected, the induction hypothesis can be applied to it. If \(G'\) has \(v'\) vertices, \(r'\) edges and \(e'\) edges, then {
}\(v'+r'-e'=2\) and in terms of the corresponding numbers for <m>G</m>, 

   \(\begin{array}{cc}
 v'=v &amp; \text{  }\text{No} \text{vertices} \text{were} \text{removed} \text{to} \text{form} G' \\
 r'=r-1 &amp; \text{One} \text{region} \text{of} G \text{merged} \text{with} \text{the} \text{infinite} \text{region} \text{when} e_1 \text{is} \text{removed}
\\
 e' = k-1 &amp; \text{We} \text{assumed} \text{that} G \text{had} k \text{edges}. \\
\end{array}\)

For the case where \(G'\) is connected, 

<m>\quad \quad</m>\(\text{            }v+ r -e= v+r-k \quad \quad = v' + (r'+1) -(e'+1)\quad \quad = v' + r'-e'\quad \quad =2\text{   }\)

 \textup{ If \(G'\) \textup{ is not connected, it must consist of two connected components, }\(G_1\)\textup{  and }\(G_2\) \textup{ since
we started with a connected graph, }G\textup{ . We can apply the induction hypothesis to each of the two components to complete the proof. 
We leave it to the students to do this, with the reminder that in counting regions, }\(G_1\) \textup{ and }\(G_2\) \textup{  will share the same
infinite region.  }\(\blacksquare\)}

<theorem xml:id="theorem-9.6.2. "><title>9.6.2. </title><index><main>9.6.2. </main></index><statement></statement><proof></proof></theorem>
 If \(G = (V, E)\) is a connected planar graph with <m>v</m> vertices, \(v\geq 3\), and <m>e</m> edges, then

$\quad \quad \quad $\(e \leq  3v - 6\).   (9.6b)

Remark: One implication of 9.6b is that the number of edges in a connected planar graph will never be larger than three times its
number.of vertices (as long as it has at least three vertices). Since the maximum number of edges in a graph with <m>v</m> vertices is a quadratic
function of <m>v</m>, as <m>v</m> increases, planar graphs are more and more sparse.

Outline of a Proof of Theorem 9.6.2.
<ol label=“a”>
<li><p> Let <m>r</m> be the number of regions in <m>G</m>. For each region, count the number of edges that comprise its border. The sum of these
counts must be at least  3r. Recall that we are working with simple graphs here, so a region made by two edges connecting the same two
vertices is not possible.

(b) Based on (a), infer that the number of edges in <m>G</m> must be at least \(\frac{3 r}{2}\).

(c) \(e\geq \frac{3r}{2}\text{   }\Rightarrow \text{      }r\leq \frac{2e}{3}\)

(d) Substitute \(\frac{2e}{3}\) for <m>r</m> in Euler's Formula to obtain an inequality that is equivalent to 9.6.b. \(\blacksquare\)



The following theorem will be useful as we turn to graph coloring.

<theorem xml:id="theorem-9.6.3."><title>9.6.3.</title><index><main>9.6.3.</main></index><statement></statement><proof></proof></theorem>
 If <m>G</m> is a connected planar graph, then it has a vertex with degree 5 or less.

\pmb{ Proof} (by contradiction): We can assume that <m>G</m> has at least seven vertices, for otherwise the degree of any vertex is at most 5.
Suppose that <m>G</m> is a connected planar graph and each vertex has a degree of 6 or more. Then, since each edge contributes to the degree
of two vertices, \(e\geq \frac{6v}{2}=3v\). However, Theorem 9.6.2 states that the \(e\leq 3v-6<3v\), which is a contradiction.
\(\blacksquare\)



<subsection xml:id="ss-GRAPH COLORING"><title>GRAPH COLORING</title><index><main>GRAPH COLORING</main></index>


\begin{center}\(\)
\end{center}


\caption{\pmb{ Figure 9.6.5}\\
A 3-coloring of Euler Island}



The map of Euler Island in Figure 9.6.5 shows that there are seven towns on the island. Suppose that a cartographer must produce a colored map in
which no two towns that share a boundary have the same color. To keep costs down, she wants to minimize the number of different colors that appear
on the map. How many colors are sufficient? For Euler Island, the answer is three. This problem motivates a more general problem.



\pmb{ The Graph Coloring Problem.} Given an undirected graph \(G = (V, E)\), find a <q>coloring function</q> <m>f</m> from <m>V</m> into a
set of colors <m>H</m> such that \(\left(v_i,v_j\right)\in E \Rightarrow  f\left(v_i\right)\neq f\left(v_j\right)\) and <m>H</m> has the smallest
possible cardinality. The cardinality of <m>H</m> is called the  chromatic number of G, \(\chi (G)\).



Notes:


<ol label=“a”>
<li><p> A coloring function onto an <m>n</m> element set is called an <m>n</m>-coloring.</p></li>
<li><p> In terms of this general problem, the chromatic number of the graph of Euler Island is three. To see that no more than three colors are needed,
we need only display a 3-coloring: \(f(1) = f(4) = f(6) = \text{blue}\), \(f(2) = \text{red}\), and \(f(3) = f(5) = f(7) = \text{white}\). This coloring
is not unique. The next smallest set of colors would be of two colors, and you should be able to convince yourself that no 2-coloring exists for
this graph.



In the mid-nineteenth century, it became clear that the typical planar graph had a chromatic number of no more than 4. At that point, mathematicians
attacked the Four-Color Conjecture, which is that if <m>G</m> is any planar graph, then its chromatic number is no more than 4. Although the conjecture
is quite easy to state, it took over 100 years, until 1976, to prove the conjecture in the affirmative.

<theorem xml:id="theorem-9.6.4: The Four-Color Theorem."><title>9.6.4: The Four-Color Theorem.</title><index><main>9.6.4: The Four-Color Theorem.</main></index><statement></statement><proof></proof></theorem>
 If <m>G</m> is a planar graph, then \(\chi (G)\leq 4\).



A proof of the Four-Color Theorem is beyond the scope of this text, but we can prove a theorem that is only 25 percent inferior.

<theorem xml:id="theorem-9.6.5: The Five-Color Theorem."><title>9.6.5: The Five-Color Theorem.</title><index><main>9.6.5: The Five-Color Theorem.</main></index><statement></statement><proof></proof></theorem>
 If <m>G</m> is a planar graph, then \(\chi (G)\leq 5\).

The number 5 is not a sharp upper bound for \(\chi (G)\) because of the Four-Color Theorem.



\pmb{ Proof}, by Induction on the Number of Vertices in the Graph:



Basis: Clearly, a graph with one vertex has a chromatic number of 1.



Induction: Assume that all planar graphs with \(n - 1\) vertices have a chromatic number of 5 or less. Let <m>G</m> be a planar graph. By Theorem
9.6.2, there exists a vertex <m>v</m> with \(\deg  v \leq 5\). Let \(G - v\) be the planar graph obtained by deleting <m>v</m> and all edges
that connect <m>v</m> to other vertices in <m>G</m>. By the induction hypothesis, \(G - v\) has a 5-coloring. Assume that the colors used
are red, white, blue, green, and yellow. 



If \(\deg  v < 5\), then we can produce a 5-coloring of <m>G</m> by selecting a color that is not used in coloring the vertices that are connected
to <m>v</m> with an edge in <m>G</m>.



If \(\deg  v = 5\), then we can use the same approach if the five vertices that are adjacent to <m>v</m> are not all colored differently. We are
now left with the possibility that \(v_1\), \(v_2\), \(v_3\), \(v_4\), and \(v_5\) are all connected to <m>v</m> by an edge and they are all colored
differently. Assume that they are colored red, white blue, yellow, and green, respectively, as in Figure 9.6.6. 


\begin{center}\(\)
\end{center}


\caption{\pmb{ Figure 9.6.6}}



Starting at \(v_1\) in \(G-v\), suppose we try to construct a path \(v_3\) that passes through only red and blue vertices.  This can either be
accomplished or it can't be accomplished. If it can't be done, consider all paths that start at \(v_1\), and go through only red and blue vertices.
If we exchange the colors of the vertices in these paths, including \(v_1\) we still have a 5-coloring of \(G - v\). Since \(v_1\) is now blue, we
can color the central vertex, <m>v</m>, red.



Finally, suppose that \(v_1\) is connected to \(v_3\) using only red and blue vertices. Then a path from \(v_{1 }\)to \(v_3\) by using red and blue
vertices followed by the edges \(\left(v_3,v\right)\) and \(\left(v,v_1\right)\) completes a circuit that either encloses \(v_2\) or encloses \(v_4\)
and \(v_5\) . Therefore, no path from \(v_2\) to \(v_4\) exists using only white and yellow vertices. We can then repeat the same process as in the
previous paragraph with \(v_2\) and \(v_4\) , which will allow us to color v white. \(\blacksquare\)

<definition xml:id="def- Bipartite Graph."><title> Bipartite Graph.</title><index><main> Bipartite Graph.</main></index><notation><usage></usage><description></description></notation><statement><p></p></statement></definition>

 A bipartite graph is a graph that has a 2-coloring. Equivalently, a graph is bipartite if its vertices
can be partitioned into two nonempty subsets so that no edge connects a vertices from the same from each subset.

<example xml:id="ex-9.6.3."><title>9.6.3.</title><p></p></example>

<ol label=“a”>
<li><p> The graph of the Three Utilities Puzzle is bipartite. The vertices are partitioned into the utilities and the homes. Of course a 2-coloring of
the graph is to color the utilities red and the homes blue.

(b) For \(n\geq 1\), the <m>n</m>-cube is bipartite. A coloring would be to color all strings with an even number of 1's red and the strings with
an odd number of 1's blue. By the definition of the <m>n</m>-cube, two strings that have the same color couldn't be connected since they would
need to differ in at least two positions.

(c) Let <m>V</m> be a set of 64 vertices, one for each square on a chess board. We can index the elements of <m>V</m> by

 <m>\quad \quad</m>\(v_{i j}\) = the square on the row <m>i</m>, column <m>j</m>. 

Connect vertices in <m>V</m> according to whether or not you can move a knight from one square to another. Using our indexing of <m>V</m>,

<m>\quad \quad</m>\(\left(v_{i j}, v_{k l}\right)\in  E\text{ if and only if      }
\begin{array}{c}
 |i-k|+|j-l|=3 \\
 \text{and} |i-k|\cdot |j-l|=2 \\
\end{array}\)

\((V, E)\) is a bipartite graph. The usual coloring of a chessboard is valid 2-coloring.



How can you recognize whether a graph is bipartite? Unlike planarity, there is a nice equivalent condition for a graph to be bipartite.



<theorem xml:id="theorem-9.6.6."><title>9.6.6.</title><index><main>9.6.6.</main></index><statement></statement><proof></proof></theorem>
 An undirected graph is bipartite if and only if it has no circuit of odd length.



Proof. (\(\Rightarrow\)) Let \(G = (V, E)\) be a bipartite graph that is partitioned into two sets,  R(ed) and  B(lue) that define
a 2-coloring. Consider any circuit in <m>V</m>. If we specify a direction in the circuit and define  f on the vertices of the circuit
by 



<m>\quad \quad</m>\(f(u) = \text{the} \text{next} \text{vertex} \text{in} \text{the} \text{circuit} \text{after} v\). 



Note that <m>f</m> is a bijection. Hence the number of red vertices in the circuit equals the number of blue vertices, and so the length of the
circuit must be even. 



(\(\Longleftarrow\)) Assume that <m>G</m> has no circuit of odd length. For each component of <m>G</m>, select any vertex <m>w</m> and color
it red. Then for every other vertex <m>v</m> in the component, find the path of shortest distance from <m>w</m> to <m>v</m>. If the length
of the path is odd, color v blue, and if it is even, color <m>v</m> red. We claim that this method defines a 2-coloring of <m>G</m>. Suppose
that it does not define a 2-coloring. Then let \(v_a\) and \(v_b\) be two vertices with identical colors that are connected with an edge. By the
way that we colored <m>G</m>, neither \(v_a\) nor \(v_{b }\) could equal  w.  We can now construct a circuit with an odd length
in <m>G</m>. First, we start at <m>w</m> and follow the shortest path to \(v_a\) . Then follow the edge \(\left(v_a,v_b\right)\), and finally,
follow the reverse of a shortest path from <m>w</m> to \(v_b\). Since \(v_a\) and \(v_b\) have the same color, the first and third segments of
this circuit have lengths that are both odd or even, and the sum of their lengths must be even. The addition of the single edge \(\left(v_a,v_b\right)\)
shows us that this circuit has an odd length. This contradicts our premise. \(\blacksquare\)

Note: An efficient algorithm for finding a 2-coloring of a graph can be designed using the method that is used in the second part of the proof above.


<exercises xml:id="exercises-9-6">
<title>Exercises for Section 9.6</title>
<exercisegroup>
<introduction><p>A Exercises</p></introduction>


<exercise number="1"><statement><p> Apply Theorem 9.6.2 to prove that once <m>n</m> gets to a certain size, a \(K_n\) is nonplanar. What is the largest complete planar graph?</p></statement></exercise>
<exercise number="2"><statement><p> Can you apply Theorem 9.6.2 to prove that the Three Utilities Puzzle can't be solved?</p></statement></exercise>
<exercise number="3"><statement> What are the chromatic numbers of the following graphs?

\begin{doublespace}
\noindent\(\)
\end{doublespace}</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="4"><statement><p> Prove that if an undirected graph has a subgraph that is a \(K_3\) it then its chromatic number is at least 3.</p></statement></exercise>
<exercise number="5"><statement><p> What is \(\chi \left(K_n\right)\), \(n\geq 1\)?</p></statement></exercise>
<exercise number="6"><statement> What is the chromatic number of the United States? </p></statement></exercise>


</exercisegroup>
<exercisegroup>
<introduction><p>B Exercises</p></introduction>
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="7"><statement><p> Complete the proof of Theorem 9.6.1.</p></statement></exercise>
<exercise number="8"><statement><p> Use the outline of a proof of Theorem 9.6.2 to write a complete proof. Be sure to point out where the premise \(v\geq 3\) is essential.</p></statement></exercise>
<exercise number="9"><statement><p> Let \(G = (V,E)\) with \(|V|\geq 11\), and let <m>U</m> be the set of all undirected edges between distinct vertices in <m>V</m>.  Prove
that either <m>G</m> or \(G' = \left(V,E^c\right)\) is nonplanar.</p></statement></exercise>
<exercise number="10"><statement><p> Design an algorithm to determine whether a graph is bipartite.</p></statement></exercise>
<exercise number="11"><statement><p> Prove that a bipartite graph with an odd number of vertices greater than or equal to 3 has no Hamiltonian circuit.</p></statement></exercise>


</exercisegroup>
<exercisegroup>
<introduction><p>C Exercises</p></introduction>
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="12"><statement><p> Prove that any graph with a finite number of vertices can be drawn in three dimensions so that no edges intersect.</p></statement></exercise>
<exercise number="13"><statement> Suppose you had to color the edges of an undirected graph so that for each vertex, the edges that it is connected to have different colors.
How can this problem be transformed into a vertex coloring problem?</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="14"><statement> (a) Suppose the edges of a \(K_6\) are colored either red or blue. Prove that there will be either a $\texttt{"}$red \(K_3\)<q> (a subset
of the vertex set with three vertices connected by red edges) or a </q>blue \(K_3\).$\texttt{"}$ </p></li>
<li><p> Suppose six people are selected at random. Prove that either there exists a subset of three of them with the property that any two people in
the subset can communicate in a common language, or there exist three people, no two of whom can communicate in a common language.


<exercise number="1"><statement> Determine which two of the graphs below are isomorphic and give an explicit isomorphism between those two graphs.

\begin{doublespace}
\noindent\(\)
\end{doublespace}</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="2"><statement> Teams 1, 2, 3, and 4 compete in a round-robin tournament. Draw a round-robin tournament graph that represents one of the possible out
comes of the tournament. In terms of your graph, what was the outcome of the tournament (in wins and losses)?</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="3"><statement> Let \(G=(V,E)\) be an undirected graph. An  independent set, <m>W</m>, is a subset of <m>V</m> having the property that no two
vertices in <m>W</m> are connected by an edge in <m>E</m>. That is,



<m>\quad \quad</m>\(v,w\in W\Rightarrow \{v,w\}\notin E\).



Finding a maximal independent set (an independent set that is as large as possible) is often of interest.


<ol label=“a”>
<li><p> Find a maximal independent set in the graph of Figure 9.1.2.</p></li>
<li><p> Prove that if <m>W</m> is a maximal independent set in <m>G</m>, then every vertex in <m>G</m> is connected by an edge to at least one
vertex in <m>W</m>.</p></li>
<li><p> How large can a maximal independent set in a \(K_n\) be?</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="4"><statement> Let \(S=\{1,2,\ldots ,n\}\) be a set of <m>n</m> cities. Define a matrix \(A=\left[a_{\text{ij}}\right]\) of order \(n\times n
\text{by} a_{\text{ij}}=0 \text{if} i=j\); otherwise \(a_{\text{ij}}\) is the  number of distinct ways of traveling directly
from city  i to city <m>j</m> by car, without visiting any other cities belonging to <m>S</m> en route.



In the following diagram, the points represent five cities, \(1,2,3,4,\) and 5, and a line is drawn between two cities and labeled with a positive
integer giving the number of  direct routes (by car) between the respective cities.

\begin{doublespace}
\noindent\(\)
\end{doublespace}


<ol label=“a”>
<li><p> Determine the \(5\times 5\) matrix <m>A</m> going with the above diagram.</p></li>
<li><p> Calculate \(A^2\).</p></li>
<li><p> Interpret the meaning of the entries in \(A^2\), both for the result in part b, and for the general set \(S=\{1,2,\ldots ,n\}\).</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="5"><statement> An undirected graph can be used to model a map of states or countries, where there is a vertex for each country and an edge between two vertices
if the two countries share a boundary. For example, the undirected graph of Central America (mainland only) would have eight vertices. $\{$Honduras,
Nicaragua$\}$ would be an edge of the graph, but $\{$Mexico, Nicaragua$\}$ would not be an edge.


\begin{center}\(\)
\end{center}


<ol label=“a”>
<li><p> Draw the graph of Central America.</p></li>
<li><p> Find a path from Mexico to Panama.</p></li>
<li><p> What significance would this path have if you intended to drive from Mexico to Panama?</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="6"><statement> Show that the graph of the states of Washington, Oregon, Idaho, Montana, Wyoming, and Colorado is isomorphic to the graph of
New England.</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="7"><statement> The outdegree of a vertex in a directed graph is the number of vertices in the graph that start at that vertex, and the indegree of the vertex
is the number of vertices in the graph that terminate at that vertex. A vertex <m>v</m> in a tournament graph is a source if the indegree of that
vertex is zero. A sink is a vertex in a tournament graph that has outdegree of zero.


<ol label=“a”>
<li><p> Prove that a round-robin tournament graph can have at most one source and at most one sink. Interpret these facts in terms of the results
of the tournament.</p></li>
<li><p> What is the outdegree of a source in a round-robin tournament graph? What is the indegree of a sink in a round-robin tournament graph?</p></li>
<li><p> Let \(G=(V,E)\) be a round-robin tournament graph with \(\left| V\right| >2\). If \(p \text{is} \text{G has a sink,}\) and \(q \text{is} \text{G
has a source,}\) prove that any one of the propositions \(\neg p\land \neg q, \neg p\land q, p\land \neg q \text{and} p\land q\) could be true.


\subsubsection{
\subsection{Section 9.2}}</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="8"><statement> Let \(G=(V,E)\) be a round-robin tournament graph with \(\left| V\right| =n\). If <m>M</m> is the matrix of <m>G</m>,


<ol label=“a”>
<li><p> For \(i=1,2,\ldots ,n\), explain why the number of 1's in column  i of <m>M</m> plus the number of 1s in row \(i\) is always equal
to \(n-1\).</p></li>
<li><p> How many 1s are there in <m>M</m>?


\subsubsection{
\subsection{Section 9.3}}</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="9"><statement> Use the broadcasting algorithm to determine a shortest path from vertex <m>a</m> to vertex <m>i</m> in the following graph. List the
depth sets.

\begin{doublespace}
\noindent\(\)
\end{doublespace}</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="10"><statement> In a breadth-first (broadcasting) search for a path from vertex <m>A</m> to vertex <m>J</m>, what would the depth sets \(\left(D_1,D_2,\ldots
\right)\) be?

\begin{doublespace}
\noindent\(\)
\end{doublespace}


\subsubsection{
\subsection{Section 9.4}}



Definition: Randomly Eulerian. \textit{ Graph G is randomly Eulerian from vertex v if every path in G that initiates at v and uses edges at random
is a Eulerian circuit.}</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="11"><statement> Give examples of undirected graphs that are randomly Eulerian from none, one, two, or all vertices. It can be proven that no graph is randomly
Eulerian from more than two vertices unless it is randomly Eulerian from all vertices.</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="12"><statement><p> Prove that <m>G</m> is randomly Eulerian from <m>v</m> if and only if every circuit in <m>G</m> contains <m>v</m>.</p></statement></exercise>
<exercise number="13"><statement> Ore's Theorem states that if \(G=(V,E)\) is an undirected graph with \(\left| V\right| =n\geqslant 3\) such that \(\{v,w\}\notin E\Rightarrow
\text{$\deg $} u+\text{$\deg $} v\geqslant n,\) then <m>G</m> has a Hamiltonian circuit. Prove Ore's Theorem given the following
out line.



Proof by contradiction:


<ol label=“a”>
<li><p> Add edges to <m>E</m> so that  G still has no Hamiltonian circuit, but so that the addition of any other edge does produce a Hamiltonian
circuit. Now select any \(\{v,w\}\notin E\). There must be a path in <m>G</m>:



\(v=\left(v_1,v_2,\ldots ,v_n\right)=w\).</p></li>
<li><p> Prove that for \(2\leqslant i\leqslant n, \left\{v_1,v_i\right\}\in E\Rightarrow \left\{v_{i-1},v_n\right\}\notin E.\)</p></li>
<li><p> Conclude that \(\text{$\deg $} v+\text{$\deg $} w<n\).


\subsubsection{
\subsection{Section 9.5}}</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="14"><statement> Given:

\begin{doublespace}
\noindent\(\)
\end{doublespace}


<ol label=“a”>
<li><p> Determine the optimal path from the vertex <m>a</m> to the vertex <m>z</m>.</p></li>
<li><p> Use the broadcasting algorithm to find a path from <m>a</m> to <m>z</m>.</p></li>
<li><p> Find the <q>costs</q> of both paths and discuss whether the algorithm in part b gives a <q>good result.</q></statement></exercise>
<exercise number="15"><statement> Consider the network

\begin{doublespace}
\noindent\(\)
\end{doublespace}



We start with a flow  f on this network partially defined by \(f(s,c)=f(s,b)=f(s,a)=1 \text{and} f(d,a)=0\).


<ol label=“a”>
<li><p> Define  f for each of the other edges in this network so as to achieve a flow.</p></li>
<li><p> Assume that the maximum capacity of each edge is 2. Determine a flow augmenting path with respect to the flow given in part a. (Use the Ford
and Fulkerson Algorithm.)</p></li>
<li><p> Is the flow obtained in part b a maximal flow? Explain.</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="16"><statement> Find a maximal flow for the following network:

\begin{doublespace}
\noindent\(\)
\end{doublespace}</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="17"><statement> (a) Given the mileage chart below, what is the closest neighbor circuit starting at city <m>A</m>?



\(\begin{array}{ccccccc}
   &amp; A &amp; B &amp; C &amp; D &amp; E &amp; F \\
 A &amp; \_ &amp; 34 &amp; 50 &amp; 12 &amp; 51 &amp; 37 \\
 B &amp; 34 &amp; \_ &amp; 40 &amp; 27 &amp; 70 &amp; 60 \\
 C &amp; 50 &amp; 40 &amp; \_ &amp; 30 &amp; 33 &amp; 41 \\
 D &amp; 12 &amp; 27 &amp; 30 &amp; \_ &amp; 39 &amp; 20 \\
 E &amp; 51 &amp; 70 &amp; 33 &amp; 39 &amp; \_ &amp; 15 \\
 F &amp; 37 &amp; 60 &amp; 41 &amp; 20 &amp; 15 &amp; \_ \\
\end{array}\)</p></li>
<li><p> Suppose it takes \((k-1)\) seconds to determine which of <m>k</m> cities is closest to any given city. Estimate how long it would take to
find a closest neighbor circuit through <m>n</m> cities.


\subsubsection{
\subsection{Section 9.6}}</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="18"><statement><p> Draw three connected graphs, \(G_2,G_3,\text{and} G_4\), with four vertices, each having chromatic numbers \(2,3, \text{and} 4\left(i.e. c\left(G_i\right)=i\right.\).</p></statement></exercise>
<exercise number="19"><statement> (a) Prove that although a \(K_5\) is not planar, it can be drawn on a  torus (a doughnut-shaped surface).



 (b) Can the Three Utilities Puzzle be solved on a torus?</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="20"><statement> Draw examples of the following graphs, if possible. Clearly indicate which of the graphs are impossible and why they are impossible. You may
cite any theorem that justifies your claim.


<ol label=“a”>
<li><p> An undirected Hamiltonian graph that is not Eulerian. Explain why your graph is not Eulerian.</p></li>
<li><p> A bipartite Hamiltonian graph with five vertices.</p></li>
<li><p> A round-robin tournament graph with four vertices.</p></li>
<li><p> A connected planar graph with four vertices, three regions, and six edges.</p></li>
<li><p> An undirected graph with chromatic number five.

\end{document}
