%% AMS-LaTeX Created with the Wolfram Language : www.wolfram.com

\documentclass{article}
\usepackage{amsmath, amssymb, graphics, setspace}

\newcommand{\mathsym}[1]{{}}
\newcommand{\unicode}[1]{{}}

\newcounter{mathematicapage}
\begin{document}


\section{
\section{SUPPLEMENTARY EXERCISES FOR CHAPTER 9}}


\subsubsection{
\subsection{Section 9.1}}



1. Determine which two of the graphs below are isomorphic and give an explicit isomorphism between those two graphs.

\begin{doublespace}
\noindent\(\)
\end{doublespace}



2. { }Teams 1, 2, 3, and 4 compete in a round-robin tournament. Draw a round-robin tournament graph that represents one of the possible out$\unicode{00ad}$
comes of the tournament. In terms of your graph, what was the outcome of the tournament (in wins and losses)?



3. { }Let \(G=(V,E)\) be an undirected graph. An\textit{  independent set}, \textit{ W}, is a subset of \textit{ V} having the property that no two
vertices in \textit{ W} are connected by an edge in \textit{ E}. That is,



$\quad \quad $\(v,w\in W\Rightarrow \{v,w\}\notin E\).



Finding a maximal independent set (an independent set that is as large as possible) is often of interest.



(a) { }Find a maximal independent set in the graph of Figure 9.1.2.



(b) Prove that if \textit{ W} is a maximal independent set in \textit{ G}, then every vertex in \textit{ G} is connected by an edge to at least one
vertex in \textit{ W}.



(c) { }How large can a maximal independent set in a \(K_n\) be?



4. { }Let \(S=\{1,2,\ldots ,n\}\) be a set of \textit{ n} cities. Define a matrix \(A=\left[a_{\text{\textit{ij}}}\right]\) of order \(n\times n
\text{by} a_{\text{\textit{ij}}}=0 \text{if} i=j\); otherwise \(a_{\text{\textit{ij}}}\) is the \textit{ number} of distinct ways of traveling directly
from city\textit{  i} to city \textit{ j} by car, without visiting any other cities belonging to \textit{ S} en route.



In the following diagram, the points represent five cities, \(1,2,3,4,\) and 5, and a line is drawn between two cities and labeled with a positive
integer giving the number of \textit{ direct} routes (by car) between the re$\unicode{00ad}$spective cities.

\begin{doublespace}
\noindent\(\)
\end{doublespace}



(a) { }Determine the \(5\times 5\) matrix \textit{ A} going with the above diagram.



(b) { }Calculate \(A^2\).



(c) { }Interpret the meaning of the entries in \(A^2\), both for the result in part b, and for the general set \(S=\{1,2,\ldots ,n\}\).



5. An undirected graph can be used to model a map of states or countries, where there is a vertex for each country and an edge between two vertices
if the two countries share a boundary. For example, the undirected graph of Central America (mainland only) would have eight vertices. $\{$Honduras,
Nicaragua$\}$ would be an edge of the graph, but $\{$Mexico, Nicaragua$\}$ would not be an edge.


\begin{center}\(\)
\end{center}



(a) { }Draw the graph of Central America.



(b) { }Find a path from Mexico to Panama.



(c) What significance would this path have if you intended to drive from Mexico to Panama?



6. { }Show that the graph of the states of Washington, Oregon, Idaho, Mon$\unicode{00ad}$tana, Wyoming, and Colorado is isomorphic to the graph of
New England.



7. { }The outdegree of a vertex in a directed graph is the number of vertices in the graph that start at that vertex, and the indegree of the vertex
is the number of vertices in the graph that terminate at that vertex. A vertex \textit{ v} in a tournament graph is a source if the indegree of that
vertex is zero. A sink is a vertex in a tournament graph that has outdegree of zero.



(a) { }Prove that a round-robin tournament graph can have at most one source and at most one sink. Interpret these facts in terms of the results
of the tournament.



(b) { }What is the outdegree of a source in a round-robin tournament graph? What is the indegree of a sink in a round-robin tournament graph?



(c) { }Let \(G=(V,E)\) be a round-robin tournament graph with \(\left| V\right| >2\). If \(p \text{is} \text{G has a sink,}\) and \(q \text{is} \text{G
has a source,}\) prove that any one of the propositions \(\neg p\land \neg q, \neg p\land q, p\land \neg q \text{and} p\land q\) could be true.


\subsubsection{
\subsection{Section 9.2}}



8. { }Let \(G=(V,E)\) be a round-robin tournament graph with \(\left| V\right| =n\). If \textit{ M} is the matrix of \textit{ G},



(a) { }For \(i=1,2,\ldots ,n\), explain why the number of 1's in column \textit{ i }of \textit{ M} plus the number of 1s in row \(i\) is always equal
to \(n-1\).



(b) How many 1s are there in \textit{ M}?


\subsubsection{
\subsection{Section 9.3}}



9. { }Use the broadcasting algorithm to determine a shortest path from vertex \textit{ a} to vertex \textit{ i} in the following graph. List the
depth sets.

\begin{doublespace}
\noindent\(\)
\end{doublespace}



10. In a breadth-first (broadcasting) search for a path from vertex \textit{ A} to vertex \textit{ J}, what would the depth sets \(\left(D_1,D_2,\ldots
\right)\) be?

\begin{doublespace}
\noindent\(\)
\end{doublespace}


\subsubsection{
\subsection{Section 9.4}}



Definition: Randomly Eulerian. \textit{ Graph G is randomly Eulerian from vertex v if every path in G that initiates at v and uses edges at random
is a Eulerian circuit.}



11. { }Give examples of undirected graphs that are randomly Eulerian from none, one, two, or all vertices. It can be proven that no graph is randomly
Eulerian from more than two vertices unless it is randomly Eulerian from all vertices.



12. { }Prove that \textit{ G} is randomly Eulerian from \textit{ v} if and only if every circuit in \textit{ G} contains \textit{ v}.



13. { }Ore's Theorem states that if \(G=(V,E)\) is an undirected graph with \(\left| V\right| =n\geqslant 3\) such that \(\{v,w\}\notin E\Rightarrow
\text{\textit{$\deg $}} u+\text{\textit{$\deg $}} v\geqslant n,\) then \textit{ G} has a Hamiltonian circuit. Prove Ore's Theorem given the following
out$\unicode{00ad}$ line.



Proof by contradiction:



(a) { }Add edges to \textit{ E} so that \textit{ G }still has no Hamiltonian circuit, but so that the addition of any other edge does produce a Hamiltonian
circuit. Now select any \(\{v,w\}\notin E\). There must be a path in \textit{ G}:



\(v=\left(v_1,v_2,\ldots ,v_n\right)=w\).



(b) Prove that for \(2\leqslant i\leqslant n, \left\{v_1,v_i\right\}\in E\Rightarrow \left\{v_{i-1},v_n\right\}\notin E.\)



(c) Conclude that \(\text{\textit{$\deg $}} v+\text{\textit{$\deg $}} w<n\).


\subsubsection{
\subsection{Section 9.5}}



14. { }Given:

\begin{doublespace}
\noindent\(\)
\end{doublespace}



(a) { }Determine the optimal path from the vertex \textit{ a} to the vertex \textit{ z}.



(b) { }Use the broadcasting algorithm to find a path from \textit{ a} to \textit{ z}.



(c) { }Find the {``}costs{''} of both paths and discuss whether the algorithm in part b gives a {``}good result.{''}



15. { }Consider the network

\begin{doublespace}
\noindent\(\)
\end{doublespace}



We start with a flow \textit{ f }on this network partially defined by \(f(s,c)=f(s,b)=f(s,a)=1 \text{and} f(d,a)=0\).



(a) { }Define \textit{ f }for each of the other edges in this network so as to achieve a flow.



(b) { }Assume that the maximum capacity of each edge is 2. Determine a flow augmenting path with respect to the flow given in part a. (Use the Ford
and Fulkerson Algorithm.)



(c) { }Is the flow obtained in part b a maximal flow? Explain.



16. Find a maximal flow for the following network:

\begin{doublespace}
\noindent\(\)
\end{doublespace}



17. (a) Given the mileage chart below, what is the closest neighbor circuit starting at city \textit{ A}?



\(\begin{array}{ccccccc}
   & A & B & C & D & E & F \\
 A & \_ & 34 & 50 & 12 & 51 & 37 \\
 B & 34 & \_ & 40 & 27 & 70 & 60 \\
 C & 50 & 40 & \_ & 30 & 33 & 41 \\
 D & 12 & 27 & 30 & \_ & 39 & 20 \\
 E & 51 & 70 & 33 & 39 & \_ & 15 \\
 F & 37 & 60 & 41 & 20 & 15 & \_ \\
\end{array}\)



(b) Suppose it takes \((k-1)\) seconds to determine which of \textit{ k} cities is closest to any given city. Estimate how long it would take to
find a closest neighbor circuit through \textit{ n} cities.


\subsubsection{
\subsection{Section 9.6}}



18. { }Draw three connected graphs, \(G_2,G_3,\text{and} G_4\), with four vertices, each having chromatic numbers \(2,3, \text{and} 4\left(i.e. c\left(G_i\right)=i\right.\).



19. (a) Prove that although a \(K_5\) is not planar, it can be drawn on a \textit{ torus} (a doughnut-shaped surface).



 (b) Can the Three Utilities Puzzle be solved on a torus?



20. { }Draw examples of the following graphs, if possible. Clearly indicate which of the graphs are impossible and why they are impossible. You may
cite any theorem that justifies your claim.



(a) An undirected Hamiltonian graph that is not Eulerian. Explain why your graph is not Eulerian.



(b) { }A bipartite Hamiltonian graph with five vertices.



(c) { }A round-robin tournament graph with four vertices.



(d) { }A connected planar graph with four vertices, three regions, and six edges.



(e) { }An undirected graph with chromatic number five.

\end{document}
