<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!-- This file is part of the book                 -->
<!--                                               -->
<!--   Applied Discrete Structures   -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- Ken Levasseur and Al Doerr     -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.  -->

<frontmatter xml:id="index-ads" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<bibinfo>
	<titlepage>

		<author>
			<personname>Al Doerr</personname>
			<department>Department of Mathematics and Statistics</department>
			<institution>University of Massachusetts Lowell</institution>
			<email></email>
		</author>
		<author>
			<personname>Ken Levasseur</personname>
			<department>Department of Mathematics and Statistics</department>
			<institution>University of Massachusetts Lowell</institution>
			<email>kenneth_levasseur@uml.edu</email>
		</author>

 
        <date><today /></date>


	</titlepage>
	
	<colophon><colophon-items/></colophon>
	
		<edition>3rd Edition - version 11</edition>
		<website>
			<url>http://discretemath.org</url>
    	</website>


		<copyright>
			<year>2024</year>
			<holder>Al Doerr, Ken Levasseur</holder>
			<minilicense>Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 United States License. 2011-2017</minilicense>
<!-- 
			<creativecommons BY="yes" NC="yes" SA="yes" version="4.0"/>
 -->
			<shortlicense>Applied Discrete Structures by Alan Doerr and Kenneth Levasseur is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 United States License. You are free to Share: copy and redistribute the material in any medium or format; Adapt: remix, transform, and build upon the material. You may not use the material for commercial purposes.  The licensor cannot revoke these freedoms as long as you follow the license terms.
			</shortlicense>
		</copyright>
		
		</bibinfo>
	
<dedication>
<title>Dedication</title>
<p>To our families</p>
<p>Donna, Christopher, Melissa, and Patrick Doerr</p>
<p>Karen, Joseph, Kathryn, and Matthew Levasseur</p>
</dedication>
	<!-- Accepted order: acknowledgements, forewords, prefaces -->

<xi:include href="./acknowledgement.xml" />


<preface xml:id="ads-preface"><title>Preface</title>
<p component="im">This is the instructors' version of the text.  Please don't distribute to students.</p>
<p><em>Applied Discrete Structures</em> is designed for use in a university course in discrete mathematics spanning up to two semesters.   Its original design was for computer science majors to be introduced to the mathematical topics that are useful in computer science.   It can also serve the same purpose for mathematics majors, providing a first exposure to many essential topics.</p>
<p>We embarked on this open-source project in 2010, twenty-one years after the publication of the 2nd edition of <em>Applied Discrete Structures for Computer Science</em> in 1989.   We had signed a contract for the second edition with Science Research Associates in 1988 but by the time the book was ready to print, SRA had been sold to MacMillan. Soon after, the rights had been passed on to Pearson Education, Inc. In 2010, the long-term future of printed textbooks was uncertain. In the meantime, textbook prices (both printed and e-books) had increased and a growing open source textbook movement had started. One of our objectives in revisiting this text is to make it available to our students in an affordable format. In its original form, the text was peer-reviewed and was adopted for use at several universities throughout the country. For this reason, we see <em>Applied Discrete Structures</em> as not only an inexpensive alternative, but a high quality alternative.</p>
<p>The current version of <em>Applied Discrete Structures</em> has been developed using <em>PreTeXt</em>, a lightweight XML application for authors of scientific articles, textbooks and monographs initiated by Rob Beezer, U. of Puget Sound.  When the PreTeXt project was launched, it was the natural next step.  The features of PreTeXt make it far more readable, with easy production of web, pdf and print formats. </p>
<p>The current computing landscape is very different from the 1980's and this accounts for the most significant changes in the text. One of the most common programming languages of the 1980's was Pascal.  We used it to illustrate many of the concepts in the text.  Although it isn't totally dead, Pascal is far from the mainstream of computing in the 21st century.  The open source software movement was just starting in the late 1980's and in 2005, the first version of Sage (later renamed SageMath), an open-source computer algebra system, was first released. In Applied Discrete Structures we have replaced "Pascal Notes" with "SageMath Notes."</p>

<p>Many of the concepts introduced in this text are illustrated using SageMath code.  SageMath (<url href="http://sagemath.org" visual="sagemath.org">sagemath.org</url>) is a free, open source, software system for advanced mathematics.  Sage can be used either on your own computer, a local server, or on SageMathCloud (<url href="https://cloud.sagemath.com" visual="">https://cloud.sagemath.com</url>). </p>

			<attribution>
			<line>Ken Levasseur</line>
			<line>Lowell, MA</line>
			</attribution>
</preface>

</frontmatter>
