<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!-- This file is part of the book                 -->
<!--                                               -->
<!--   Applied Discrete Structures   -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- Ken Levasseur and Al Doerr     -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.  -->

<frontmatter xml:id="index" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

	<titlepage>

		<author>
			<personname>Al Doerr</personname>
			<department>Department of Mathematical Sciences</department>
			<institution>University of Massachusetts Lowell</institution>
			<email></email>
		</author>
		<author>
			<personname>Ken Levasseur</personname>
			<department>Department of Mathematical Sciences</department>
			<institution>University of Massachusetts Lowell</institution>
			<email>kenneth_levasseur@uml.edu</email>
		</author>

		<date>September, 2016</date>


	</titlepage>

	<colophon>

		<copyright>
			<year>2016</year>
			<holder>Al Doerr, Ken Levasseur</holder>
			<minilicense>Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 United States License. 2011-2016</minilicense>
<!-- 
			<creativecommons BY="yes" NC="yes" SA="yes" version="4.0"/>
 -->
			<shortlicense>Applied Discrete Structures by Alan Doerr and Kenneth Levasseur is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 United States License. You are free to Share: copy and redistribute the material in any medium or format; Adapt: remix, transform, and build upon the material. You may not use the material for commercial purposes.  The licensor cannot revoke these freedoms as long as you follow the license terms.
			</shortlicense>
		</copyright>

	</colophon>

	<!-- Accepted order: acknowledgements, forewords, prefaces -->

	<acknowledgement>

		<p>We would like to acknowledge the following instructors for their helpful comments and suggestions. </p>
<list>
		<ul>
			<li><p>Tibor Beke, UMass Lowell</p></li>
			<li><p>Alex DeCourcy, UMass Lowell</p></li>
			<li><p>Vince DiChiacchio</p></li>
			<li><p>Dan Klain, UMass Lowell</p></li>
			<li><p>Ravi Montenegro, UMass Lowell</p></li>
			<li><p>Tony Penta, UMass Lowell</p></li>
			<li><p>Jim Propp, UMass Lowell</p></li>
			<li><p>Students at Luzurne County Community College (PA)</p></li>
		</ul>
</list>
<p>Many students have provided feedback and pointed out typos in several editions of this book.  Among them are:</p>		

<list>
		<ul>
			<li><p>Sam Bouchard</p></li>
			<li><p>Sam Chambers</p></li>
			<li><p>Anthony Gaeta</p></li>
			<li><p>William Jozefczyk</p></li>
			<li><p>Andrew Magee</p></li>
			<li><p>Paola Pevzner</p></li>
			<li><p>Anh Vo</p></li>
			<li><p>Several students at Luzurne County Community College (PA)</p></li>
		</ul>
</list>

		<p>I would like to thank Rob Beezer, David Farmer and other participants on the <url href="https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups#!forum/mathbook-xml-support">mathbook-xml-support group</url> for their guidance and work on MathBook XML.  Thanks to the Pedagogy Subcommittee of the UMass Lowell Transformational Education Committee for their financial assistance in helping getting this project started.</p>


	</acknowledgement>

	<preface>
<p>This version of <em>Applied Discrete Structures</em> is being developed using <em>Mathbook XML</em>, A lightweight XML application for authors of scientific articles, textbooks and monographs initiated by Rob Beezer, U. of Puget Sound.  </p>


<p><em> What a difference seven years make!</em>We embarked on this open-source project in 2010.   The choice of Mathematica for "source code" was based on the speed with which we could do the conversion.  However, the format was not ideal, with no viable web version available.  The project has been well-received in spite of these issues.  Validation through the listing of this project on the American Institute of Mathematics has been very helpful.  When the MBX project was launched, it was the natural next step.  The features of MBX make it far more readable than our first versions, with web, pdf and print copies being far more readable.</p>
<p>Twenty-one years after the publication of the 2nd edition of Applied Discrete Structures for Computer Science, in 1989 the publishing and computing landscape had both changed dramatically. We signed a contract for the second edition with Science Research Associates in 1988 but by the time the book was ready to print, SRA had been sold to MacMillan. Soon after, the rights had been passed on to Pearson Education, Inc. In 2010, the long-term future of printed textbooks is uncertain. In the meantime, textbook prices (both printed and e-books) have increased and a growing open source textbook market movement has started. One of our objectives in revisiting this text is to make it available to our students in an affordable format. In its original form, the text was peer-reviewed and was adopted for use at several universities throughout the country. For this reason, we see Applied Discrete Structures as not only an inexpensive alternative, but a high quality alternative.</p>
<p>As indicated above the computing landscape is very different from the 1980's and accounts for the most significant changes in the text. One of the most common programming languages of the 1980's, Pascal; and we used it to illustrate many of the concepts in the text. Although it isn't totally dead, Pascal is far from the mainstream of computing in the 21st century. In 1989, Mathematica had been out for less than a year — now a major force in scientific computing. The open source software movement also started in the 1980's and in 2005, the first version of Sage, an open-source alternative to Mathematica was first released. In Applied Discrete Structures we have replaced "Pascal Notes" with "Mathematica Notes" and "Sage Notes." Finally, 1989 was the year that World Wide Web was invented by Tim Berners-Lee. There wasn't a single www in the 2nd edition. In this version, we intend to make use of extensive web resources, including video demonstrations.</p>
<p>We would like to thank Tony Penta, Sitansu Mittra, and Dan Klain for using the preliminary versions of Applied Discrete Structures. The corrections and input they provided was appreciated.</p>
<p>
<em>Preface to Applied Discrete Structures for Computer Science, 2nd Ed. (1989)</em> 
We feel proud and fortunate that most authorities, including MAA and ACM, have settled on a discrete mathematics syllabus that is virtually identical to the contents of the first edition of Applied Discrete Structures for Computer Science. For that reason, very few topical changes needed to be made in this new edition, and the order of topics is almost unchanged. The main change is the addition of a large number of exercises at all levels. We have "fine-tuned" the contents by expanding the preliminary coverage of sets and combinatorics, and we have added a discussion of binary integer representation. We have also added an introduction including several examples, to provide motivation for those students who may find it reassuring to know that mathematics has "real" applications. "Appendix B—Introduction to Algorithms," has also been added to make the text more self-contained.</p>
<p><em>How This Book Will Help Students</em>
In writing this book, care was taken to use language and examples that gradually wean students from a simpleminded mechanical approach and move them toward mathematical maturity. We also recognize that many students who hesitate to ask for help from an instructor need a readable text, and we have tried to anticipate the questions that go unasked.
The wide range of examples in the text are meant to augment the "favorite examples" that most instructors have for teaching the topics in discrete mathematics.</p>
<p>To provide diagnostic help and encouragement, we have included solutions and/or hints to the odd-numbered exercises. These solutions include detailed answers whenever warranted and complete proofs, not just terse outlines of proofs.
Our use of standard terminology and notation makes Applied Discrete Structures for Computer Science a valuable reference book for future courses. Although many advanced books have a short review of elementary topics, they cannot be complete.</p>
<p><em>How This Book Will Help Instructors</em>
The text is divided into lecture-length sections, facilitating the organization of an instructor's presentation.
Topics are presented in such a way that students' understanding can be monitored through thought-provoking exercises. The exercises require an understanding of the topics and how they are interrelated, not just a familiarity with the key words.</p>
<p><em>How This Book Will Help the Chairperson/Coordinator</em>
The text covers the standard topics that all instructors must be aware of; therefore it is safe to adopt Applied Discrete Structures for Computer Science before an instructor has been selected.
The breadth of topics covered allows for flexibility that may be needed due to last-minute curriculum changes.</p>
<p>Since discrete mathematics is such a new course, faculty are often forced to teach the course without being completely familiar with it. An Instructor's Guide is an important feature for the new instructor. <em>An instructor's guide is not currently available for the open-source version of the project.</em></p>
<p><em>What a Difference Five Years Makes!</em>
In the last five years, much has taken place in regards to discrete mathematics. A review of these events is in order to see how they have affected the Second Edition of Applied Discrete Structures for Computer Science.
(1) Scores of discrete mathematics texts have been published. Most texts in discrete mathematics can be classified as one-semester or two- semester texts. The two-semester texts, such as Applied Discrete Structures for Computer Science, differ in that the logical prerequisites for a more thorough study of discrete mathematics are developed.
(2) Discrete mathematics has become more than just a computer science support course. Mathematics majors are being required to take it, often before calculus. Rather than reducing the significance of calculus, this recognizes that the material a student sees in a discrete mathematics/struc- tures course strengthens his or her understanding of the theoretical aspects of calculus. This is particularly important for today's students, since many high school courses in geometry stress mechanics as opposed to proofs. The typical college freshman is skill-oriented and does not have a high level of mathematical maturity. Discrete mathematics is also more typical of the higher-level courses that a mathematics major is likely to take.
(3) Authorities such as MAA, ACM, and A. Ralson have all refined their ideas of what a discrete mathematics course should be. Instead of the chaos that characterized the early '80s, we now have some agreement, namely that discrete mathematics should be a course that develops mathematical maturity.
(4) Computer science enrollments have leveled off and in some cases have declined. Some attribute this to the lay-offs that have taken place in the computer industry; but the amount of higher mathematics that is needed to advance in many areas of computer science has also discouraged many. A year of discrete mathematics is an important first step in overcoming a deficiency in mathematics.
(5) The Educational Testing Service introduced its Advanced Placement Exam in Computer Science. The suggested preparation for this exam includes many discrete mathematics topics, such as trees, graphs, and recursion. This continues the trend toward offering discrete mathematics earlier in the overall curriculum.</p>
<p><em>Acknowledgments</em>
The authors wish to thank our colleagues and students for their comments and assistance in writing and revising this text. Among those who have left their mark on this edition are Susan Assmann, Shim Berkovitz, Tony Penta, Kevin Ryan, and Richard Winslow.</p>
<p>We would also like to thank Jean Hutchings, Kathy Sullivan, and Michele Walsh for work that they did in typing this edition, and our department secretaries, Mrs. Lyn Misserville and Mrs. Danielle White, whose cooperation in numerous ways has been greatly appreciated.</p>
<p>We are grateful for the response to the first edition from the faculty and students of over seventy-five colleges and universities. We know that our second edition will be a better learning and teaching tool as a result of their useful comments and suggestions. Our special thanks to the following reviewers: David Buchthal, University of Akron; Ronald L. Davis, Millersville University; John W Kennedy, Pace University; Betty Mayfield, Hood College; Nancy Olmsted, Worcester State College; and Pradip Shrimani, Southern Illinois University. Finally, it has been a pleasure to work with Nancy Osman, our acquisitions editor, David Morrow, our development editor, and the entire staff at SRA.</p>


<p>Sage (<url href="http://sagemath.org">sagemath.org</url>) is a free, open source, software system for advanced mathematics.  Sage can be used either on your own computer, a local server, or on SageMathCloud (<url href="https://cloud.sagemath.com">https://cloud.sagemath.com</url>). </p>

			<attribution>
			<line>Ken Levasseur</line>
			<line>Lowell MA</line>
			</attribution>

	</preface>

<xi:include href="./introduction.xml" />

</frontmatter>