<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!-- This file is part of the book                 -->
<!--                                               -->
<!--   Applied Discrete Structures   -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- Ken Levasseur and Al Doerr     -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.  -->

<frontmatter xml:id="index" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

	<titlepage>

		<author>
			<personname>Al Doerr</personname>
			<department>Department of Mathematical Sciences</department>
			<institution>University of Massachusetts Lowell</institution>
			<email></email>
		</author>
		<author>
			<personname>Ken Levasseur</personname>
			<department>Department of Mathematical Sciences</department>
			<institution>University of Massachusetts Lowell</institution>
			<email>kenneth_levasseur@uml.edu</email>
		</author>

		<date>September, 2016</date>


	</titlepage>

	<colophon>

		<copyright>
			<year>2016</year>
			<holder>Al Doerr, Ken Levasseur</holder>
			<minilicense>Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 United States License. 2011-2016</minilicense>
<!-- 
			<creativecommons BY="yes" NC="yes" SA="yes" version="4.0"/>
 -->
			<shortlicense>Applied Discrete Structures by Alan Doerr and Kenneth Levasseur is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 United States License. You are free to Share: copy and redistribute the material in any medium or format; Adapt: remix, transform, and build upon the material. You may not use the material for commercial purposes.  The licensor cannot revoke these freedoms as long as you follow the license terms.
			</shortlicense>
		</copyright>

	</colophon>

	<!-- Accepted order: acknowledgements, forewords, prefaces -->

	<acknowledgement>

		<p>I would like to thank Rob Beezer, David Farmer and other participants on the <url href="https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups#!forum/mathbook-xml-support">mathbook-xml-support group</url> for their guidance and work on MathBook XML.  Thanks to the Pedagogy Subcommittee of the UMass Lowell Transformational Education Committee for their financial assistance in helping getting this project started.</p>


	</acknowledgement>

	<preface>
<p>This version of <em>Applied Discrete Structures</em> is being developed using <em>Mathbook XML</em>, A lightweight XML application for authors of scientific articles, textbooks and monographs initiated by Rob Beezer, U. of Puget Sound.  </p>


<p>Sage (<url href="http://sagemath.org">sagemath.org</url>) is a free, open source, software system for advanced mathematics.  Sage can be used either on your own computer, a local server, or on SageMathCloud (<url href="https://cloud.sagemath.com">https://cloud.sagemath.com</url>). </p>

			<attribution>
			<line>Ken Levasseur</line>
			<line>Lowell MA</line>
			</attribution>

	</preface>
</frontmatter>