<glossary xml:id="ads-glossary">
<idx>Glossary</idx>
<headnote><p>Many of the words in this glossary are not formally defined in the book either because they are viewed as prerequisites to a course in discrete mathematics or are terms in computer science that some students may be unfamiliar with.</p></headnote>

<gi xml:id="gloss-An">
<title>An</title> <idx>An</idx>
<p>When referring to “an entity” we mean that the object can be any of the elements is some set.  For example, if you say that <m>n</m> is an integer, it could be any integer.</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Bit"> 
<title>Bit</title><idx>Bit</idx>
<p>The smallest unit of computer memory, normally represented as a 0 or 1.</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Byte">
<title>Byte</title> <idx>Byte</idx>
<p>A basic unit of computer memory containing eight <xref ref="gloss-Bit" text="title"/>s, normally modeled as a sequence of eight 0’s and 1’s.</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Complex-Number">
<title>Complex Number</title> <idx>Complex Number</idx>
<p>A number of the form <m>a + b \boldsymbol{i}</m>, where <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> are real numbers and <m>\boldsymbol{i}^2=-1</m>.</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Composite-Integer"> 
<title>Composite Integer</title><idx>Composite Integer</idx>
<p>A positive integer is composite if it is greater than one and is the product of two positive integers greater than one.  For example, 10 (equal to <m>2\cdot 5</m>) is composite.  Any positive integer greater than one that is not composite is <xref ref="gloss-Prime" text="title"/>.</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Constant">
<title>Constant</title> <idx>Constant</idx>
<p>A numerical value that is unchanging .  The value might be unknown and it still may be represented with a symbol.  For example if we are discussing the process of sorting a file of <m>N</m> numbers, <m>N</m> is considered a constant with respect to the sorting algorithm.  Constants can become <xref ref="gloss-Variable" text="custom">variables</xref> though.  If we have designed a sorting algorithm, and want to analyze its efficiency, we would consider <m>N</m> to be a variable.</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Creative-Commons">
<title>Creative Commons</title> <idx>Creative Commons</idx>
<p>An organization which has created several open licenses for creative works such as <em>Applied Discrete Structures</em>.</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Data-Structure">
<title>Data Structure</title> <idx>data Structure</idx>
<p>A format for organizing, processing, retrieving and storing data. </p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Distinct"> 
<title>Distinct</title><idx>distinct</idx>
<p>Two entities are distinct if they are not the same.  For example, any two student ID numbers at a school should be distinct.  If not, confusion could ensue. See also <xref ref="gloss-Unique" text="title"/>.</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Even-Integer">
<title>Even Integer</title> <idx>Even Integer</idx>
<p>Any <xref ref="gloss-Integer" text="title"/> that is equal to two times an integer.  That includes 0, since <m>0 = 2 \cdot 0</m>.</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Factor"> 
<title>Factor</title><idx>Factor</idx>
<p>If an algebraic expression is the product of several expressions, each of those expressions is a factor.</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Iff">
<title>Iff</title> <idx>Iff</idx>
<p>Shorthand for “if and only if”</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Integer">
<title>Integer</title> <idx>Integer</idx>
<p>Whole number, whether positive, negative or zero.</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Into">
<title>Into</title> <idx>Into</idx>
<p>When defining a function we use <em>into</em> as a connector between the domain and codomian. Occasionally further abbeviated to <em>to</em></p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Irrational-Number">
<title>Irrational Number</title> <idx>Irrational Number</idx>
<p>A number that is not equal to any fraction.  <m>\sqrt{2}</m> is one we prove to be irrational in the book.</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-LaTeX"> 
<title>LaTeX</title><idx>LaTeX</idx>
<p>A markup language used for books and papers with lots of mathematics, which is built on <tex/>.  <pretext/> uses <latex/> as an intermediate format to produce <init>PDF</init> and print output.</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Multiples"> 
<title>Multiples</title><idx>Multiples</idx>
<p>Multiples of a number <m>c</m> are <m>\dots, -3c,—2c,-c,0,c,2c,3c,\dots</m></p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Natural-Numbers">
<title>Natural Numbers</title> <idx>Natural Numbers</idx>
<p>In this book, its the numbers 0,1,2,3,4,… .  There isn’t 100% agreement here.  Some people say its the numbers 1,2,3,4, … . We call those numbers the positive integers. The symbol we use of the natural numbers is <m>\mathbb{N}</m>. There is no consistent definition of positive complex numbers.</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Nonnegative-Number"> 
<title>Nonnegative Number</title><idx>Nonnegative Number</idx>
<p>A number that is either positive or zero.</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Odd-Integer">
<title>Odd Integer</title> <idx>Odd Integer</idx>
<p>An integer <m>n</m> is odd if there exists an integer <m>k</m> so that <m>n = 2k + 1</m>.  Any integer that is not even is odd.</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Positive-Number"> 
<title>Positive Number</title><idx>Positive Number</idx>
<p>A positive number is a number that is greater than zero.  Normally visualized as being to the right of zero on a conventional number line. The set of positive integers is denoted <m>\mathbb{P}</m>.  The sets of positive rational and real numbers are denoted <m>\mathbb{Q}^+</m> and <m>\mathbb{R}?^+</m>, respectively</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Powers">
<title>Powers</title> <idx>Powers</idx>
<p>Powers of a nonzero number <m>c</m> are <m>\dots, c^{-3},c^{-2},c^{-1},1,c^1,c^2,c^3,\dots</m>.  Recall that <m>c^0=1</m>.</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-PreTeXt"> 
<title>PreTeXt</title><idx>PreTeXt</idx>
<p>An authoring and publishing system for authors of textbooks, research articles, and monographs, especially in STEM disciplines.  <em>Applied Discrete Structures</em> is produced using PreTeXt.</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Prime"> 
<title>Prime</title><idx>Prime</idx>
<p>A positive integer that is divisible by exactly two positive integers, itself and <m>1</m>.  One is not prime, but <m>2</m> is the oddest prime because it’s even.  See also <xref ref="gloss-Composite-Integer" text="title"/>.</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Queue">
<title>Queue</title> <idx>Queue</idx>
<p>A conventional waiting line, with the first come-first serve service rule. A queue is a common <xref ref="gloss-Data-Structure" text="title"/> in computer science.  See also <xref ref="gloss-Stack" text="title"/>.</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Rational-Number"> 
<title>Rational Number</title><idx>Rational Number</idx>
<p>Any real number that is equal to a quotient two integers, <m>a/b</m>, with <m>b \neq 0</m>.</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Real-Number"> 
<title>Real Number</title><idx>Real Number</idx>
<p>For the purposes of this book, think of the numbers on a standard number line.  All of the points make up the set of real numbers.</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-SageMath"> 
<title>SageMath</title><idx>SageMath</idx>
<p>An open source computer algebra system for a wide range of symbolic and numerical mathematical computations. Originally named simply Sage.</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Stack"> 
<title>Stack</title><idx>Stack</idx>
<p>A <xref ref="gloss-Data-Structure" text="title"/> similar to a queue, but where the last come-first serve service rule is used.  This wouldn’t be a fair waiting line rule, but it is a very useful data structure. See also <xref ref="gloss-Queue" text="title"/></p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Subtraction"> 
<title>Subtraction</title><idx>Subtraction</idx>
<p>Subtraction is really addition of the negation of a number:  <m>a-b=a+(-b)</m>.</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Term">
<title>Term</title> <idx>Term</idx>
<p>If an algebraic expression is the sum of several expressions, each of those expressions is a term. For example there are three terms in the expression <m>2y + x-(w+1)/2</m>.  Note that subtraction is considered the same as addition here.</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-To">
<title>To</title> <idx>To</idx>
<p>See <xref ref="gloss-Into" text="title"/></p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Unique">
<title>Unique</title> <idx>Unique</idx>
<p>We say a mathematical entity is unique when there’s nothing else like it.   For example, the solution, <m>x=3</m> to the equation <m>2x+1=7</m> is unique. No other number solves the equation.  See also <xref ref="gloss-Distinct" text="title"/>.</p>
</gi>

<gi xml:id="gloss-Variable"> 
<title>Variable</title><idx>Variable</idx>
<p>A quantity  whose value that can vary within a specified set.  Normally represented by an algebraic symbol. For discrete variables it is customary to use the letters in the range from i to n, but this isn’t a rigid rule. Letters at the end of the alphabet are traditionally used for continuous variables.</p>
</gi>

</glossary>