<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<section xml:id="s-Atoms of a Boolean Algebra">
<title>Atoms of a Boolean Algebra</title>
<index><main>Atoms of a Boolean Algebra</main></index>



In this section we will look more closely at previous claims that every finite Boolean algebra is isomorphic to an algebra of sets. We will show
that every finite Boolean algebra has \(2^n\) elements for some <m>n</m> with precisely <m>n</m> generators, called atoms. .



   Consider the Boolean algebra \([B; -, \lor , \land ]\), whose graph is:


\begin{center}\(\)
\end{center}


\caption{\pmb{ Figure 13.4.1\\
Illustration of the atom concept}}



   We note that \(1 = a_1 \lor  a_2 \lor  a_3\), \(b_1 = a_1 \lor  a_2\), \(b_2 = a_1 \lor  a_3\), and \(b_3 = a_2 \lor  a_3\); that is, each of
the elements above level one can be described completely and uniquely in terms of the elements on level one. The \(a_is\) have uniquely generated
the nonzero elements of <m>B</m> much like a basis in linear algebra generates the elements in a vector space. We also note that the \(a_is\)
are the immediate successors of the minimum element, 0. In any Boolean algebra, the immediate successors of the minimum element are called \textit{
atoms}. Let <m>A</m> be any nonempty set. In the Boolean algebra \([\mathcal{P}(A); c, \cup , \cap ]\) (over $\subseteq $), the
singleton sets are the generators, or atoms, of the algebraic structure since each element \(\mathcal{P}(A)\) can be described completely and uniquely
as the join or union of singleton sets.

<definition xml:id="def-Atom."><title>Atom.</title><index><main>Atom.</main></index><notation><usage></usage><description></description></notation><statement><p></p></statement></definition>

 A nonzero element a in a Boolean algebra . \([B; -, \lor , \land ]\) is called an atom if for every . \(x
\in  B\), . \(x \land  a = a\) or . \(x \land  a = 0\).. 



   The condition that \(x \land  a = a\) tells us that <m>x</m> is a successor of <m>a</m>; that is, \(a \leq  x\), as depicted in Figure
13.4.2a.



   The condition \(x \land  a = 0\) is true only when <m>x</m> and <m>a</m> are <q>not connected.</q> This occurs when <m>x</m> is another
atom or if <m>x</m> is a successor of atoms different from <m>a</m>, as depicted in Figure 13.4.2b.


\begin{center}\(\)
\end{center}


\caption{\pmb{ Figure 13.4.2}}



<example xml:id="ex-13.4.1."><title>13.4.1.</title><p></p></example>   The set of atoms of the Boolean algebra \(\left[D_{30}; -, \lor , \land \right]\) is \(M = \{2, 3, 5\}\). To see that
\(a = 2\) is an atom, let <m>x</m> be any nonzero element of \(D_{30}\) and note that one of the two conditions \(x \land  2 = 2\) or \(x \land
 2 = 1\) holds. Of course, to apply the definition to this Boolean algebra, we must remind ourselves that in this case the 0-element is 1, the operation
$\land $ is gcd. , and the poset relation $\leq $ is <q>divides.</q> So if \(x = 10\), we have \(10 \land  2 = 2\) (or 2 $|$ 10), so Condition
1 holds. If \(x = 15\), the first condition is not true. (Why?) However, Condition 2, \(15 \land  2 = 1\), is true. The reader is encouraged to show
that each of the elements 2, 3, and 5 satisfy the definition (see Exercise 13.4.1). Next, if we compute the join (lcm.  in this case) of
all possible combinations of the atoms 2, 3, and 5, we will generate all nonzero elements of \(D_{30}\). For example, \(2 \lor  3 \lor  5 = 30\)
and \(2 \lor  5 = 10\). We state this concept formally in the following theorem, which we give without proof.

<theorem xml:id="theorem-13.4.1."><title>13.4.1.</title><index><main>13.4.1.</main></index><statement></statement><proof></proof></theorem>   Let . \([B; -, \lor , \land ]\).  be any finite Boolean algebra. Let . \(A = \left\{a_1, a_2,.
. . ,a_n\right\}\) be the set of all n atoms of . \([B;\text -, \lor , \land ]\)\textit{ . Then every nonzero element in B can be expressed
uniquely as the join of a subset of A.}



   We now ask ourselves if we can be more definitive about the structure of different Boolean algebras of a given order. Certainly, the Boolean
algebras \(\left[D_{30}; -, \lor , \land \right]\) and \([\mathcal{P}(A); c, \cup , \cap ]\) have the same graph (that of Figure 13.4.1), the same
number of atoms, and, in all respects, look the same except for the names of the elements and the operations. In fact, when we apply corresponding
operations to corresponding elements, we obtain corresponding results. We know from Chapter 11 that this means that the two structures are isomorphic
as Boolean algebras. Furthermore, the graphs of these examples are exactly the same as that of Figure 13.4.1, which is an arbitrary Boolean algebra
of order \(8 = 2^3\).



   In these examples of a Boolean algebra of order 8, we note that each had 3 atoms and \(2^3 = 8\) number of elements, and all were isomorphic
to \([\mathcal{P}(A ); c, \cup , \cap ]\), where \(A = \{a, b, c\}\). This leads us to the following questions:



   (1) Are there any other different (nonisomorphic) Boolean algebras of order 8?



   (2) What is the relationship, if any, between finite Boolean algebras and their atoms?



  (3) How many different (nonisomorphic) Boolean algebras are there of order 2? Order 3? Order 4? And so on.



   The answers to these questions are given in the following theorem and corollaries. We include the proofs of the corollaries since they are instructive.



<theorem xml:id="theorem-13.4.2."><title>13.4.2.</title><index><main>13.4.2.</main></index><statement></statement><proof></proof></theorem>   Let . \([B; -, \lor , \land ]\). \textit{  be any finite Boolean algebra, and let A be the set of all
atoms in this Boolean algebra. Then }\([B; -, \lor , \land ]\).  is isomorphic to . \([\mathcal{P. (A); c, \cup , \cap ]\)}\textit{
.}



\pmb{ Corollary 13.4.1.}   Every finite Boolean algebra . \([B; -, \lor , \land ]\).  has . \(2^n\)\textit{  elements for
some positive integer n.}



   Proof: Let <m>A</m> be the set of all atoms of <m>B</m> and let \(\left| A\right|  = n\). Then there are exactly \(2^n\) elements (subsets)
in \(\mathcal{P}(A)\), and by Theorem 13.4.2, \([B; -, \lor , \land ]\) is isomorphic to \([\mathcal{P}(A); c, \cup , \cap ]\).  $\blacksquare
$



\(\pmb{\textrm{ Corollary 13.4.2.}}\)   All Boolean algebras of order \(2^n\) are isomorphic to each other. (The graph of the Boolean algebra of order
\(2^n\) is the <m>n</m>-cube).



   Proof:   By Theorem 13.4.2, every Boolean algebra of order \(2^n\) is isomorphic to \([\mathcal{P}(A); c, \cup , \cap ]\) when \(\left| A\right|
 = n\). Hence, they are all isomorphic to one another.  $\blacksquare $



   The above theorem and corollaries tell us that we can only have finite Boolean algebras of orders \(2^1, 2^2, 2^3,. . . , 2^n\), and that all
finite Boolean algebras of any given order are isomorphic. These are powerful tools in determining the structure of finite Boolean algebras. In the
next section, we will try to find the easiest way of describing a Boolean algebra of any given order.



\pmb{ EXERCISES FOR SECTION 13.4}



       A Exercises

<exercise number="1"><statement>    (a) Show that \(a = 2\) is an atom of the Boolean algebra \(\left[D_{30}; -, \lor , \land \right]\).



       (b) Repeat part a for the elements 3 and 5 of \(D_{30}\).



       (c) Verify Theorem 13.4.1 for the Boolean algebra \(\left[D_{30}; -, \lor , \land \right]\).
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="2"><statement>   Let \(A = \{a, b, c\}\).



       (a) Rewrite the definition of atom for \([\mathcal{P}(A); c, \cup , \cap ]\). What does \(a \leq  x\) mean in this example?



       (b) Find all atoms of \([\mathcal{P}(A); c, \cup , \cap ]\).



       (c) Verify Theorem 13.4.1 for \([\mathcal{P}(A); c, \cup , \cap ]\).
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="3"><statement>   Verify Theorem 13.4.2 and its corollaries for the Boolean algebras in Exercises 1 and 2 of this section.
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="4"><statement>  Give a description of all Boolean algebras of order 16. (Hint. : Use Theorem 13.4.2.) Note that the graph of this Boolean algebra is
given in Figure 9.4.5.
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="5"><statement>   Corollary 13.4.1 states that there do not exist Boolean algebras of orders 3, 5, 6, 7, 9, etc. (orders different from \(2^n\)). Prove that
we cannot have a Boolean algebra of order 3. (Hint. : Assume that \([B; -, \lor , \land ]\) is a Boolean algebra of order 3 where \(B = \{0,
x, 1\}\) and show that this cannot happen by investigating the possibilities for its operation tables.)
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="6"><statement>   (a)  There are many different, yet isomorphic, Boolean algebras with two elements. Describe one such Boolean algebra that is derived from
a power set, \(\mathcal{P}(A)\), under $\subseteq $. Describe a second that is described from \(D_n\), for some \(n \in  P\), under <q>divides.</q>




       (b)  Since the elements of a two-element Boolean algebra must be the greatest and least elements, 1 and 0, the tables for the operations
on $\{$0, 1$\}$ are determined by the Boolean algebra laws. Write out the operation tables for \([\{0, 1\};\text -, \lor , \land ]\).



       B Exercises
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="7"><statement>   Find a Boolean algebra with a countably infinite number of elements.
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="8"><statement>   Prove that the direct product of two Boolean algebras is a Boolean algebra. (Hint. : <q>Copy</q> the corresponding proof for groups
in Section 11.6.)

\end{document}
