<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<section xml:id="s-cosets-and-factor-groups">
<title>Cosets and Factor Groups</title>
<idx>Cosets and Factor Groups</idx>
<p>Consider the group <m>\left[\mathbb{Z}_{12};+_{12}\right]</m>. As we saw in the previous section, we can picture its cyclic properties with the string art of <xref ref="fig-string-art"/>. Here we will be interested in the non-generators, like 3. The solid lines in <xref ref="fig-string-art-cosets"/> show that only one-third of the
tacks have been reached by starting at zero and jumping to every third tack. The numbers of these tacks correspond to <m>\langle 3 \rangle = \{0, 3, 6, 9\}</m>. </p>
           <figure xml:id="fig-string-art-cosets">
                <caption><q>String art</q> cosets
                </caption>
                <image width="70%" source="images/fig-string-art-cosets.png">
                    <description><q>String art</q> cosets</description>
                </image>
            </figure>
<p>What happens if you start at one of the unused tacks and again jump to every third tack? The two broken paths on <xref ref="fig-string-art-cosets"/> show that identical
squares are produced. The tacks are thus partitioned into very similar subsets. The subsets of <m>\mathbb{Z}_{12}</m> that they correspond to are <m>\{0,
3, 6, 9\}</m>, <m>\{1, 4, 7, 10\}</m>, and <m>\{2, 5, 8, 11\}</m>. These subsets are called cosets. In particular, they are called cosets of the subgroup <m>\{0, 3, 6, 9\}</m>. We will see that under certain conditions, cosets of a subgroup can form a group of their own. Before pursuing this example any further we will examine the general situation.</p>

<definition xml:id="def-coset"><title>Coset</title>
<idx>Coset</idx>
<notation><usage>a*H, H*a</usage><description>the left and right cosets generated by <m>a</m></description></notation>
<statement><p>If <m>[G;*]</m> is a group, <m>H \leq  G</m> and <m>a \in  G</m>, the left coset  of <m>H</m> generated by <m>a</m> is

 <me>a*H = \{ a*h | h \in  H\}</me> 

and the right coset of <m>H</m> generated by <m>a</m> is 

 <me>H*a = \{h*a | h\in H\}.</me></p></statement></definition>

  <note><p>
<ol label="(a)">
<li><p>  <m>H</m> itself is both a left and right coset since <m>e*H = H*e = H</m>.</p></li>
<li><p>  If <m>G</m> is abelian, <m>a*H = H*a</m> and the left-right distinction for cosets can be dropped. We will normally use left coset notation in that
situation.</p></li>
</ol></p></note>

<definition xml:id="def-coset-representative"><title>Coset Representative</title><idx>Coset Representative</idx>
<statement><p>Any element of a coset is called a representative of that coset.</p></statement></definition>

<p>One might wonder whether <m>a</m> is in any way a special representative of <m>a*H</m> since it seems to define the coset. It is not, as we shall see.</p>

<remark><title>A Duality Principle</title><p> A duality principle can be formulated concerning cosets because left and right cosets are defined in such similar ways.
Any theorem about left and right cosets will yield a second theorem when <q>left</q> and <q>right</q> are exchanged for <q>right</q> and <q>left.</q></p></remark>

<theorem xml:id="theorem-15-2-1">
<statement><p>If <m>b\in a*H</m>, then <m>a*H = b*H</m>, and if <m>b \in  H*a</m>, then <m>H*a = H*b</m>.</p></statement><proof><p>In light of the remark above, we need only prove the first part of this theorem. Suppose that <m>x \in  a*H</m>.  We need
only find a way of expressing <m>x</m> as <q><m>b</m> times an element of <m>H</m>.</q> Then we will have proven that <m>a*H \subseteq  b*H</m>.  By the definition of <m>a*H</m>, since <m>b</m> and <m>x</m> are in <m>a*H</m>, there exist <m>h_1</m> and <m>h_2</m> in <m>H</m> such that <m>b =
a*h_1</m> and <m>x = a*h_2</m>. Given these two equations, <m>a = b h_1^{-1}</m> and
<me>x = a*h_2 = (b *h_1^{-1})*h_2 = b*(h_1^{-1}*h_2)</me>

Since <m>h_1,h_2 \in H</m>,   <m>h_1^{-1}*h_2 \in H</m>, and we are done with this part of the proof.  In order to show that <m>b*H \subseteq a*H</m>, one can follow essentially the same steps, which we will let the reader fill in.</p></proof></theorem> 


<example xml:id="ex-15-2-1"><p>In <xref ref="fig-string-art-cosets"/>, you can start at either 1 or 7 and obtain the same path by taking jumps of three tacks in each step.
Thus,
<me>1+_{12} \{0, 3, 6, 9\} = 7 +_{12} \{0, 3, 6, 9\} = \{1, 4, 7, 10\}.</me></p></example>  



<p>The set of left (or right) cosets of a subgroup partition a group in a special way:</p>

<theorem xml:id="theorem-cosets-partition"><title>Cosets Partition a Group</title><idx><h>Partition</h><h>of a group by cosets</h></idx>
<statement><p>If <m>[G; *]</m> is a group and <m>H\leq  G</m>, the set of left cosets of <m>H</m> is a partition of <m>G</m>. In addition, all of the left
cosets of <m>H</m> have the same cardinality. The same is true for right cosets.</p></statement>
<proof><p>That every element of <m>G</m> belongs to a left coset is clear because <m>a \in  a*H</m> for all <m>a \in  G</m>. If <m>a*H</m> and <m>b*H</m> are
left cosets, we will prove that they are either equal or disjoint. If <m>a*H</m> and <m>b*H</m> are not disjoint, <m>a*H\cap b*H</m> is nonempty and some element <m>c \in G</m> belongs to the intersection. Then by <xref ref="theorem-15-2-1" text="type-global"/>, <m>c\in a*H \Rightarrow  a*H = c*H</m> and
<m>c \in b*H \Rightarrow  b*H = c*H</m>. Hence  <m>a*H = b*H</m>.</p>
<p>We complete the proof by showing that each left coset has the same cardinality as <m>H</m>. To do this, we simply observe that if <m>a \in  G</m>, <m>\rho:H \to  a*H</m> defined by <m>\rho(h)= a*h</m> is a bijection and hence <m>\lvert H\rvert =\lvert a *H\rvert</m>.  We will leave the proof of this statement to the reader.</p></proof></theorem>  

<p>The function <m>\rho</m> has a nice interpretation in terms of our opening example.  If <m>a \in  \mathbb{Z}_{12}</m>, the graph of <m>\{0, 3, 6, 9\}</m> is rotated <m>(30a)^{\circ}</m> to coincide with one of the three cosets of <m>\{0, 3, 6, 9\}</m>.</p>

<corollary xml:id="corollary-counting-cosets">
<title>A Coset Counting Formula</title>
<idx>Coset Counting Formula</idx>
<statement><p>If <m>\lvert G\rvert &lt; \infty</m> and <m>H\leq G</m>, the number of distinct left cosets of <m>H</m> equals <m>\frac{\lvert
G\rvert }{\lvert H\rvert }</m>. For this reason we use <m>G/H</m> to denote the set of left cosets of <m>H</m> in <m>G</m></p></statement>
<proof><p>This follows from the partitioning of <m>G</m> into equal sized sets, one of which is <m>H</m>.</p></proof></corollary>


<example xml:id="ex-finite-number-of-infinite-cosets"><p>The set of integer multiples of four, <m>4\mathbb{Z}</m>, is a subgroup of <m>[\mathbb{Z}; +]</m>. Four distinct cosets of <m>4\mathbb{Z}</m>
partition the integers. They are <m>4\mathbb{Z}</m>, <m>1+4\mathbb{Z}</m>, <m>2+4\mathbb{Z}</m>, and <m>3+4\mathbb{Z}</m>, where, for example, <m>1+4\mathbb{Z}
= \{1+4k | k \in  \mathbb{Z}\}</m>.   <m>4\mathbb{Z}</m> can also be written <m>0+4\mathbb{Z}</m>.</p></example>


<convention xml:id="conv-distinguishedi-representatives"><title>Distinguished Representatives</title><p>Although we have seen that any representative can describe a coset, it is often convenient to select a distinguished
representative from each coset. The advantage to doing this is that there is a unique name for each coset in terms of its distinguished representative.
In numeric examples such as the one above, the distinguished representative is usually the smallest nonnegative representative. Remember, this is
purely a convenience and there is absolutely nothing wrong in writing <m>-203+4\mathbb{Z}</m>, <m>5+4\mathbb{Z}</m>, or <m>621+4\mathbb{Z}</m> in place of
<m>1+4\mathbb{Z}</m>  because  <m>-203, 5, 621 \in 1+4\mathbb{Z}</m>.</p></convention>



<p>Before completing the main thrust of this section, we will make note of a significant implication of <xref ref="theorem-cosets-partition" text="type-global"/>. Since a finite group is divided into cosets of a common size by any subgroup, we can conclude:</p>
<theorem xml:id="th-lagrange-theorem"><title>Lagrange's Theorem</title>
<idx>Lagrange's Theorem</idx>
<statement><p>The order of a subgroup of a finite group must divide the order of the group.</p></statement>
</theorem>

<p>One immediate implication of Lagrange's Theorem is that if <m>p</m> is prime, <m>\mathbb{Z}_p</m>  has no proper subgroups.</p>



<p>We will now describe the operation on cosets which will, under certain circumstances, result in a group. For most of this section, we will assume
that <m>G</m> is an abelian group. This is one sufficient (but not necessary) condition that guarantees that the set of left cosets will form a group.</p>

<definition xml:id="def-operation-on-cosets"><title>Operation on Cosets</title>
<idx><h>Cosets</h><h>Operation on</h></idx>
<statement><p>Let <m>C</m> and <m>D</m> be left cosets of <m>H</m>, a subgroup of <m>G</m> with representatives <m>c</m> and <m>d</m>, respectively. Then 

<me>C\otimes D = (c*H) \otimes (d*H) = (c*d)*H </me>
 The operation <m>\otimes</m> is called the operation induced on left cosets by <m>*</m>.</p></statement></definition>


<p>In <xref ref="theorem-coset-operation-well-defined" text="type-global" />, later in this section, we will prove that if <m>G</m> is an abelian group, <m>\otimes</m> is indeed an operation. In practice, if the group <m>G</m> is an additive group, the symbol <m>\otimes</m> is replaced by <m>+</m>, as in the following example.</p>

<example xml:id="ex-cosets-of-4z"><title>Computing with cosets of <m>4\mathbb{Z}</m></title>
<p>Consider the cosets described in <xref ref="ex-finite-number-of-infinite-cosets" text="type-global" />.  For brevity, we rename <m>0+4\mathbb{Z}</m>, <m>1+4\mathbb{Z}</m>, <m>2+4\mathbb{Z}</m>,
and <m>3+4\mathbb{Z}</m> with the symbols <m>\bar{0}</m>, <m>\bar{1}</m>, <m>\bar{2}</m>, and <m>\bar{3}</m>.   Let's do a typical calculation, <m>\bar{1}+\bar{3}</m>.  We will see that the result is always going to be <m>\bar{0}</m> , no matter what representatives we select.  For example, <m>9 \in  \bar{1}</m>, <m>7\in  \bar{3}</m>, and <m>9+7=16 \in  \bar{0}</m>. Our choice of the representatives <m>\bar{1}</m> and <m>\bar{3}</m> were completely arbitrary.</p></example>   

<p>In general,  <m>C \otimes  D</m>  can be computed in many ways, and so it is necessary to show that the choice of representatives does not affect the result. When the result we get for <m>C \otimes  D</m> is always independent of our choice of representatives, we say that <q><m>\otimes</m> is well defined.</q>  Addition of cosets is a well-defined operation on the left cosets of 4<m>\mathbb{Z}</m> and is summarized in the following table.
Do you notice anything familiar?
<me>
\begin{array}{c|cccc}
\otimes &amp; \bar{0} &amp; \bar{1} &amp; \bar{2}  &amp; \bar{3}\\
\hline
\bar{0} &amp; \bar{0} &amp; \bar{1}  &amp; \bar{2}  &amp; \bar{3}\\
\bar{1} &amp; \bar{1} &amp; \bar{2}  &amp; \bar{3} &amp; \bar{0}\\
\bar{2} &amp; \bar{2}  &amp;\bar{3} &amp; \bar{0} &amp; \bar{1}\\
\bar{3} &amp; \bar{3}&amp; \bar{0}   &amp; \bar{1} &amp; \bar{2} \\
\end{array}
</me>
</p>
<example xml:id="cosets-of-a-in-r"><title>Cosets of the integers in the group of Real numbers</title>
<p>Consider the group of real numbers, <m>[\mathbb{R}; +]</m>, and its subgroup of integers, <m>\mathbb{Z}</m>. Every element of <m>\mathbb{R}/\mathbb{Z}</m> has the same cardinality as <m>\mathbb{Z}</m>. Let <m>s, t\in \mathbb{R}</m>. <m>s\in t+\mathbb{Z}</m> if <m>s</m> can be written <m>t+n</m> for some <m>n \in \mathbb{Z}</m>.  Hence <m>s</m> and <m>t</m> belong to the same coset if they differ by an integer. (See <xref ref="exercise-15-2-6" text="type-global" /> for a generalization of
this fact.)</p>
<p>Now consider the coset <m>0.25+\mathbb{Z}</m>. Real numbers that differ by an integer from 0.25 are <m>1.25, 2.25, 3.25, \ldots</m> and <m>-0.75, -1.75, -2.75, \ldots</m>.  If any real number is selected, there exists a representative of its coset that is greater than or equal to 0 and less than 1. We will call that representative the distinguished representative of the coset. For example, 43.125 belongs to the coset represented by 0.125; <m>-6.382+\mathbb{Z}</m> has 0.618 as its distinguished representative. The operation on <m>\mathbb{R}/\mathbb{Z}</m> is commonly called addition modulo 1. A few typical calculations in <m>\mathbb{R}/\mathbb{Z}</m> are
<me>
\begin{array}{c}
(0.1+\mathbb{Z})+(0.48+\mathbb{Z}) = 0.58+\mathbb{Z}\\
(0.7+\mathbb{Z})+(0.31+\mathbb{Z}) = 0.01+\mathbb{Z}\\
-(0.41+\mathbb{Z}) = -0.41+\mathbb{Z} = 0.59+\mathbb{Z}\\
\textrm{and in general, } -(a+\mathbb{Z}) = (1 - a)+\mathbb{Z}
\end{array}
</me>.</p></example> 

<example xml:id="ex-cosets-in-direct-product"><title>Cosets in a Direct Product</title>
<p>Consider <m>F = (\mathbb{Z}_4\times  \mathbb{Z}_2 )/H</m>, where <m>H=\{(0,0),(0,1)\}</m>. Since <m>\mathbb{Z}_4 \times \mathbb{Z}_2</m> is of order 8, each element of <m>F</m> is a coset containing two ordered pairs. We will leave it to the reader to verify that the four distinct cosets are
<m>(0, 0)+H</m>,  <m>(1,0) +H</m>, <m>(2, 0)+H</m> and  <m>(3, 0)+H</m>.
The reader can also verify that <m>F</m> is isomorphic to <m>\mathbb{Z}_4</m> , since <m>F</m> is cyclic. An educated guess should give you a generator.</p></example>  

<example xml:id="ex-cosets-in-z2-to-4">
<p>Consider the group <m>\mathbb{Z}_2{}^4 = \mathbb{Z}_2\times \mathbb{Z}_2\times \mathbb{Z}_2\times \mathbb{Z}_2</m> . Let <m>H</m> be <m>\langle (1,0,1, 0)\rangle</m>, the cyclic subgroup of <m>\mathbb{Z}_2{}^4</m> generate by (1,0,1,0). Since 
<me>(1,0,1, 0)+(1,0,1, 0)=(1+_21,0+_20,1+_21,0+_20) = (0,0,0,0)</me>
the order of <m>H</m> is 2 and , <m>\mathbb{Z}_2{}^4/H</m> has <m>\lvert \mathbb{Z}_2^4 /H\rvert =\frac{\lvert
\mathbb{Z}_2^4\rvert }{\lvert H\rvert }=\frac{16}{2}= 8</m> elements. A typical coset is 
    <me>C = (0, 1, 1, 1)+H = \{(0, 1, 1, 1), (1, 1, 0, 1)\}</me>
Note that since <m>2(0, 1, 1, 1) = (0, 0, 0, 0)</m>, <m>2C = C\otimes C = H</m>, the identity for the operation on  <m>\mathbb{Z}_2{}^4/H</m>. The orders of non-identity elements of this factor group are all 2, and it can be shown that the factor group is isomorphic to <m>\mathbb{Z}_2{}^3</m>.</p></example> 

<theorem xml:id="theorem-coset-operation-well-defined">
<title>Coset operation is well-defined (Abelian Case)</title>
<statement><p>If <m>G</m> is an abelian group, and <m>H \leq  G</m>, the operation induced on cosets of <m>H</m> by the operation of <m>G</m> is well defined.</p></statement><proof><p>Suppose that <m>a</m>, <m>b</m>, and <m>a'</m>, <m>b'</m>.  are two choices for representatives of cosets <m>C</m> and <m>D</m>. That is to say that <m>a, a' \in  C</m>, <m>b, b' \in D</m>. We will show that <m>a*b</m> and <m>a'*b'</m> are representatives of the same coset. <xref ref="theorem-15-2-1" text="type-global"/>1 implies that <m>C = a*H</m> and <m>D = b*H</m>, thus we have <m>a' \in  a*H</m> and <m>b' \in  b*H</m>.  Then there exists <m>h_1, h_2 \in  H</m> such that  <m>a' = a*h_1</m>   and <m>b' = b*h_2</m>  and so

<me>a'*b' = (a*h_1)*(b*h_2) = (a*b)*(h_1*h_2)</me>

by various group properties and the assumption that <m>G</m> is abelian, which lets us reverse the order in which <m>b</m> and <m>h_1</m> appear in the chain of equalities.  This last expression for <m>a'*b'</m> implies that <m>a'*b' \in  (a*b)*H</m> since <m>h_1*h_2 \in  H</m> because <m>H</m> is a subgroup of <m>G</m>.  Thus, we get the same coset for both pairs of representatives.</p></proof></theorem> 

<theorem xml:id="theorem-15-2-4">
<statement><p>Let <m>G</m> be a group and <m>H \leq  G</m>. If the operation induced on left cosets of <m>H</m> by the operation of <m>G</m> is well defined, then the set of left cosets forms a group under that operation.</p></statement>
<proof><p>Let <m>C_1</m><m>,C_2</m>, and <m>C_3</m> be the left cosets with representatives <m>r_1</m>, <m>r_2</m>, and <m>r_3</m>, respectively.   The values of <m>C_1 \otimes  \left(C_2 \otimes C_3\right)</m> and <m>\left(C_1\ \otimes  C_2\right)\otimes  C_3</m> are determined by   <m>r_1 * \left(r_2 * r_3\right)</m> and <m>\left(r_1 * r_2\right) * r_3</m>, respectively. By the associativity of <m>*</m> in <m>G</m>, these two group elements are equal and so  the two
coset expressions must be equal. Therefore, the induced operation is associative. As for the identity and inverse properties, there is no surprise.
The identity coset is <m>H</m>, or <m>e*H</m>, the coset that contains <m>G</m>'s identity. If <m>C</m> is a coset with representative <m>a</m>; that is, if  <m>C = a*H</m>, then <m>C^{-1}</m> is <m>a^{-1}*H</m>. 
 <me>(a*H)\otimes  \left(a^{-1}*H\right) = \left(a*a^{-1}\right)*H = e*H = \textrm{ identity} \textrm{ coset}</me>.
</p></proof></theorem> 

<definition xml:id="def-factor-group"><title>Factor Group</title>
<idx>Factor Group</idx>
<notation><usage>G/H</usage><description>The factor group G mod H.</description></notation><statement><p>Let <m>G</m> be a group and <m>H \leq  G</m>. If the set of left cosets of <m>H</m> forms a group, then that group is called the factor group of <q><m>G</m> modulo <m>H</m>.</q>   It is denoted <m>G/H</m>.</p></statement></definition>

<note><p>If <m>G</m> is abelian, then every subgroup of <m>G</m> yields a factor group. We will delay further consideration of the non-abelian case to Section 15.4.</p></note>



<remark><title>On Notation</title><p>It is customary to use the same symbol for the operation of <m>G/H</m> as for the operation on <m>G</m>.  The reason we used distinct symbols in this section was to make the distinction clear between the two operations.</p></remark>


<exercises xml:id="exercises-15-2">
<title>Exercises for Section 15.2</title>
<exercise number="1"><statement><p> Consider <m>\mathbb{Z}_{10}</m> and the subsets of <m>\mathbb{Z}_{10}</m>, <m>\{0, 1, 2, 3, 4\}</m> and <m>\{5, 6, 7, 8, 9\}</m>. Why is the operation induced on these subsets by modulo 10 addition not well defined?</p>
</statement><answer><p>An example of a valid correct answer: Call the subsets <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> respectively. If we choose <m>0 \in A</m> and <m>5 \in B</m> we get <m>0 +_{10} 5 =5 \in  B</m>. On the other hand, if we choose <m>3 \in A</m> and <m>8 \in  B</m>, we get <m>3 +_{10} 8 = 1 \in  A</m>. Therefore, the induced operation is not well defined on <m>\{A,B\}</m>.
</p></answer></exercise>
<exercise number="2"><statement><p> Can you think of a group <m>G</m>, with a subgroup <m>H</m> such that <m>\lvert H\rvert  = 6</m> and <m>\lvert G/H\rvert  = 6</m>? Is your
answer unique?</p>
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="3"><statement><p>For each group and subgroup, what is <m>G/H</m> isomorphic to?
<ol label="(a)">
<li><p>  <m>G = \mathbb{Z}_4 \times \mathbb{Z}_2</m>  and  <m>H = \langle (2, 0)\rangle</m>. Compare to <xref ref="ex-cosets-in-direct-product" text="type-global" />.</p></li>
<li><p>  <m>G = [\mathbb{C}; +]</m>  and <m>H = \mathbb{R}</m>.</p></li>
<li><p>  <m>G</m> = <m>\mathbb{Z}_{20}</m>  and  <m>H = \langle 8\rangle</m>.</p></li>
</ol></p>
</statement>
<answer><p>
<ol label="(a)">
<li><p> The four distinct cosets in <m>G/H</m> are <m>H = \{(0, 0), (2, 0)\}</m>, <m>(1, 0) + H= \{(1,0),(3,0)\}</m>,
 <m>(0, 1) + H= \{(0,1),(2,1)\}</m>,  and <m>(1, 1) + H= \{(1,1),(3,1)\}</m>. None of these cosets generates <m>G/H</m>; therefore <m>G/H</m> is not cyclic. Hence <m>G/H</m> must be isomorphic to <m>\mathbb{Z}_2\times \mathbb{Z}_2</m>.</p></li>
<li><p> The factor group is isomorphic to <m>[\mathbb{R}; +]</m>. Each coset of <m>\mathbb{R}</m> is a line in the complex plane that is parallel to the x-axis: <m>\tau :\mathbb{C}/\mathbb{R}\to  \mathbb{R}</m>, where <m>T(\{a + b i\mid a\in \mathbb{R}\}) = b</m> is an isomorphism.</p></li>
<li><p> <m>\langle 8\rangle  = \{0, 4, 8, 12, 16\} </m><m>\Rightarrow</m>  <m>\lvert \mathbb{Z}_{20}/\langle 8\rangle \rvert =4</m>. The four cosets are: <m>\bar{0}</m>, <m>\bar{1}</m>, <m>\bar{2}</m>, and <m>\bar{3}</m>. 1 generates all four cosets.  The factor group is isomorphic to <m>[\mathbb{Z}_4; +_4]</m>  because <m>\bar{1}</m> is a generator.</p></li>
</ol>
</p></answer>
</exercise>
<exercise number="4"><statement><p>For each group and subgroup, what is <m>G/H</m> isomorphic to?
<ol label="(a)">
<li><p>  <m>G = \mathbb{Z}\times \mathbb{Z}</m> and  <m>H = \{(a, a) | a \in  \mathbb{Z}\}</m>.</p></li>
<li><p>  <m>G = \left[\mathbb{R}^*; \cdot \right]</m>  and  <m>H = \{1, -1\}</m>.</p></li>
<li><p>  <m>G =\mathbb{Z}_2{}^5</m>  and <m>H = \langle (1, 1, 1, 1, 1)\rangle</m>.</p></li>
</ol></p>
</statement>
</exercise>
<exercise number="5"><statement><p>Assume that <m>G</m> is a group, <m>H \leq  G</m>, and <m>a, b \in  G</m>.  Prove that <m>a*H= b*H</m>  if and only if  <m>b^{-1}*a \in H</m>.</p>
</statement><answer><p>
<me>\begin{split}
a*H= b*H &amp;\Leftrightarrow a \in b H\\
		  &amp;\Leftrightarrow  a = b * h \textrm{      for  some }h \in H\\
       &amp;\Leftrightarrow b^{-1}*a = h \textrm{    for some }h \in H\\
       &amp; \Leftrightarrow  b^{-1}*a \in  H\\
\end{split}
</me>
</p></answer></exercise>
<exercise number="6" xml:id="exercise-15-2-6"><statement><p><ol label="(a)">
<li><p> Real addition modulo <m>r</m>,  <m>r > 0</m>, can be described as the operation induced on cosets of <m>\langle r\rangle</m> by ordinary addition. Describe a system of distinguished representatives for the elements of <m>\mathbb{R}/\langle r\rangle</m>.</p></li>
<li><p> Consider the trigonometric function sine. Given that <m>\sin (x+2\pi k) = \sin  x</m> for all <m>x\in \mathbb{R}</m> and <m>k\in \mathbb{Z}</m>, show how the distinguished representatives of <m>\mathbb{R}/\langle 2\pi \rangle</m> can be useful in developing an algorithm for calculating the sine of a number.</p></li>
</ol></p>
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="7"><statement><p>Complete the proof of <xref ref="theorem-cosets-partition" text="type-global"/> by proving that if <m>a \in  G</m>, <m>\rho:H \to  a*H</m> defined by <m>\rho(h)= a*h</m> is a bijection.</p>
</statement></exercise> 
</exercises>
</section>


