<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<section xml:id="s-Fields">
<title>Fields</title>
<index><main>Fields</main></index>



Although the algebraic structures of rings and integral domains are widely used and play an important part in the applications of mathematics, we
still cannot solve the simple equation \(a x = b\), \(a \neq  0\) in all rings or in all integral domains. Yet this is one of the first equations
we learn to solve in elementary algebra and its solubility is basic to innumerable questions. Certainly, if we wish to solve a wide range of problems
in a system we need at least all of the laws true for rings and the cancellation laws together with the ability to solve the equation \(a x = b\),
\(a \neq  0\). We summarize the above in a definition and list several theorems without proof that will place this concept in the context of the
previous section.

Definition: Field. A field is a commutative ring with unity such that each nonzero element has a multiplicative inverse. 



In this chapter, we denote a field generically by the letter <m>F</m>.  The letters k,.  <m>K</m> and <m>L</m> are also conventionally
used for fields.

\pmb{ Example16.2.1. }\(\textrm{    }[\mathbb{Q}, +, \cdot ]\), \([\mathbb{R}; +, \cdot ]\),  and \([\mathbb{C}; +, \cdot ]\)  are all fields.



Reminder: Since every field is a ring, all facts and concepts that are true for rings are true for any field.

<theorem xml:id="theorem-16.2.1"><title>16.2.1</title><index><main>16.2.1</main></index><statement></statement><proof></proof></theorem>. Every field is an integral domain. 



Of course the converse of Theorem 16.2.1 is not true.  Consider \([\mathbb{Z}; +, \cdot ]\).

<theorem xml:id="theorem-16.2.2."><title>16.2.2.</title><index><main>16.2.2.</main></index><statement></statement><proof></proof></theorem> Every finite integral domain is a field.

<theorem xml:id="theorem-16.2.3."><title>16.2.3.</title><index><main>16.2.3.</main></index><statement></statement><proof></proof></theorem> If p is a prime, then \(\mathbb{Z}_p\) is a field. 



Theorem 16.2.3  is immediate from Theorem 16.2.2.



Theorem 16.2.1 reminds us that the cancellation laws must be true for any field. Theorem 16.2.3 gives us a large number of finite fields, but we
must be cautious. This theorem does not tell us that all finite fields are of the form \(\mathbb{Z}_p\) , <m>p</m> a prime. To see this, let's
try to construct a field of order 4.

<example xml:id="ex-16.2.2: a field of order 4."><title>16.2.2: a field of order 4.</title><p></p></example>   First the field must contain the additive and multiplicative identities, 0 and 1, so, without loss
of generality, we can assume that the field we are looking for is of the form \(F = \{0, 1, a, b\}\).  Since there are only two nonisomorphic groups
of order 4, we have only two choices for the group table for \([F; +]\).   If the additive group is isomorphic to \(\mathbb{Z}_4\) then two of
the nonzero elements of F . would not be their own additive inverse (as are 1 and 3 in\(\mathbb{Z}_4\)).   Lets assume \(\beta \in F\)
is one of those elements and \(\beta +\beta =\gamma \neq 0\).  An isomorphism between the additive groups <m>F</m> and  \(\mathbb{Z}_4\) would
require that $\gamma $ in <m>F</m>  correspond with 2 in  \(\mathbb{Z}_4\).  We could continue our argument and infer that \(\gamma \cdot
\gamma =0\), producing a zero divisor, which we need to avoid if <m>F</m> is to be a field.   We leave the remainder of the argument to the
reader.   We can thus complete the addition table so that \([F;+]\)  is isomorphic to \(\mathbb{Z}_2{}^2\):



   \(\begin{array}{c|c}
 + &amp; 
\begin{array}{cccc}
 0 &amp; 1 &amp; a &amp; b \\
\end{array}
 \\
\hline
 
\begin{array}{c}
 0 \\
 1 \\
 a \\
 b \\
\end{array}
 &amp; 
\begin{array}{cccc}
 0 &amp; 1 &amp; a &amp; b \\
 1 &amp; 0 &amp; b &amp; a \\
 a &amp; b &amp; 0 &amp; 1 \\
 b &amp; a &amp; 1 &amp; 0 \\
\end{array}
 \\
\end{array}\)

Next, by Theorem 16.1.2, Part 1, and since 1 is the unity of <m>F</m>, the table for multiplication must look like:



   \(\begin{array}{c|c}
 \cdot  &amp; 
\begin{array}{cccc}
 0 &amp; 1 &amp; a &amp; b \\
\end{array}
 \\
\hline
 
\begin{array}{c}
 0 \\
 1 \\
 a \\
 b \\
\end{array}
 &amp; 
\begin{array}{cccc}
 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\
 0 &amp; 1 &amp; a &amp; b \\
 0 &amp; a &amp; - &amp; - \\
 0 &amp; b &amp; - &amp; - \\
\end{array}
 \\
\end{array}\)

Hence, to complete the table, we have only four entries to find, and, since <m>F</m> must be commutative, this reduces our task to filling in
three entries. Next, each nonzero element of <m>F</m> must have a unique multiplicative inverse. The inverse of <m>a</m> must
be either <m>a</m> itself or <m>b</m>. If \(a^{-1} = a\), then \(b^{-1}=b\). (Why?) But

 \(a^{-1} = a\text \Rightarrow  a \cdot  a = 1\). And if\(\text a \cdot  a = 1\), then \(a \cdot  b\) is equal to <m>a</m> or <m>b</m>.
In either case, by the cancellation law, we obtain \(a = 1\) or \(b = 1\), which is impossible. Therefore we are forced to conclude that \(a^{-1}
= b\) and \(b^{-1} = a\). To determine the final two products of the table, simply note that, \(a \cdot  a \neq  a\) because the equation \(x^2=x\)
has only two solutions, 0 and 1 in any field. We also know that \(a\cdot a\) cannot be 1 because <m>a</m> doesn{'}t invert itself and cannot be
0 because <m>a</m> can{'}t be a zero divisor. This leaves us with one possible conclusion, that  \(a \cdot  a = b\) and similarly \(b \cdot
 b = a\).  Hence, our multiplication table for <m>F</m> is:



   \(\begin{array}{c|c}
 \cdot  &amp; 
\begin{array}{cccc}
 0 &amp; 1 &amp; a &amp; b \\
\end{array}
 \\
\hline
 
\begin{array}{c}
 0 \\
 1 \\
 a \\
 b \\
\end{array}
 &amp; 
\begin{array}{cccc}
 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\
 0 &amp; 1 &amp; a &amp; b \\
 0 &amp; a &amp; b &amp; 1 \\
 0 &amp; b &amp; 1 &amp; a \\
\end{array}
 \\
\end{array}\)

The table listing the multiplicative inverse of each nonzero element is:



   \(\begin{array}{c|c}
 u &amp; u^{-1} \\
\hline
 
\begin{array}{c}
 1 \\
 a \\
 b \\
\end{array}
 &amp; 
\begin{array}{c}
 1 \\
 b \\
 a \\
\end{array}
 \\
\end{array}\)

We leave it to the reader to convince him- or herself, if it is not already clear, that \([F; +, \cdot ]\), as described above, is a field. Hence,
we have produced a field of order 4 and 4 is not a prime.



This construction would be difficult to repeat for larger fields.  In section 16.4 we will introduce a different approach to constructing fields
that will be far more efficient.



Even though not all finite fields are isomorphic to \(\mathbb{Z}_p\), for some prime <m>p</m> it can be shown that every field <m>F</m> must
have either:

<ol label=“1”>
<li><p> a subfield isomorphic to \(\mathbb{Z}_p\) for some prime <m>p</m>, or</p></li>
<li><p>  a subfield isomorphic to <m>\mathbb{Q}</m>.



In particular, if <m>F</m> is a finite field, a subfield of <m>F</m> must exist that is isomorphic to \(\mathbb{Z}_p\). One can think of all
fields as being constructed from either \(\mathbb{Z}_p\) or <m>\mathbb{Q}</m>.

<example xml:id="ex-16.2.3."><title>16.2.3.</title><p></p></example>  [<m>\mathbb{R}</m>, +, $\cdot $ ] is a field, and it contains a subfield isomorphic to [<m>\mathbb{Q}</m>, +, $\cdot $], namely <m>\mathbb{Q}</m>
itself.

<example xml:id="ex-16.2.4."><title>16.2.4.</title><p></p></example>  The field <m>F</m> that we constructed in Example 16.2.2 should have a subfield isomorphic to \(\mathbb{Z}_p\) for some
prime <m>p</m>.  From the tables, we note that the subset \(\{0, 1\}\) of \(\{0, 1, a, b\}\) under the given operations of F behaves exactly
like \(\left[\mathbb{Z}_2; +_2,\times _2\right]\).  Hence, the field in Example 16.2.2 has a subfield isomorphic to \(\mathbb{Z}_2\). Does it have
a subfield isomorphic to a larger field, say \(\mathbb{Z}_3\)? We claim not and leave this investigation to the reader (see Exercise 3 of this section).



We close this section with a brief discussion of isomorphic fields. Again, since a field is a ring, the definition of isomorphism of fields is the
same as that of rings. It can be shown that if <m>f</m> is a field isomorphism, then \(f\left(a^{-1} \right) = f(a)^{-1}\); that is, inverses
are mapped onto inverses under any field isomorphism. A major question to try to solve is: How many different non-isomorphic finite fields are there
of any given order? If <m>p</m> is a prime, it seems clear from our discussions that all fields of order <m>p</m> are isomorphic to \(\mathbb{Z}_p\).
But how many nonisomorphic fields are there, if any, of order 4, 6, 8, 9, etc? The answer is given in the following theorem, whose proof is beyond
the scope of this text.

<theorem xml:id="theorem-16.2.4."><title>16.2.4.</title><index><main>16.2.4.</main></index><statement></statement><proof></proof></theorem><ol label=“1”>
<li><p> Any finite field F has order \(p^n\) for a prime p and a positive integer n.</p></li>
<li><p>  For any prime p and any positive integer n there is a field of order \(p^n\) .</p></li>
<li><p>  Any two fields of order \(p^n\) are isomorphic. This field of order \(p^n\) is frequently referred to as the Galois field of order \(p^n\)
and it is designated by \(\textrm{ GF}\left(p^n\right.\)).



Evariste Galois (1811-32) was a pioneer in the field of abstract algebra.


\begin{center}\(\)
\end{center}


\caption{A French stamp honoring Evariste Galois (1811-32)}



Theorem 16.2.4 tells us  that there is a field of order \(2^2\textrm{ = 4}\), and there is only one such field up to isomorphism.   That is, all
such fields of order 4 are isomorphic to <m>F</m>, which we constructed in Example 16.2.2.


<exercises xml:id="exercises-16-2">
<title>Exercises for Section 16.2</title>



<exercisegroup>
<introduction><p>A Exercises</p></introduction>

<exercise number="1"><statement>  Write out the addition, multiplication, and <q>inverse</q> tables for each of the following fields'.

<ol label="a">
<li><p> \(\left[\mathbb{Z}_2, +_2 , \times _2\right]\)</p></li>
<li><p> \(\left[\mathbb{Z}_3, +_3 , \times _3\right]\)</p></li>
<li><p> \(\left[\mathbb{Z}_5, +_5 , \times _5\right]\)
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="2"><statement>  Show that the set of units of the fields in Exercise 1 form a group under the operation of the multiplication of the given field. Recall that
a unit is an element which has a multiplicative inverse.
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="3"><statement>  Complete the argument in Example 16.2.2 to show that if \([F; +]\) is isomorphic to\(\mathbb{Z}_4\), then <m>F</m> would have a zero divisor.
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="4"><statement> Write out the operation tables for \(\mathbb{Z}_2{}^2\).   Is \(\mathbb{Z}_2{}^2\) a ring? An integral domain? A field? Explain.
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="5"><statement>  Determine all values <m>x</m> from the given field that satisfy the given equation: 

<ol label="a">
<li><p> \(x + 1 = -1\)  over \textrm{ \(\mathbb{Z}_2\)} , \textrm{ \(\mathbb{Z}_3\)} and \textrm{ \(\mathbb{Z}_5\)}</p></li>
<li><p> \(2x + 1 = 2\) over \textrm{ \(\mathbb{Z}_3\)} and \textrm{ \(\mathbb{Z}_5\)}</p></li>
<li><p>\(3x + 1 = 2\) over \textrm{ \(\mathbb{Z}_5\)}
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="6"><statement> (a) Prove that if <m>p</m> and <m>q</m> are prime, then \(\mathbb{Z}_p \times  \mathbb{Z}_q\), is never a field. 



     (b) Can \(\mathbb{Z}_p{}^n\) be a field for any prime <m>p</m> and any positive integer \(n \geq  2\)?
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="7"><statement>  The following are equations over \textrm{ \(\mathbb{Z}_2\)} . Their coefficients come solely from \textrm{ \(\mathbb{Z}_2\)} . Determine all
solutions over \textrm{ \(\mathbb{Z}_2\)} ; that is, find all numbers in \textrm{ \(\mathbb{Z}_2\)} that satisfy the equations:

<ol label="a">
<li><p>  \(x^2 + x = 0\)</p></li>
<li><p>  \(x^2 + 1 = 0\)</p></li>
<li><p>  \(x^3 + x^2 + x + 1 = 0\)</p></li>
<li><p>  \(x^3 + x + 1 = 0\)
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="8"><statement> Determine the number of different fields, if any, of all orders 2 through 15. Wherever possible, describe these fields via a known field.



<subsection xml:id="ss-B Exercise"><title>B Exercise</title><index><main>B Exercise</main></index>
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="9"><statement>  Let \(\mathbb{Q}\left(\sqrt{2}\right) = \left\{\left.a + b\sqrt{2}\text \right| a, b \in  \mathbb{Q}\right\}\). 

<ol label="a">
<li><p> Prove that \(\left[\mathbb{Q}\left(\sqrt{2}\right), +, \cdot \right]\) is a field.</p></li>
<li><p> Show that <m>\mathbb{Q}</m> is a subfield of \(\mathbb{Q}\left(\sqrt{2}\right)\). For this reason, \(\mathbb{Q}\left(\sqrt{2}\right)\) is called an
extension field of <m>\mathbb{Q}</m>.</p></li>
<li><p>  Show that all the roots of the equation \(x^2 - 2 = 0\) lie in the extension field \(\mathbb{Q}\left(\sqrt{2}\right)\).</p></li>
<li><p>  Do the roots of the equation \(x^2 - 3 = 0\) lie in this field? Explain.

