<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<section xml:id="s-Field Extensions">
<title>Field Extensions</title>
<index><main>Field Extensions</main></index>



From high school algebra we realize that to solve a polynomial equation means to find its roots (or, equivalently, to find the zeros of the polynomials).
From Example 16.3.5 of the previous section we know that the zeros may not lie in the given ground field. Hence, to solve a polynomial really involves
two steps: first, find the zeros, and second, find the field in which the zeros lie. For economy{'}s sake we would like this field to be the smallest
field that contains all the zeros of the given polynomial. To illustrate this concept, let us reconsider Example 16.3.5.

<example xml:id="ex-16.4.1."><title>16.4.1.</title><p></p></example> Let \(f(x)=x^2 - 2 \in  \mathbb{Q}[x]\). It is important to remember that we are considering \(x^2-2\) over <m>\mathbb{ZQ}</m>,
no other field. We would like to find all zeros of \(f(x)\) and the smallest field, call it <m>S</m> for now, that contains them. The zeros are
\(x=\pm \sqrt{2}\), neither of which is an element of <m>\mathbb{ZQ}</m>. The set <m>S</m> we are looking for must satisfy the conditions:<ol label=“1”>
<li><p> S . be a field.</p></li>
<li><p>  <m>S</m> must contain <m>\mathbb{ZQ}</m> as a subfield,</p></li>
<li><p>  S . must contain all zeros of \(f(x)=x^2 - 2\), and

By condition (3),  \(\sqrt{2}\) must be an element of <m>S</m>, and, if <m>S</m> is to be a field, the sum, product, difference, and quotient
of elements in <m>S</m> must be in <m>S</m>. So \(\sqrt{2}\), \(\left(\sqrt{2}\right)^2\) , \(\left(\sqrt{2}\right)^3\), $\ldots $ , \(\sqrt{2}+\sqrt{2}\)
, \textrm{ \(\sqrt{2}-\sqrt{2}\)} , and \(\sqrt{2}/\sqrt{2}\)  must all be elements of <m>S</m>.   Further, since S contains <m>\mathbb{ZQ}</m>
as a subset, any element of <m>\mathbb{ZQ}</m> combined with \textrm{ \(\sqrt{2}\)} under any field operation must be an element of <m>S</m>. Hence,
every element of the form \(a + b \sqrt{2}\), where <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> can be any elements in <m>\mathbb{ZQ}</m>, is an element of S. We leave
to the reader to show that <m>S</m> is a field (see Exercise 1 of this section). We note that the second zero of \(x^2 - 2\), namely  \(-\sqrt{2}\),
is an element of <m>S</m>. To see this, simply take \(a = 0\) and \(b = -1\). The field <m>S</m> is frequently denoted as \(\mathbb{Q}\left(\sqrt{2}\right)\),
and it is referred to as an extension field of <m>\mathbb{ZQ}</m>.  Note that the polynomial \(x^2-2=\left(x-\sqrt{2}\right)\left(x+\sqrt{2}\right)\)
 factors into linear factors, or splits. , in \(\mathbb{Q}\left(\sqrt{2}\right)[x]\); that is, all coefficients of both factors are elements
of the field \(\mathbb{Q}\left(\sqrt{2}\right)\).

<example xml:id="ex-16.4.2."><title>16.4.2.</title><p></p></example> Consider the polynomial \(g(x) = x^2 + x + 1 \in  \mathbb{Z}_2[x]\). Let's repeat the previous example for \(g(x)\) over \(\mathbb{Z}_2\).
First, \(g(0) = 1\) and \(g(l) = 1\), so none of the elements of \(\mathbb{Z}_2\) are zeros of \(g(x)\). Hence, the zeros of \(g(x)\) must lie in
an extension field of \(\mathbb{Z}_2\). By Theorem 16.3.3, \(g(x) = x^2 + x + 1\) can have at most two zeros. Let <m>a</m> be a zero of \(g(x)\).
Then the extension field <m>S</m> of \(\mathbb{Z}_2\) must contain \(a \cdot a = a^2\), \(a^3\) , \(a + a\),  \(a+1\), and so on. But, since
\(g(a) = 0\), we have \(a^2 + a + 1 = 0\), or, equivalently, \(a^2= -(a+1)=a+1\) (remember, we are working in an extension of \(\mathbb{Z}_2\)).
  Note the recurrence relation we can use to reduce powers of <m>a</m>.

So far our extension field \(S\) of \(\mathbb{Z}_2\) is the set \(\{0, 1, a, a + 1\}\). For <m>S</m> to be a field, all possible sums, products,
differences, and quotients of elements in <m>S</m> must be in <m>S</m>. Let's try a few: 

\(a + a = a\left(1 +_2 1\right)=a\cdot 0=0\in S\)

Since \(a+a=0\),  \(-a = a\), which is in S.  . Adding three <m>a</m>'s together doesn't give us anything new: \(a + a + a = a\in
S\)   In fact, \(n a\) is in <m>S</m> for all possible positive integers <m>n</m>.  Next, 

$\quad \quad \quad \quad $\(\textrm{            }a^3 = a^2 \cdot  a \quad = (a +1)\cdot a \quad =\text a^2+ a\quad = (a+1)+a\quad =1 \in S\textrm{ }\)





Therefore,  \(a^{-1}= a+1\)   and \((a+1)^{-1}=a\).

It is not difficult to see that \(a^n\) is in <m>S</m> for all positive <m>n</m>.  Does <m>S</m> contain all zeros of \(x^2 + x + 1\)?
Remember, \(g(x)\) can have at most two distinct zeros and we called one of them <m>a</m>, so if there is a second, it must be \(a + 1\). To see
if \(a + 1\) is indeed a zero of \(g(x)\), simply compute \(f(a + 1)\): 

\(f(a+1)= (a + 1)^2 + (a+1) + 1\\
\\
\quad \quad = a ^2 +1 + a+1+ 1 \\
\\
\quad \quad =a^2+a + 1\\
\\
\quad \quad =0\)

Therefore, \(a + 1\) is also a zero of \(x^2 + x + 1\). Hence, \(S = \{0, 1, a, a + 1\}\) is the smallest field that contains \(\mathbb{Z}_2 = \{0,
1\}\) as a subfield and all zeros of \(x^2 + x + 1\). This extension field is denoted by \(\mathbb{Z}_2(a)\). Note that \(x^2 + x + 1\) splits in
\(\mathbb{Z}_2(a)\); that is, it factors into linear factors in \(\mathbb{Z}_2(a)\). We also observe that \(\mathbb{Z}_2(a)\) is a field containing
exactly four elements. By Theorem 16.2.4, we expected that \(\mathbb{Z}_2(a)\) would be of order \(p^2\) for some prime <m>p</m> and positive
integer <m>n</m>. Also recall that all fields of order \(p^n\) are isomorphic. Hence, we have described all fields of order \(2^2 = 4\) by finding
the extension field of a polynomial that is irreducible over \(\mathbb{Z}_2\).



The reader might feel somewhat uncomfortable with the results obtained in Example 16.4.2. In particular, what is <m>a</m>? Can we describe it
through a known quantity? All we know about <m>a</m> is that it is a zero of \(g(x)\) and that \(a^2= a + 1\). We could also say that \(a(a +
1) = 1\), but we really expected more. However, should we expect more? In Example 16.4.1, \(\sqrt{2}\) is a number we are more comfortable with,
but all we really know about it is that \(\alpha =\sqrt{2}\) is the number such that \(\alpha ^2= 2\). Similarly, the zero that the reader will obtain
in Exercise 2 of this section is the imaginary number \(i\). Here again, this is simply a symbol, and all we know about it is that \(i^2=-1\). Hence,
the result obtained in Example 16.4.2 is not really that strange.



The reader should be aware that we have just scratched the surface in the development of topics in polynomial rings. One area of significant applications
is in coding theory.


<exercises xml:id="exercises-16-4">
<title>Exercises for Section 16.4</title>



<exercisegroup>
<introduction><p>A Exercises</p></introduction>

<exercise number="1"><statement>  (a) Use the definition of a field to show that <m>\mathbb{ZQ}</m>(\textrm{ \(\sqrt{2}\)}) is a field.</p></li>
<li><p>  Use the definition of vector space to show that \(\mathbb{Q}\left(\sqrt{2}\right)\) is a vector space over <m>\mathbb{ZQ}</m>.</p></li>
<li><p>  Prove that \(\left\{1,\sqrt{2}\right\}\) is a basis for the vector space \(\mathbb{Q}\left(\sqrt{2}\right)\) over <m>\mathbb{ZQ}</m>, and, therefore,
the dimension of  <m>\mathbb{ZQ}</m>(\textrm{ \(\sqrt{2}\)}) over <m>\mathbb{ZQ}</m> is 2.
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="2"><statement>  (a) Determine the splitting field of \(f(x) = x^2+ 1\) over <m>\mathbb{R}</m>. This means consider the polynomial \(f(x) = x^2+1 \in  \mathbb{R}[x]\)
and find the smallest field that contains <m>\mathbb{R}</m> and all the zeros of \(f(x)\).  Denote this field by \(\mathbb{R}(i)\).



 (b)  <m>\mathbb{R}</m>(i) is more commonly referred to by a different name. What is it?



 (c)  Show that \(\{1, i\}\) is a basis for the vector space \(\mathbb{R}(i)\) over <m>\mathbb{R}</m>. What is the dimension of this vector space (over
<m>\mathbb{R}</m>)?
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="3"><statement> Determine the splitting field of \(x^4 - 5x^2 + 6\) over <m>\mathbb{ZQ}</m>.
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="4"><statement>  (a) Factor \(x^2 + x + 1\) into linear factors in \(\mathbb{Z}_2(a)\).</p></li>
<li><p>  Write out the field tables for the field \(\mathbb{Z}_2(a)\) and compare the results to the tables of Example 16.2.2.</p></li>
<li><p>  Cite a theorem and use it to show why the results of part b were to be expected.
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="5"><statement> (a) Show that \(x^3+ x + 1\) is irreducible over \(\mathbb{Z}_2\).</p></li>
<li><p> Determine the splitting field of \(x^3+ x + 1\) over \(\mathbb{Z}_2\).</p></li>
<li><p>  Use Theorem 16.2.4 to illustrate that you have described all fields of order \(2^3\) .
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="6"><statement> (a) List all polynomials of degree 1, 2, 3, and 4 over \(\mathbb{Z}_2 = \textrm{ GF}(2)\).</p></li>
<li><p> Use your results in part a and list all irreducible polynomials of degree 1, 2, 3, and 4.</p></li>
<li><p>  Determine the splitting fields of each of the polynomials in part b.</p></li>
<li><p>  What is the order of each of the splitting fields obtained in part c? Explain your results using Theorem 16.2.4.
