<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xml:id="s-propositions-logic-operators"><title>Propositions and Logical Operators</title>
<subsection xml:id="ss-propositions"><title>Propositions</title>
<definition xml:id="def-proposition"><title>Proposition</title><idx>proposition</idx><statement><p> A proposition is a sentence to which one and only one of the terms <em>true</em> or <em>false</em> can be meaningfully applied.</p></statement></definition>
<example xml:id="some-propositions"><title>Some Propositions</title>
<statement><p><q>Four is even,</q>, <q><m>4 \in  \{1,3, 5\}</m></q> and <q><m>43 > 21</m></q> are propositions.</p></statement></example>

<p>In traditional logic, a declarative statement with a definite truth value is considered a proposition. Although our ultimate aim is to discuss mathematical logic, we won't separate ourselves completely from the traditional setting. This is natural because the basic assumptions, or postulates, of mathematical logic are modeled after the logic we use in everyday life. Since compound sentences are frequently used in everyday speech, we expect that logical propositions contain connectives like the word <q>and.</q> The statement <q>Europa supports life or Mars supports life</q> is a proposition and, hence,
must have a definite truth value. Whatever that truth value is, it should be the same as the truth value of <q>Mars supports life or Europa supports life.</q></p>
</subsection>
<subsection xml:id="ss-logical-operations"><title>Logical Operations</title>
<p>There are several ways in which we commonly combine simple statements into compound ones. The words/phrases <em>and</em>, <em>or</em>, <em>not</em>, <em>if ... then...</em>, and <em>...if and only if ...</em> can be added to one or more propositions to create a new proposition. To avoid any confusion, we will precisely define each one's meaning and introduce its standard symbol.  With the exception of negation (<em>not</em>), all
of the operations act on pairs of propositions. Since each proposition has two possible truth values, there are four ways that truth can be assigned to two propositions. In defining the effect that a logical operation has on two propositions, the result must be specified for all four cases. The most convenient way of doing this is with a truth table, which we will illustrate by defining the word <em>and</em>.</p>

<definition xml:id="def-conjunction"><title>Logical Conjunction</title><idx>conjunction, Logical</idx>
<notation>
<usage><m>p \land q</m></usage><description> the conjunction, <m>p \textrm{ and } q</m>  </description>
</notation><statement><p> If <m>p</m> and <m>q</m> are propositions, their conjunction, <m>p \textrm{ and } q</m> (denoted <m>p \land q</m>), is defined by the truth table <me>
\begin{array}{ccc}
 p &amp; q &amp; p\land q \\
 \hline
 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\
 0 &amp; 1 &amp; 0 \\
 1 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\
 1 &amp; 1 &amp; 1 \\
\end{array}
</me>
</p></statement>

</definition>


<p>
Notes:</p>
<p><ol marker="(a)">
<li><p>The numbers 0 and 1 are used to denote false and true, respectively. This is 
consistent with the way that many programming languages treat logical, or Boolean, variables since a single bit, 0 or 1, can represent a truth value.  Many people use either False/True or F/T instead of 0/1 in truth table.  Although 0/1 usage seems to be in the minority, we prefer to use it in order make a connection with the binary representation of numbers, as pointed out below.</p>
<p>One notable case where False/True notation is used is in Sage, as can be seen in the following Sage cell.  Notice that Sage uses an ampersand for the conjunction symbol.</p>
<sage>
<input>
r = propcalc.formula('p &amp; q')
r.truthtable()
</input>
<output>
p      q      value
False  False  False  
False  True   False  
True   False  False  
True   True   True 
</output>
</sage>

</li>
<li><p> To read this truth table, you must realize that any one line represents a case: one possible set of truth values for <m>p</m> and <m>q</m>.</p></li>

<li><p>For each case, the symbol under <m>p</m> represents the truth value of <m>p</m>. The same is true for <m>q</m>. The symbol under <m>p \land q</m> represents its truth value for that case. For example, the second row of the truth table represents the case in which <m>p</m> is false, <m>q</m> is true, and the resulting truth value for <m>p \land q</m> is false. As in everyday speech, <m>p \land q</m> is true only when both propositions are true.</p></li>
<li><p>Just as the letters <m>x</m>, <m>y</m> and <m>z</m> are frequently used in algebra to represent numeric variables, <m>p</m>, <m>q</m> and <m>r</m> seem to be the most commonly used symbols for logical variables. When we say that <m>p</m> is a logical variable, we mean that any proposition can take the place of <m>p</m>.</p></li>
<li><p>One final comment: The order in which we list the cases in a truth table is standardized in this book. If the truth table involves two simple propositions, the numbers under the simple propositions can be interpreted as the two-digit binary integers in increasing order, 00, 01, 10, and 11, for 0, 1, 2, and 3, respectively.</p></li>
</ol>
</p>

<definition xml:id="def-disjunction"><title>Logical Disjunction</title><idx>disjunction, Logical</idx><notation>
<usage><m> p \lor q</m></usage><description> the disjunction, <m>p \textrm{ or } q</m>  </description>
</notation><statement><p> If <m>p</m> and <m>q</m> are propositions, their disjunction, <m>p \textrm{ or } q</m> (denoted <m>p \lor q</m>), is defined by the truth table <me>
\begin{array}{ccc}
 p &amp; q &amp; p\lor q \\
 \hline
 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\
 0 &amp; 1 &amp; 1 \\
 1 &amp; 0 &amp; 1 \\
 1 &amp; 1 &amp; 1 \\
\end{array}
</me>
</p></statement>

</definition>


<definition xml:id="def-negation"><title>Logical Negation</title><idx>Negation, Logical</idx><notation>
<usage><m>\neg p</m></usage><description> the negation of <m>p</m>, <q>not <m>p</m></q>  </description>
</notation><statement><p> If <m>p</m> is a proposition, its negation, <m>\textrm{not } p</m>,  denoted <m>\neg p</m>, and is defined by the truth table
<me>\begin{array}{cc}
 p &amp; \neg p \\
\hline
 0 &amp; 1 \\
 1 &amp; 0 \\
\end{array}
</me>
</p></statement>

</definition>
<p>Note: Negation is the only standard operator that acts on a single proposition; hence only two cases are needed.</p>
<p>Consider the following propositions from everyday speech:</p>
<p><ol marker="(a)"><li><p>I'm going to quit if I don't get a raise.</p></li>
<li><p>If I pass the final, then I'll graduate.</p></li>
<li><p>I'll be going to the movies provided that my car starts.</p></li>
</ol>
</p>
<p>All three propositions are conditional, they can all be restated to fit into the form  <q>If <em>Condition</em>, then <em>Conclusion</em>.</q> For example, the first statement can be rewritten as <q>If I don't get a raise, then I'm going to quit.</q></p>

<p>A conditional statement is meant to be interpreted as a guarantee; if the condition is true, then the conclusion is expected to be true. It says no more and no less.</p>

<definition xml:id="def-conditional"><title>Conditional Statement</title><idx>Conditional Statement</idx>
<notation><usage><m>p \to  q</m></usage>
<description>The conditional proposition If <m>p</m> then <m>q</m>.</description>
</notation>
<statement><p>The conditional statement <q>If <m>p</m> then <m>q</m>,</q> denoted <m>p \rightarrow  q</m>, is defined by the truth table</p>
<table xml:id="tt-conditional">
<title>Truth Table for <m>p \rightarrow q</m></title>
<tabular  halign="center">
 <row bottom="major"><cell><m>p</m> </cell><cell><m> q</m> </cell><cell><m> p \rightarrow q </m></cell></row>
 <row><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell></row>
 <row><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 1 </cell></row>
 <row><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row>
 <row><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 1 </cell></row>
 </tabular>
</table>

</statement>

</definition>

<example xml:id="conditional-analysis"><title>Analysis of a Conditional Proposition</title><p> Assume your instructor told you <q>If you receive a grade of 95 or better in the final examination, then you will receive
an A in this course.</q> Your instructor has made a promise to you. If you fulfill his condition, you expect the conclusion
(getting an A) to be forthcoming. Suppose your graded final has been returned to you. Has your instructor told the truth 
or is your instructor guilty of a falsehood?</p>
<p>Case I: Your final exam score was less than 95 (the condition is false) and you did not receive an A (the conclusion is false). The instructor told the truth.</p>
<p>Case II: Your final exam score was less than 95, yet you received an A for the course. The instructor told the truth. (Perhaps your overall course average was excellent.) </p>
<p>Case III: Your final exam score was greater than 95, but you did not receive an A. The instructor lied.</p>
<p>Case IV: Your final exam score was greater than 95, and you received an A. The instructor told the truth.</p>
<p>To sum up, the only case in which a conditional proposition is false is when the condition is true and the conclusion is false.</p>
</example>

<p>The order of the condition and conclusion in a conditional proposition is important. If the condition and conclusion are exchanged, a different proposition is produced.</p>

<definition xml:id="def-converse"><title>Converse</title><idx>Converse</idx><statement><p> The converse of the proposition <m>p \rightarrow q</m> is the proposition <m>q \rightarrow p</m>.</p></statement></definition>

<p>The converse of <q>If you receive a grade of 95 or better in the final exam, then you will receive an A in this course,</q> is <q>If you receive an A in this course, then you received a grade of 95 or better in the final exam.</q> It should be clear that these two statements say different things.</p>
<p>There <em>is</em> a proposition related to <m>p \rightarrow q</m> that does have the same logical meaning.  This is the contrapositive.</p>

<definition xml:id="def-contrapositive"><title>Contrapositive</title><idx>Contrapositive</idx>
<statement><p> The contrapositive of the proposition <m>p \rightarrow q</m> is the proposition <m>\neg q \rightarrow \neg p</m>.</p></statement></definition>

<p>As we will see when we discuss logical proofs, we can prove a conditional proposition by proving its contrapositive, which may be somewhat easier.</p>

<p>Finally, there is a third variation on the proposition <m>p \rightarrow q</m>, the inverse, which we will see that has the same logical meaning as the converse.</p>

<definition xml:id="def-inverse-proposition"><title>Logical Inverse</title>
<idx><h>Inverse</h><h>Logical</h></idx>
<statement><p> The inverse of the proposition <m>p \rightarrow q</m> is the proposition <m>\neg p \rightarrow \neg q</m>.</p></statement></definition>
<p>The inverse of <q>If it snows today, we have a day off.</q>  would be <q>If it doesn't snow today, we don't have a day off.</q>  Can you see that the original proposition and the inverse are saying different things?</p>

<p>Our final logical operator is a conjunction of two conditionals</p>


<definition xml:id="def-biconditional"><title>Biconditional Proposition</title><idx>Biconditional Proposition</idx>
<notation>
<usage><m> p \leftrightarrow q</m></usage><description> The biconditional proposition <m>p</m>
if and only if <m>q</m>  </description>
</notation><statement><p>If <m>p</m> and <m>q</m> are propositions, the biconditional statement <q><m>p</m>
if and only if <m>q</m>,</q> denoted <m>p \leftrightarrow q</m>, is defined by the truth table
<me>
\begin{array}{ccc}
 p &amp; q &amp; p\leftrightarrow q \\
 \hline
 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 1 \\
 0 &amp; 1 &amp; 0 \\
 1 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\
 1 &amp; 1 &amp; 1 \\
\end{array}
</me>
</p></statement>

</definition>
<p>Note that <m>p \leftrightarrow q</m> is true when <m>p</m> and <m>q</m> have the same truth values. It is common to abbreviate <q>if and only if</q> to <q>iff.</q></p>
<p>Although <q>if ... then...</q> and <q> ...if and only if ...</q> are frequently used in everyday speech,
 there are several alternate forms that you should be aware of. They are summarized in the following lists.</p>  
<p>All of the following are equivalent to <q>If <m>p</m> then <m>q</m></q>:</p>
<p><ul>
<li><p><m>p</m> implies <m>q</m>.</p></li>
<li><p><m>q</m> follows from <m>p</m>.</p></li>
<li><p><m>p</m>, only if <m>q</m>.</p></li>
<li><p><m>q</m>, if <m>p</m>.</p></li>
<li><p><m>p</m> is sufficient for <m>q</m>.</p></li>
<li><p><m>q</m> is necessary for <m>p</m>.</p></li>
</ul>
</p>
<p>All of the following are equivalent to <q><m>p</m> if and only if <m>q</m></q>:</p>	
<p>
<ul>
<li><p><m>p</m> is necessary and sufficient for <m>q</m>.</p></li>
<li><p><m>p</m> is equivalent to <m>q</m>.</p></li>
<li><p>If <m>p</m>, then <m>q</m>, and if <m>q</m>, then <m>p</m>.</p></li>
<li><p>If <m>p</m>, then <m>q</m> and conversely.</p></li>
</ul>
</p>
</subsection>
<exercises xml:id="exercises-3-1">
<title>Exercises</title>

<exercise number="1">
<statement><p>Let <m>d</m> = <q>I like discrete structures</q>, <m>c</m> = <q>I will pass this course</q> and <m>s</m> = <q>I will do my assignments.</q>  Express each of the following propositions in symbolic form:</p>
<p><ol marker="(a)">
<li><p>I like discrete structures and I will pass this course.</p></li>
<li><p>I will do my assignments or I will not pass this course.</p></li>
<li><p>It is not true that I both like discrete structures, and will do my assignments.</p></li>
<li><p>I will not do my assignment and I will not pass this course.</p></li>
</ol></p>
</statement>
<answer><p><ol marker="(a)" cols="2">
<li> <m>d\land c</m></li>
<li> <m>s\lor \neg c</m></li>
<li> <m>\neg (d\land s)</m> </li>
<li> <m>\neg s\land \neg c</m></li>
</ol></p>
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise number="2">
<statement><p>
For each of the following propositions, identify simple propositions, express the compound proposition in symbolic form, and determine whether it is true or false:</p>
<p><ol marker="(a)">
<li><p>The world is flat or zero is an even integer.</p></li>
<li><p>If 432,802 is a multiple of 4, then 432,802 is even.</p></li>
<li><p>5 is a prime number and 6 is not divisible by 4. </p></li>
<li><p><m>3 \in \mathbb{Z}</m> and <m>3 \in  \mathbb{Q}</m>.</p></li>
<li><p><m>2/3 \in  \mathbb{Z}</m> and <m>2/3 \in  \mathbb{Q}</m>.</p></li>
<li><p>The sum of two even integers is even and the sum of two odd integers is odd.</p></li>
</ol></p>
</statement>
<answer component="im">
<p><ol marker="(a)">
<li><p><m>p</m>: The world is flat,  <m>q</m>: zero is an even integer.  <m>p \lor q</m>  is true since <m>q</m> is true.</p></li>
<li><p><m>p</m>: 432,802 is a multiple of 4,  <m>q</m>: 432,802 is a multiple of 4.  <m>p\lor q</m>  is true because <m>p</m> is false.</p></li>
<li><p><m>p</m>: 5 is a prime number, <m>q</m>: 6 is not divisible by 4.  <m>p \land q</m> is true since both <m>p</m> and <m>q</m> are true. </p></li>
<li><p><m>p</m>: <m>3 \in \mathbb{Z}</m>, <m>q</m>: <m>3 \in  \mathbb{Q}</m>. <m>p \land q</m> is true since both <m>p</m> and <m>q</m> are true.</p></li>
<li><p><m>p</m>: <m>2/3 \in \mathbb{Z}</m>, <m>q</m>: <m>2/3 \in  \mathbb{Q}</m>. <m>p \land q</m> is false  since <m>p</m> is false.</p></li>
<li><p><m>p</m>:The sum of two even integers is even, <m>q</m>: The sum of two odd integers is odd. <m>p \land q</m> is false  since <m>q</m> is false. </p></li>
</ol></p>
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise number="3">
<statement><p>Let <m>p =</m><q><m> 2 \leq 5</m></q>, <m>q</m> = <q>8 is an even integer,</q> and <m>r</m> = <q>11 is a prime number.</q> Express the following as a statement in English and determine whether the statement is true or false:</p>
<p><ol marker="(a)" cols="2">
<li><p> <m>\neg  p \land  q</m> </p></li>
<li><p> <m>p\rightarrow q</m></p></li>
<li><p> <m>(p \land q)\to r</m> </p></li>
<li><p> <m>p \rightarrow (q \lor  (\neg r))</m></p></li>
<li><p> <m>p \rightarrow ((\neg q)\lor  (\neg r))</m></p></li>
<li><p> <m>(\neg q) \rightarrow  (\neg p)</m></p></li>
</ol></p>
</statement>
<answer><p><ol marker="(a)"><li> <m>2>5</m> and 8 is an even integer. False.</li>
<li> If <m>2\leqslant 5</m> then 8 is an even integer. True.</li>
<li> If <m>2\leqslant 5</m> and 8 is an even integer then 11 is a prime number. True.</li>
<li> If <m>2\leqslant 5</m> then either 8 is an even integer or 11 is not a prime number. True.</li>
<li> If <m>2\leqslant 5</m> then either 8 is an odd integer or 11 is not a prime number. False.</li>
<li>If 8 is not an even integer then <m>2>5</m>. True.</li>
</ol></p>
</answer></exercise>
<exercise number="4">
<statement><p>Rewrite each of the following statements using the other conditional forms:</p>
<p><ol marker="(a)">
<li><p>It is sufficient for an integer to be even that it is a multiple of four.</p></li>
<li><p>The fact that a polygon is a square is a sufficient condition that it is a rectangle.</p></li>
<li><p>If <m>x = 5</m>, then <m>x^2=25</m>.</p></li>
<li><p>If <m>x^2 - 5x + 6 = 0</m>, then <m>x = 2</m> or <m>x = 3</m>.</p></li>
<li><p> <m>x^2=y^2</m> is a necessary condition for <m>x = y</m>. </p></li>
</ol></p>
</statement>
<answer component="im">
<p>Some possible answers. <ol marker="(a)">
<li><p>If an in integer is a multiple of four, then it is even.</p></li>
<li><p>If a polygon is a square, then it is a rectangle.</p></li>
<li><p>It is necessary that <m>x^2=25</m> for <m>x = 5</m> to be true.</p></li>
<li><p>It is sufficient for <m>x^2 - 5x + 6 = 0</m>, that <m>x = 2</m> or <m>x = 3</m>. For this example, the two propositions are equivalent so it is true that <q><m>x^2 - 5x + 6 = 0</m>, is necessary and sufficient for <m>x = 2</m> or <m>x = 3</m></q>, however the sample answer given here literally restates the given proposition.</p></li>
<li><p> If <m>x = y</m> then <m>x^2=y^2</m>. </p></li>
</ol></p>
</answer>

</exercise>
<exercise number="5">
<statement><p>Write the converse of the propositions in exercise 4. Compare the truth of each proposition and its converse.
</p></statement>
<answer><p> Only the converse of <m>d</m> is true.  The converse of (a) is <q>It it necessary for an integer to be a even that it be a multiple of four.</q>  This is false because 6 is even and it isn't a multiple of four.</p></answer>
</exercise>

</exercises>
</section>