<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xml:id="s-properties-of-functions"><title>Properties of Functions </title><idx>Properties of Functions</idx>
<subsection><title>Properties</title>
<p>Consider the following functions:</p>
<p>Let <m>A = \{1, 2, 3, 4\}</m> and <m>B = \{a, b, c, d\}</m>, and define <m>f:A \rightarrow  B</m> by 
<me>f(1) = a, f(2) = b, f(3) = c \textrm{ and } f(4) = d</me>
</p>
<p>Let <m>A = \{1, 2, 3, 4\}</m> and <m>B = \{a, b, c, d\}</m>, and define <m>g:A \rightarrow  B</m> by 
<me>g(1) = a , g(2) = b, g(3) = a \textrm{ and } g(4) = b.</me>
</p>

<p>The first function, <m>f</m>, gives us more information about the set <m>B</m> than the second function, <m>g</m>. Since <m>A</m> clearly has four elements, <m>f</m> tells us that <m>B</m> contains at least four elements since each element of <m>A</m> is mapped onto a different element of <m>B</m>. The properties that <m>f</m> has, and <m>g</m> does not have, are the most basic properties that we look for in a function. The following definitions summarize the basic vocabulary for function properties.</p>

<definition xml:id="def-injective-function"><title>Injective Function, Injection</title><idx><h>Function</h><h>Injective</h></idx><idx><h>Function</h><h>One-to-one</h></idx><idx>Injection</idx>
<statement><p>A function <m>f: A \rightarrow B</m> is injective if 
<me>\forall a, b\in  A, a\neq b \Rightarrow  f(a) \neq  f(b)</me>
An injective function is called an injection, or a one-to-one function.</p></statement></definition>

<p>Notice that the condition for an injective function is logically equivalent to
  <me> f(a) = f(b) \Rightarrow   a = b</me>. 
for all <m>a, b\in  A</m>.  This is often a more convenient condition to prove than what is given in the definition.</p>

<definition xml:id="def-surjective-function"><title>Surjective Function, Surjection</title><idx><h>Function</h><h>Surjective</h></idx><idx><h>Function</h><h>Onto</h></idx><idx>Surjection</idx>
<statement><p>A function <m>f: A \rightarrow B</m> is surjective if its range, <m>f(A)</m>, is equal to its codomain, <m>B</m>.  A surjective function is called a surjection, or an onto function.</p></statement></definition>
  <p>Notice that the condition for a surjective function is equivalent to 
<me>\textrm{For all } b \in  B\textrm{, there exists } a\in A \textrm{ such that } f(a)=b</me>.</p>

<definition xml:id="def-bijective-function">
<title>Bijective Function, Bijection</title>
<idx><h>Function</h><h>Bijective</h></idx>
<idx>Bijection</idx>
<statement><p> A function <m>f: A \rightarrow B</m> is bijective if it is both injective and surjective. Bijective functions are also called one-to-one, onto functions.</p></statement></definition>
<p>The function <m>f</m> that we opened this section with is bijective. The function <m>g</m> is neither injective nor
surjective.</p>
<example xml:id="ex-injective-notsurjective"><title>Injective but not surjective function</title><p>Let <m>A = \{1, 2, 3\}</m> and <m>B = \{a, b, c, d\}</m>, and define <m>f:A \rightarrow  B</m> by <m>f(1) = b</m>, <m>f(2) = c</m>, and <m>f(3)
= a</m>. Then <m> f </m> is injective but not surjective.</p></example> 
<example xml:id="ex-characteristic-properties"><title>Characteristic Functions</title><p>The characteristic function, <m>\chi _S</m>, in <xref ref="exercise-characteristic-function" text="type-global" />  is surjective if <m>S</m> is a proper subset of <m>A</m>, but never injective if <m>\lvert A \rvert \gt 2</m>.</p></example> 
</subsection>
<subsection><title>Counting</title>
<example xml:id="ex-classroom"><title>Seating Students</title><p>Let <m>A</m> be the set of students who are sitting in a classroom,  let <m>B</m> be the set of seats in the classroom, and let <m>s</m> be the function which maps each student into the chair he or she is sitting in. When is <m>s</m> one to one? When is it onto? Under normal circumstances, <m>s</m>  would always be injective since no two different students would be in the same seat.  In order for <m>s</m> to be surjective, we need all seats to be used, so <m>s</m>  is a surjection if the classroom is filled to capacity.</p>
</example> 
<p>Functions can also be used for counting the elements in large finite sets or in infinite sets. Let's say we wished to count the occupants in an auditorium containing 1,500 seats. If each seat is occupied, the answer is obvious, 1,500 people. What we have done is to set up a one-to-one correspondence, or bijection, from seats to people. We formalize in a definition.</p>
<definition xml:id="def-cardinality"><title>Cardinality</title><idx>Cardinality.</idx><notation><usage><m>\lvert A \rvert = n</m></usage><description><m>A</m> has cardinality <m>n</m></description></notation><statement><p>Two sets are said to have the same cardinality if there exists a bijection between them. If a set has the same cardinality as the set <m>\{1,2,3,\ldots , n\}</m>, then we say its cardinality is <m>n</m>.  </p></statement></definition>
<p>The function <m>f</m> that opened this section serves to show that the two sets <m>A=\{1, 2, 3, 4\}</m> and <m>B=\{a, b, c, d\}</m> have the same cardinality. Notice in applying the definition of cardinality, we don't actually appear to count either set, we just match up the elements. However, matching the letters in <m>B</m> with the numbers 1, 2, 3, and 4 is precisely how we count the letters.</p>
<definition xml:id="def-countable-set"><title>Countable Set</title><idx>Countable Set</idx><statement><p>If a set is finite or has the same cardinality as the set of positive integers, it is called a countable set.</p></statement></definition> 

<example xml:id="ex-the-alphabet"><title>Counting the Alphabet</title><p> The alphabet <m>\{A, B, C, . . . , Z\}</m> has cardinality 26 through the following bijection into the set <m>\{1,2,3,\ldots ,26\}</m>.
<me>
\begin{array}{ccccc}
 A &amp; B &amp; C &amp; \cdots  &amp; Z \\
 \downarrow  &amp; \downarrow  &amp; \downarrow  &amp; \cdots  &amp; \downarrow  \\
 1 &amp; 2 &amp; 3 &amp; \cdots  &amp; 26 \\
\end{array}
</me>.</p></example>



<example xml:id="ex-evens-eq-all"><title>As many evens as all positive integers</title><p>Recall that <m>2\mathbb{P}= \{b\in \mathbb{P} \mid b= 2k \textrm{ for some } k \in \mathbb{P} \}</m>.  Paradoxically, <m>2\mathbb{P}</m>  has the same cardinality as the set <m>\mathbb{P}</m> of positive integers. To prove this, we must find a bijection from <m>\mathbb{P}</m> to <m>2\mathbb{P}</m>.  Such a function isn't unique, but this one is the simplest: <m>f:\mathbb{P} \rightarrow  2\mathbb{P}</m> where <m>f(m) = 2m</m>.  Two statements must be proven to justify our claim that <m>f</m> is a bijection:</p>
<p><ul>
<li><p> <m>f</m> is one-to-one.</p>
<p>Proof: Let <m>a, b \in  \mathbb{P}</m> and assume that <m>f(a) = f(b)</m>. We must prove that <m>a = b</m>. 
<me> f(a) = f(b) \Longrightarrow  2a = 2b \Longrightarrow  a = b.</me> </p></li>
<li><p><m> f </m> is onto.</p>
<p>Proof:  Let <m>b \in  2\mathbb{P}</m>. We want to show that there exists an element <m>a \in  \mathbb{P}</m> such that <m>f(a) = b</m>. If <m>b \in 
2\mathbb{P}</m>, <m>b = 2k</m> for some <m>k \in  \mathbb{P}</m> by the definition of <m>2\mathbb{P}</m>. So we have <m>f(k) = 2k = b</m>. Hence, each element
of 2<m>\mathbb{P}</m> is the image of some element of <m>\mathbb{P}</m>. </p></li>
</ul></p>
</example> 

<p>Another way to look at any function with <m>\mathbb{P}</m> as its domain is creating a list of the form <m>f(1),f(2), f(3), \ldots</m>.  In the previous example, the list  is <m>2, 4, 6, \ldots</m>.  This infinite list clearly has no duplicate entries and every even positive integer appears in the list eventually.</p>

<p>A function <m>f:\mathbb{P}\to A</m> is a bijection if the infinite list <m>f(1), f(2), f(3), \ldots</m> contains no duplicates, and every element of <m>A</m> appears on in the list.  In this case, we say the <m>A</m> is <term>countably infinite</term>, or simply <term>countable</term>.</p>

<example xml:id="ex-infinity-paradox-1"><title>A First Paradox of Infinity</title><p>When studying infinity, paradoxes abound.  One of the first instances of this is when we observe that the set of even positive integers, in spite of the fact that they make up only half of the positive integers, has the same cardinality as the whole set of positive integers.  This follows from our definition of cardinality  with the function <m>f(k)=2k</m>, which is a bijection from the positive integers to the even positive integers. We can make a similar observation that the seemingly smaller set of powers of <m>10</m>, <m>\{10^0,10^1,10^2,10^3,\dots\}</m>, also has the same cardinality as the positive integer. Here, the function <m>g(k)=10^k</m> serves as our justification.</p>
<p>Going in the opposite direction, there are seemingly larger sets than the positive integer that are countably infinite.  One such example is the Cartesian product of the positive integers with itself, <m>\mathbb{P}\times \mathbb{P}</m>. A function that justifies this claim doesn't have such a neat formula, but it would start like this:
</p>
<table>
	<title></title>
<tabular>
	<row><cell colspan='4'><m>f(1)=(1,1)</m></cell>
	</row>
	<row><cell><m>f(2)=(1,2)</m></cell><cell colspan='3'><m>f(3)=(2,1)</m></cell>
	</row>
	<row><cell><m>f(4)=(1,3)</m></cell><cell><m>f(5)=(2,2)</m></cell><cell colspan='2'><m>f(6)=(3,1)</m></cell>
	</row>
	<row><cell><m>f(7)=(1,4)</m></cell><cell><m>f(8)=(2,3)</m></cell><cell><m>f(9)=(3,2)</m></cell><cell><m>f(10)=(4,1)</m></cell>
	</row>
</tabular>
</table>
<p>See the pattern?  If it continues, every positive integer will map to a different pair and every pair of positive integer will be in the range of <m>f</m>.</p>
</example> 

<p>Readers who have studied real analysis should recall that the set of rational numbers is a countable set, while the set of real numbers is not a
countable set. See the exercises at the end of this section for an another example of such a set.</p>

<p>We close this section with a theorem called the Pigeonhole Principle, which has numerous applications even though it is an obvious, common-sense statement. Never underestimate the importance of simple ideas. The Pigeonhole Principle states that if there are more pigeons than
pigeonholes, then two or more pigeons must share the same pigeonhole. A more rigorous mathematical statement of the principle follows.</p>

<theorem xml:id="th-pigeonhole-principle"><title>The Pigeonhole Principle</title><idx>Pigeonhole Principle</idx><statement><p>Let <m>f</m> be a function from a finite set <m>X</m> into a finite set <m>Y</m>. If <m>n\geq 1</m> and <m>\lvert X\rvert > n\lvert Y\rvert</m>, then there exists an element of <m>Y</m> that is the image under <m>f</m> of at least <m>n + 1</m> elements of X.</p></statement>
<proof><p>Assume no such element exists. For each <m>y \in Y</m>, let <m>A_y = \{x\in X \mid f(x) =y \}</m>.  Then it must be that <m>\lvert A_y \rvert \leq n</m>.  Furthermore, the set of nonempty <m>A_y</m> form a partition of <m>X</m>.   Therefore,  
<me> \lvert X \rvert = \sum_{y\in Y}{\lvert A_y \rvert} \leq n \lvert Y \rvert </me>
which is a contradiction.</p>
</proof></theorem>

<example xml:id="ex-names"><title>A duplicate name is assured</title><p>Assume that a room contains four students with the first names John, James, and Mary. Prove that two students have the same first name. We can visualize a mapping from the set of students to the set of first names; each student has a first name. The pigeonhole principle applies with <m>n = 1</m>, and we can conclude that at least two of the students have the same first name.</p>
</example> 

</subsection>

<exercises xml:id="exercises-7-2">
<title>Exercises</title>

<exercise number="1"><statement><p> Determine which of the functions in <xref ref="exercise-7-1-1" text="type-global"/> of Section 7.1 are one- to-one and which are onto.</p>
</statement>
<answer><p> The only one-to-one function and the only onto function is <m>f</m>.</p> 
</answer></exercise>
<exercise number="2"><statement>
<p><ol marker="(a)">
<li><p> Determine all bijections from <m>\{1, 2, 3\}</m> into <m>\{a, b, c\}</m>.</p></li>
<li><p>Determine all bijections from <m>\{1, 2, 3\}</m> into <m>\{a, b, c, d\}</m>.</p></li>
</ol></p>
</statement>
<answer component="im">
<ol marker="(a)">
<li><tabular top="major" halign="center">
<row>
		<cell><m>f_1 =\left(
		\begin{array}{ccc}
		 1 &amp; 2 &amp; 3 \\
		 a &amp; b &amp; c \\
		\end{array}
		\right)</m></cell>
		<cell><m>f_2=\left(
		\begin{array}{ccc}
		 1 &amp; 2 &amp; 3 \\
		 b &amp; c &amp; a \\
		\end{array}
		\right)</m></cell>
		<cell><m>f_3=\left(
		\begin{array}{ccc}
		 1 &amp; 2 &amp; 3 \\
		 c &amp; a &amp; b \\
		\end{array}
		\right)</m></cell>
</row>
<row>
		<cell><m>f_4=\left(
		\begin{array}{ccc}
		 1 &amp; 2 &amp; 3 \\
		 a &amp; c &amp; b \\
		\end{array}
		\right) </m></cell>
		<cell><m>f_5=\left(
		\begin{array}{ccc}
		 1 &amp; 2 &amp; 3 \\
		 c &amp; b &amp; a \\
		\end{array}
		\right)</m></cell>
		<cell><m>f_6=\left(
		\begin{array}{ccc}
		 1 &amp; 2 &amp; 3 \\
		 b &amp; a &amp; c \\
		\end{array}
		\right)</m></cell>
</row>
</tabular></li>
<li><p>There are no bijections since the range of any function on a domain having three elements cannot have more than three elements, so it can't be onto. </p></li>
</ol>
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise number="3"><statement><p> Which of the following are one-to-one, onto, or both?</p>
<p><ol marker="(a)">
 <li><p> <m>f_1:\mathbb{R} \rightarrow \mathbb{R}</m> defined by <m>f_1(x) = x^3 - x</m>.</p></li>
<li><p> <m>f_2 :\mathbb{Z} \rightarrow  \mathbb{Z}</m> defined by <m>f_2(x)= -x + 2</m>.</p></li>
<li><p> <m>f_3:\mathbb{N} \times \mathbb{N}\to \mathbb{N}</m> defined by <m>f_3(j, k) =2^j3^k</m>.</p></li>
<li><p> <m>f_4 :\mathbb{P} \rightarrow  \mathbb{P}</m> defined by <m>f_4(n)=\lceil n/2\rceil</m>, where <m>\lceil x\rceil</m> is the ceiling of <m>x</m>,
the smallest integer greater than or equal to <m>x</m>.</p></li>
<li><p> <m>f_5 :\mathbb{N} \rightarrow  \mathbb{N}</m> defined by <m>f_5(n)=n^2+n</m>.</p></li>
<li><p><m> f_6:\mathbb{N} \rightarrow  \mathbb{N} \times  \mathbb{N}</m> defined by <m>f_6(n)= (2n, 2n+1)</m>.</p></li>
</ol></p>
</statement>
<answer><p><ol marker="(a)">
<li><p><m>f_1</m> is onto but not one-to-one: <m>f_1(0)=f_1(1)</m>.</p></li>
<li><p><m>f_2</m> is  one-to-one and onto.</p></li>
<li><p><m>f_3</m> is  one-to-one but not onto.</p></li>
<li><p><m>f_4</m> is  onto but not one-to-one.</p></li>
<li><p><m>f_5</m> is  one-to-one but not onto.</p></li>
<li><p><m>f_6</m> is  one-to-one but not onto.</p></li>
</ol></p>
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise number="4"><statement><p> Which of the following are injections, surjections, or bijections on <m>\mathbb{R}</m>, the set of real numbers?</p>
<p><ol marker="(a)">
<li><p> <m>f(x) = -2x</m>.</p></li>
<li><p> <m>g(x) = x^2- 1</m>.</p></li>
<li> <p> <m>h(x)=\left\{ \begin{array}{cc}
 x &amp; x &lt; 0 \\
 x^2 &amp; x\geq 0 \\
\end{array} \right.</m></p></li>
<li><p> <m>q(x)=2^x</m></p></li>
<li><p> <m>r(x) =x^3</m></p></li>
<li><p> <m>s(x) = x^3-x</m></p></li>
</ol></p>
</statement>
<answer component="im">
<ol marker="(a)">
<li><p> <m>f</m> is a bijection.</p></li>
<li><p> <m>g</m> is neither an injection nor a surjection.</p></li>
<li> <p> <m>h</m> is a bijection.</p></li>
<li><p> <m>q</m> is an injection, but not a surjection.</p></li>
<li><p> <m>r</m> is a bijection.</p></li>
<li><p> <m>s</m> is a surjection but not and injection.</p></li>
</ol>
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise number="5"><statement><p> Suppose that <m>m</m> pairs of socks are mixed up in your sock drawer. Use the Pigeonhole Principle to explain why, if you pick <m>m + 1</m>
socks at random, at least two will make up a matching pair.</p>
</statement>
<answer><p> Let <m>X=\{\textrm{socks selected}\}</m> and <m>Y=\{\textrm{pairs of socks}\}</m> and define <m>f:X \to Y</m> where <m>f(x) =</m>the pair of socks that <m>x</m> belongs to . By the Pigeonhole principle, there exist two socks that were selected from the same pair.</p>
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise  number="6">
<statement><p>Given five points on the unit square, <m>\{(x,y) \mid 0 \leq x, y \leq 1 \}</m>, prove that there are two of the points a distance of no more than <m>\frac{\sqrt{2}}{2}</m> from one another.</p>
</statement>
<answer component="im"><p>Create four <q>pigeonholes</q> by drawing a vertical line and a horizontal line, both through the center of the square.  You can assign the boundaries between these small squares any way to care to. Now just observe that among the five points, there must be at least one <m>\frac{1}{2}\times\frac{1}{2}</m> square containing two points. Their maximium distance is <m>\frac{\sqrt{2}}{2}\quad \blacksquare</m> </p>
</answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="7"><statement><p>Let <m>A =\text{  }\{1, 2, 3, 4, 5\}</m>. Find functions, if they exist that have the properties specified below.</p>
<p><ol marker="(a)">
<li><p> A function that is one-to-one and onto.</p></li>
<li><p> A function that is neither one-to-one nor onto.</p></li>
<li><p> A function that is one-to-one but not onto.</p></li>
<li><p> A function that is onto but not one-to-one.</p></li>
</ol></p>
</statement>
<answer><p><ol marker="(a)"><li><p> <m>f(n)=n</m>, for example</p></li>
<li><p> <m>f(n)=1</m>, for example</p></li>
<li><p> None exist.</p></li>
<li><p> None exist.</p></li>
</ol></p>
</answer>

</exercise>
<exercise number="8"><statement><p><ol marker="(a)">
<li><p> Define functions, if they exist, on the positive integers, <m>\mathbb{P}</m>, with the same properties as in Exercise 7 (if possible).</p></li>
<li><p>Let <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> be finite sets where <m>|A|=|B|</m>. Is it possible to define a function <m>f:A \rightarrow  B</m> that is one-to-one but not onto? Is it possible to find a function  <m>g:A \rightarrow  B</m> that is onto but not one-to-one?</p></li>
</ol></p>
</statement>
<answer component="im">
<ol marker="(a)">
<li><p> There are an infinite number of correct answers here, but we will list some of the simplest ones.
<ul>
<li><p><m>i</m>, defined by <m>i(k)=k</m> is one to one and onto.</p></li>
<li><p><m>d</m>, defined by <m>d(k)=2k</m> is one to one but not onto.</p></li>
<li><p><m>h</m>, defined by <me>h(k) =\left\{
\begin{array}{cc}
 \frac{k-1}{2} &amp;  \textrm{ if } k \textrm{ is odd} \\
 \frac{k}{2} &amp; \textrm{if } k \textrm{ is even} \\
\end{array}
\right.</me> is onto but not one to one.</p></p></li>
<li><p><m>s</m>, defined by <m>s(k)=k^2</m> is neither one to one nor onto.</p></li>
</ul></p></li>
<li><p>It is not possible to define a function <m>f:A \rightarrow  B</m> that is one-to-one but not onto; nor is it possible to find a function  <m>g:A \rightarrow  B</m> that is onto but not one-to-one.  The two properties imply one another on finite sets of the same cardinality.</p></li>
</ol>
</answer>
</exercise>


<exercise number="9"><statement>
<p><ol marker="(a)"><li><p> Prove that the set of natural numbers is countable.</p></li>
<li><p>Prove that the set of integers is countable.</p></li>
<li><p>Prove that the set of rational numbers is countable.</p></li>
</ol></p>
</statement>
<answer><p><ol marker="(a)"><li><p> Use <m>s:\mathbb{N}\to \mathbb{P}</m> defined by <m>s(x)=x+1</m>.</p></li>
<li><p> Use the function<m>f:\mathbb{N}\to \mathbb{Z}</m> defined by <m>f(\text{x0}=x/2</m> if <m>x</m> is even and <m>f(x)=-(x+1)/2</m> if <m>x</m> is odd.</p></li>
<li><p>The proof is due to Georg Cantor (1845-1918), and involves listing the rationals
 through a definite procedure so that none are omitted and duplications are avoided.
  In the first row list all nonnegative rationals with denominator 1,
   in the second all nonnegative rationals with denominator 2, etc.
    In this listing, of course, there are duplications, for example, <m>0/1=0/2=0</m>,
     <m>1/1=3/3=1</m>, <m>6/4=9/6=3/2</m>, etc. To obtain a list without duplications follow the arrows in <xref ref="fig-sol-7-2-9" text="type-global"/>, listing only the circled numbers.</p>
 <p>We obtain: <m>0,1,1/2,2,3,1/3,1/4,2/3,3/2,4/1,\ldots</m> Each nonnegative rational appears in this list exactly once.
  We now must insert in this list the negative rationals, and follow the same scheme to obtain:
   <me>0,1,-1,1/2,-1/2,2,-2,3,-3,1/3,-1/3, \ldots</me>
    which can be paired off with the elements of <m>\mathbb{N}</m>.</p>
</li>
</ol></p>
<figure xml:id="fig-sol-7-2-9">
				 <caption>Enumeration of the rational numbers.
				 </caption>
				 <image width="100%" source="images/fig-sol-7-2-9.png">
				 </image>
	</figure>
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise number="10">
<statement><p><ol marker="(a)">
<li><p> Prove that the set of finite strings of 0's and 1's is countable.</p></li>
<li><p>Prove that the set of odd integers is countable.</p></li>
<li><p>Prove that the set  <m>\mathbb{N}\times  \mathbb{N}</m> is countable.</p></li>
<li><p>Prove that the set  <m>\mathbb{N}\times  \mathbb{N}\times  \mathbb{N}</m> is countable.</p></li>
</ol></p>
</statement>
<answer component="im">
<p>For each part, we provide a bijection with domain <m>\mathbb{P}</m> that proves that that each set is countable.
<ol marker="(a)">
<li><p>If <m>k=1 b_{n-1} \dots b_1 b_0</m>, map it to the string <m>b_{n-1} \dots b_1 b_0</m>  Note that <m>1</m> will map to the empty string, <m>\lambda</m>. </p></li>
<li><p>Map each odd positive integer to itself and any even positive integer, <m>2k</m> to <m>-2k+1</m></p></li>
<li><p>Similar to the function that proves that the rationals are countable, we follow paths diagonally from bottom to left side of an array of ordered pairs, as indicated in <xref ref="fig-sol-7-2-10c" text="type-local"/>.   A formula for this function isn't so simple, but clearly, it exists and every ordered pair is is that image of some positive integer. </p>
</li>
<li><p>If <m>p</m> is the function in the previous part of this exercise that maps the positive integers to <m>\mathbb{N}\times\mathbb{N}</m>, we list the images under <m>p</m> of each positive integer on the <m>y</m> axis of the array in <xref ref="fig-sol-7-2-10d" text="type-local"/>. Each point in the array can be thought of as a triple with first coordinate the <m>x</m> value and the second and third coordinates the coordinates of the <m>y</m> value.  We follow the same kind of paths in succession as the previous part the is exercise to list all triples.</p></li>
</ol>
</p>
<sidebyside widths="45% 45%">
<figure xml:id="fig-sol-7-2-10c">
				 <caption>Enumeration of the set <m>\mathbb{N}\times\mathbb{N}</m>
				 </caption>
				 <image width="100%" source="images/fig-sol-7-2-10c.png">
				 <description>Visual describing why  <m>\mathbb{N}\times\mathbb{N}</m> is countably infinite </description>
				 </image>
	</figure>
	<figure xml:id="fig-sol-7-2-10d">
				 <caption>Enumeration of the set <m>\mathbb{N}\times\mathbb{N}\times\mathbb{N}</m>
				 </caption>
				 <image width="100%" source="images/fig-sol-7-2-10d.png">
				 <description>Visual describing why  <m>\mathbb{N}\times\mathbb{N}\times\mathbb{N}</m> is countably infinite </description>
				 </image>
	</figure>
</sidebyside>

</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise number="11"><statement><p> Use the Pigeonhole Principle to prove that an injection cannot exist between a finite set <m>A</m> and a finite set <m>B</m> if the
cardinality of <m>A</m> is greater than the cardinality of <m>B</m>.</p>
</statement><answer><p> Let <m>f</m> be any function from <m>A</m> into <m>B</m>. By the Pigeonhole principle with <m>n=1</m>, there exists an element of <m>B</m> that is the image of at least two elements of <m>A</m>. Therefore, <m>f</m> is not an injection.
</p></answer>
</exercise>
<exercise number="12"><statement><p> The important properties of relations are not generally of interest for functions. Most functions are not reflexive, symmetric, antisymmetric,
or transitive. Can you give examples of functions that do have these properties?</p>
</statement>
<answer component="im">
<p>Given any domain <m>U</m>, the only function that is reflexive is the function <m>i</m>, defined by <m>i(a)=a</m> for all <m>a\in U</m>. This is the <xref ref="" text="type-global"/>, which is formally introduced in the next section.  This function has the other three properties, and is the equality relation on <m>U</m>. There are other functions have some of the individual properties.  For example, on the integer, the function <m>f</m> defined by <m>f(k)=-k</m> is symmetric. The function <m>g</m> defined by <m>g(k)=k+1</m> is antisymmetric. A constant function such as the function that maps each integer to zero is transitive, but not very interesting as far as transitivity is concerned..</p>
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise number="13"><statement><p> Prove that the set of all infinite sequences of 0's and 1's is not a countable set. </p>
</statement>
<answer><p> The proof is indirect and follows a technique called the Cantor diagonal process.
 Assume to the contrary that the set is countable, then the elements can be listed:

 <m>n_1,n_2,n_3,\ldots</m> where each <m>n_i</m> is an infinite sequence of 0s and 1s. Consider the array:
<me>
\begin{array}{c}
n_1=n_{11}n_{12}n_{13}\cdots\\
n_2=n_{21}n_{22}n_{23}\cdots\\
n_3=n_{31}n_{32}n_{33}\cdots\\
\quad \vdots\\
\end{array}
</me> 
</p>
   <p>We assume that this array contains all infinite sequences of 0s and 1s. Consider the sequence <m>s</m> defined by

<m>s_i=\begin{cases}
 0 &amp; \textrm{ if } n_{\textrm{ii}}=1 \\
 1 &amp; \textrm{ if } n_{\textrm{ii}}=0
\end{cases}</m>
</p>
<p>Notice that <m>s</m> differs from each <m>n_i</m> in the <m>i</m>th position and so cannot be in the list. This is a contradiction, which completes our proof.</p>
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise number="14"><statement><p> Prove that the set of all functions on the integers is an uncountable set.</p>
</statement>
</exercise>
<exercise  number="14">
<statement><p>Given five points on the unit square, <m>\{(x,y) \mid 0 \leq x, y \leq 1 \}</m>, prove that there are two of the points a distance of no more than <m>\frac{\sqrt{2}}{2}</m> from one another.</p>
</statement>
</exercise>

</exercises>
</section>