<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<chapter>
<title>Set Theory I</title>
<introduction number="no" id="Goals-for-Chapter-1">
<title>Goals for Chapter 1</title>
In this chapter we will cover some of the basic set language and notation that will be used throughout the text. Venn diagrams will be introduced in order to give the reader a clear picture of set operations. In addition, we will describe the binary representation of positive integers (Section 1.4) and introduce summation notation and its generalizations (Section 1.5).  
</introduction> 
<section xml:id="Set-Notation-and-Relations">
<title>Set Notation and Relations </title>
<subsection>
<title>The notion of a set</title>
<p>The term set is intuitively understood by most people to mean a collection of objects that are called elements (of the set). This concept is the
starting point on which we will build more complex ideas, much as in-geometry where the concepts of point and line are left undefined. 
Because a set is such a simple notion, you may be surprised to learn that it is one of the most difficult concepts for mathematicians to define to
their own liking. For example, the description above is not a proper definition because it requires the definition of a collection. (How would you
define <q>collection</q>?) Even deeper problems arise when you consider the possibility that a set could contain itself. Although these problems
are of real concern to some mathematicians, they will not be of any concern to us. 
Our first concern will be how to describe a set; that is, how do we most conveniently describe a set and the elements that are in it? If we are going to discuss a set for any length of time, we usually give it a name in the form of a capital letter (or occasionally some other symbol). In discussing set <m> A</m>, if <m> x</m> is an element of <m> A</m>, then we will write <m>x \in  A</m>. On the other hand, if <m> x</m> is not an element
of <m> A</m>, we write <m>x \notin  A</m>. The most convenient way of describing the elements of a set will vary depending on the specific set. </p>
<p><em> Enumeration.</em> When the elements of a set are enumerated (or listed) it is traditional to enclose them in braces. For example, the
set of binary digits is<m>\{0, 1\}</m> and the set of decimal digits is <m>\{0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9\}</m>. The choice of a name for these sets would
be arbitrary; but it would be <q>logical</q> to call them <m> B</m> and <m> D</m> , respectively. The choice of a set name is much like the
choice of an identifier name in programming. Some large sets can be enumerated without actually listing all the elements. For example, the letters
of the alphabet and the integers from 1 to 100 could be described as 
<m>A = \{a, b, c,\ldots , x, y, z\}</m>, and <m>G = \{1, 2, \ldots  , 99, 100\}</m>. 
The three consecutive <q>dots</q> are called an ellipsis. We use them when it is clear what elements are included but not listed. An ellipsis is
used in two other situations. To enumerate the positive integers, we would write <m>\{1, 2, 3,\ldots  \}</m>, indicating that the list goes on infinitely.
If we want to list a more general set such as the integers between 1 and <m> n</m>, where <m> n</m> is some undetermined positive integer, we
might write <m>\{1,\ldots ,n\}</m>.
</p>   
<p><em> Standard Symbols</em>. Frequently used sets are usually given symbols that are reserved for them alone. For example, since we will be
referring to the positive integers throughout this book, we will use the symbol <m>\mathbb{P}</m> instead of writing <m>\{1, 2, 3, \ldots \}</m>. A few
of the other sets of numbers that we will use frequently are: 
<ul>
<li><m>\mathbb{N}</m> for the natural numbers, <m>\{0, 1, 2, 3, \ldots \}</m></li>
<li><m>\mathbb{Z}</m> for the integers, <m>\{\ldots , -3, -2, -1, 0, 1, 2, 3,\ldots \}</m></li>
<li><m>\mathbb{Q}</m> for the rational numbers</li>
<li><m>\mathbb{R}</m> for the real numbers</li>
<li><m>\mathbb{C}</m> for the complex numbers</li>
</ul>
</p>	
<p><em> Set-Builder Notation</em>. Another way of describing sets is to use set-builder notation. For example, we could define the rational numbers as <m>\mathbb{Q}=\{a/b : a, b \in  \mathbb{Z}, b\neq 0\}</m>.  Note that in the set-builder description for the rational numbers: 
<ul><li> <m>a/b</m> indicates that a typical element of the set is a <q>fraction.</q> </li>
<li> The colon is read <q>such that</q> or <q>where,</q> and is used interchangeably with a vertical line, <m>\mid</m>. 
 </li>
<li> <m>a, b\in \mathbb{Z}</m> is an abbreviated way of saying <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> are integers. 
 </li>
<li> All commas in mathematics are read as <q>and.</q> 
</li>
</ul>
The important fact to keep in mind in set notation, or in any mathematical notation, is that it is meant to be a help, not a hindrance. We hope that notation will assist us in a more complete understanding of the collection of objects under consideration and will enable us to describe it in a concise manner. However, brevity of notation is not the aim of sets. If you prefer to write <m>a\in \mathbb{Z}</m> and <m>b\in \mathbb{Z}</m> instead of <m>a, b\in \mathbb{Z}</m>, you should do so. Also, there are frequently many different, and equally good, ways of describing sets. For example, <m>\left\{x\in
\mathbb{R}\left| x^{2 }-5x+6\right.=0\right\}</m> and <m>\left\{x \left| x\in \mathbb{R}: x^{2 }-5x+6\right.=0\right\}</m> both describe the solution set <m>\{2, 3\}</m>. 
</p>
<p>A proper definition of the real numbers is beyond the scope of this text. It is sufficient to think of the real numbers as the set of points on a
number line. The complex numbers can be defined using set-builder notation as <m>\mathbb{C} = \{a + b i:a, b \in \mathbb{R}\}</m>, where <m>i^2 = -1</m>.  </p>
<p>In the following definition we will leave the word <q>finite</q> undefined.   
</p>
<definition  xml:id="finite-set">
	<title> Finite Set.</title>
	<statement>A set is a finite set if it has a finite number of elements. Any set that is not finite is an infinite set.
	</statement>
	<description>Informal definition of "finite set."</description>
</definition> 
<definition  xml:id="cardinality.">
<title> Cardinality.</title>
<statement>Let A be a finite set. The number of different elements in A is called its cardinality.
</statement>
<notation> <m>\lvert A \rvert </m></notation>
</definition>   
<p>As we will see later, there are different infinite cardinalities. We can't make this distinction now, so we will restrict cardinality to finite sets
until later.</p>
</subsection>
<subsection number="no">
<title>Subsets</title>
<definition  xml:id="subset.">
<title> Subset.</title>
<statement> Let <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> be sets. We say that <m>A</m> is a subset of <m>b</m>  if and only if every element of <m>A</m> is an element of <m>b</m>. 
</statement>
<notation> <m>A $\subseteq $ B</m></notation>
</definition>
<example  xml:id="Some_Subsets">
<title> Some Subsets </title>
<p><ol type="a">
<li> If <m>A = \{3, 5, 8\}</m> and <m>B = \{5, 8, 3, 2, 6\}</m>, then <m>A\subseteq B</m>. </li>
<li>  <m>\mathbb{N}\subseteq \mathbb{Z}\subseteq \mathbb{Q}\subseteq \mathbb{R}\subseteq \mathbb{C}</m> 
 </li>
<li>If <m>A = \{3, 5, 8\}</m> and <m>B = \{5, 3, 8\}</m>, then <m>A \subseteq  B</m> and <m>B \subseteq  A</m>. </li>
</ol>
</p>
</example>
<definition  xml:id="set_equality">
<title> Set Equality. </title>
<statement>Let <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> be sets. We say that <m>A</m> is equal to <m>B</m> (notation <m>A = B</m>) if and only if every element of
A is an element of B and conversely every element of B is an element of A; that is, <m>A \subseteq  B</m> and <m>B \subseteq  A</m>. 
</statement>
</definition>
<example  xml:id="set_equality_examples">
<title> Examples illustrating set equality</title>
<p><ol cols="1" style="a">
<li>In the previous example, <m>A = B</m>. Note that the ordering of the elements is unimportant. </li>
<li>The number of times that an element appears in an enumeration doesn't affect a set. For example, if <m>A = \{1, 5, 3, 5\}</m> and <m>B = \{1, 5, 3\}</m>, then <m>A = B</m>.  Warning to readers of other texts: Some books introduce the concept of a multiset, in which the number of occurrences of an element matters.</li> 
</ol>
</p>
</example> 
<p>A few comments are in order about the expression <q>if and only if</q> as used in our definitions. This expression means <q>is equivalent to saying,</q>
or more exactly, that the word (or concept) being defined can at any time be replaced by the defining expression. Conversely, the expression that
defines the word (or concept) can be replaced by the word. </p>
<p>Occasionally there is need to discuss the set that contains no elements, namely the empty set, which is denoted by <m>\emptyset</m>.
This set is also called the null set.</p> 
<p>It is clear, we hope, from the definition of a subset, that given any set <m> A</m> we have <m>A\subseteq A</m> and <m>\emptyset \subseteq A</m>. Both
<m>\emptyset</m> and <m> A</m> are called <em>improper subsets </em>of <m>A</m>. If <m>B \subseteq  A</m>, <m>B\neq \emptyset</m>, and <m>B\neq A</m>,
then <m>B</m> is called a <em> proper subset</em> of <m>A</m>.</p> 
</subsection>  
<exercises>
<title>Exercises for Section 1.1 </title>
<exercisegroup><introduction><p>A Exercises</p></introduction>
<exercise number="1">
<statement>
 List four elements of each of the following sets:
<ol cols="1" style="a">
 <li> <m>\{k \in  \mathbb{P} \mid {k - 1} \textrm{ is a multiple of 7}\}</m> </li>
 <li> <m>\{x \mid x \textrm{ is a fruit and its skin is normally eaten }\}</m></li>
 <li><m>\{x \in \mathbb{Q}\mid x\in \mathbb{Z}\}</m></li>
 <li> <m>\{2n \mid n \in \mathbb{Z}, n &lt; 0 \}</m></li>
 <li> <m>\{s \mid s = 1 + 2 + \cdots  + n, n \in \mathbb{P}\}</m></li>
 </ol>
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="2"><statement>  List all elements of the following sets:
<ol cols="1" style="a">
<li> <m>\{\frac{1}{n} \mid n \in \{3,4,5,6\}\}</m> 
  </li>
<li>  <m>\{\alpha \in  \textrm{the alphabet} \mid  \textrm{\alpha precedes F\ }</m> 
  </li>
<li> <m>\{-k \mid k \in \mathbb{P}\}</m> 
  </li>
<li> <m>\{n^2 \mid  n = -2, -1, 0, 1, 2\}</m> 
  </li>
<li> <m>\{n \in  \mathbb{P} \mid n \textrm{is a  factor of  24 }\}</m> 
  </li>
  </ol>
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="3"><statement>  Describe the following sets using set-builder notation. 
<ol cols="1" style="a">
<li> <m>\{ 5, 7, 9, \dots , 77, 79\}</m> </li>
<li>the rational numbers that are strictly between <m>-1</m> and <m>1</m> </li>
<li> the even integers</li>
<li> <m>\{-18, -9,0,9, 18,27, \dots \}</m> </li>
</ol>
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="4"><statement>  Use set-builder notation to describe the following sets: 
<ol cols="1" style="a">
<li><m>\{1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7\}</m> </li>
<li> <m>\{1, 10, 100, 1000, 10000\}</m>  </li>
<li> <m>\{1, 1/2, 1/3, 1/4, 1/5, . . .\}</m> </li>
<li>  <m>\{0\}</m></li>
</ol>
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="5"><statement>  Let <m>A = \{0, 2, 3\}</m>, <m>B = \{2, 3\}</m>, and <m>C = \{1, 5, 9\}</m>. Determine which of the following statements are true. Give reasons for
your answers. 
<ol cols="2" style="a">
<li><m>3 \in  A</m></li>
<li><m>\{3\} \in  A</m> </li>
<li><m>\{3\} \subseteq A</m></li>
<li> <m>B\subseteq A</m></li>
<li> <m>A\subseteq B</m></li>
<li><m>\emptyset \subseteq C</m> </li>
<li> <m>\emptyset \in A</m></li>
<li> <m>A\subseteq A</m></li>
</ol>
</statement></exercise>
</exercisegroup>
<exercisegroup><introduction><p>C Exercises</p></introduction>
<exercise number="6"><statement>  One reason that we left the definition of a set vague is Russell's Paradox. Many mathematics and logic books contain an account of this paradox.
Two references are Stoll and Quine. Find one such reference and read it.  
</statement></exercise>
</exercisegroup>
</exercises>
</section> 
<section xml:id="Basic_Set_Operations">
<title>Basic Set Operations  </title>
<subsection number="no">
<title>Definitions</title>
<definition  xml:id="intersection">
<title> Intersection</title>.
<statement> Let <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> be sets. The intersection of <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> (denoted by <m>A \cap  B</m>) is the set of all elements
that are in both <m>A</m> and <m>B</m>. That is, <m>A \cap  B = \{x:x \in  A \textrm{ and } x \in  B)</m>. 
</statement>
<notation> denoted by <m>A \cap  B</m></notation> 
</definition>
<example  xml:id="some_intersections">
<title>Some Intersections</title>
<p><ul>
<li> Let <m>A = \{1, 3, 8\}</m> and <m>B = \{-9, 22, 3\}</m>. Then <m>A \cap  B = \{3\}</m>.</li>
<li>Solving a system of simultaneous equations such as <m>x + y = 7</m> and <m>x - y = 3</m> can be viewed as an intersection. Let <m>A = \{(x,y): x + y = 7, x,y \in  \mathbb{R}\}</m> and <m>B = \{(x,y): x - y - 3, x,y\in  \mathbb{R}\}</m>. These two sets are lines in the plane and their intersection,
<m>A \cap  B = \{(5, 2)\}</m>, is the solution to the system. </li>
<li> <m>\mathbb{Z}\cap \mathbb{Q}=\mathbb{Z}</m>. </li>
<li>If <m>A = \{3, 5, 9\}</m> and <m>B = \{-5, 8\}</m>, then <m>A\cap  B =\emptyset</m>. </li>
</ul></p>
</example> 
<definition  xml:id="disjoint-sets.">
<title> Disjoint Sets.</title> <statement>Two sete are disjoint if they have no elements in common (as in Example 1.2.1 d). That is, <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> are disjoint if <m>A \cap  B = \emptyset</m>.
</statement> 
</definition>
<definition  xml:id="union.">
<title> Union.</title>
<statement> Let <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> be sets. The union of <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> (denoted by <m>A \cup  B</m>) is the set of all elements that are
in <m>A</m> or in <m>B</m> or in both A and B. That is, <m>A\cup B= \{x:x \in  A\textrm{ or } x\in  B\}</m>. 
It is important to note in the set-builder notation for <m>A\cup B</m>, the word <q>or</q> is used in the inclusive sense; it includes the case where
<m> x</m> is in both <m>A</m> and <m>B</m>.
</statement>
<notation> <m>A \cup  B</m></notation> 
 </definition>
<example  xml:id="some_unions">
<title>Some Unions</title>
<p><ul>
<li> If <m>A = \{2, 5, 8\}</m> and  <m>B = \{7, 5, 22\}</m>, then <m>A \cup  B = \{2, 5, 8, 7, 22\}</m>. </li>
<li> <m>\mathbb{Z}\cup \mathbb{Q}=\mathbb{Q}.</m> </li>
<li> <m>A \cup \emptyset  = A</m> for any set <m>A</m>.</li>
</ul></p>
</example>  
<p>Frequently, when doing mathematics, we need to establish a universe or set of elements under discussion. For example, the set <m>A = \{x : 81x^4 -16 = 0 \}</m> contains different elements depending on what kinds of numbers we allow ourselves to use in solving the equation <m>81 x^4 -16 = 0</m>. This set of numbers would be our universe. For example, if the universe is the integers, then <m>A</m> is empty. If our universe is the
rational numbers, then <m> A</m> is <m>\{2/3, -2/3\}</m> and if the universe is the complex numbers, then A is <m>\{2/3, -2/3, 2i/3, - 2i/3\}</m>.
</p>

<definition  xml:id="universe.">
<title> Universe.</title><statement> The universe, or universal set, is the set of all elements under discussion for possible membership
in a set. We normally reserve the letter <m> U</m> for a universe in general discussions.   
</statement>
</definition>
</subsection>
<subsection number="no">
<title>Set Operations and their Venn Diagams </title>
<p>When working with sets, as in other branches of mathematics, it is often quite useful to be able to draw a picture or diagram of the situation under consideration. A diagram of a set is called a Venn diagram. The universal set U is represented by the interior of a rectangle and the sets by disks inside the rectangle.</p> 
<example  xml:id="venn_diagram_examples">
<title>Venn Diagram Examples</title>
 <p>(a) <m>A \cap  B</m> is illustrated in the following figure by shading the appropriate region. 
           <figure xml:id="venn_diagram_intersection">
                    <caption>Venn Diagram</caption>
                    <image xml:id="sageplot-venn-intersection">
                        <description>A two set Venn Diagram for intersection</description>
                        <sageplot>
								m=2
								scale = 1.7
								sx=3
								sy=2
								centers = [(cos(n*2*pi/m), sin(n*2*pi/m)) for n in range(m)]
								clr = ['blue', 'blue', 'green']
								G = Graphics()
								r=lambda x,y:(x-centers[0][0])^2+(y-centers[0][1])^2 &lt; scale^2  and (x-centers[1][0])^2+(y-centers[1][1])^2 &lt; scale^2 
								G+=region_plot(r,(-sx,sx),(-sy,sy),plot_points=200,incol='lightblue',axes=False)
								for i in range(m):
									G += circle(centers[i], scale)
								for i in range(m):
									G += circle(centers[i], scale)
								G+=line([[-sx,-sy],[sx,-sy],[sx,sy],[-sx,sy],[-sx,-sy]],rgbcolor=(0,0,0))
								G+=text('B',centers[0],fontsize='x-large')
								G+=text('A',centers[1],fontsize='x-large')
								G
                        </sageplot>
                    </image>
                </figure>
 </p>               
<p>(b) The union <m>A \cup  B</m> is illustrated in the following figure.
            <figure xml:id="venn_diagram_union">
                    <caption>Venn Diagram for the union <m>A \cup  B</m> </caption>
                    <image xml:id="sageplot-venn-union">
                        <description>A two set Venn Diagram for union</description>
                        <sageplot>
								m=2
								scale = 1.7
								sx=3
								sy=2
								centers = [(cos(n*2*pi/m), sin(n*2*pi/m)) for n in range(m)]
								clr = ['blue', 'blue', 'green']
								G = Graphics()
								r=lambda x,y:(x-centers[0][0])^2+(y-centers[0][1])^2 &lt; scale^2  or (x-centers[1][0])^2+(y-centers[1][1])^2 &lt; scale^2 
								G+=region_plot(r,(-sx,sx),(-sy,sy),plot_points=200,incol='lightblue',axes=False)
								for i in range(m):
									G += circle(centers[i], scale)
								for i in range(m):
									G += circle(centers[i], scale)
								G+=line([[-sx,-sy],[sx,-sy],[sx,sy],[-sx,sy],[-sx,-sy]],rgbcolor=(0,0,0))
								G+=text('B',centers[0],fontsize='x-large')
								G+=text('A',centers[1],fontsize='x-large')
								G
                        </sageplot>
                    </image>
                </figure> 
In a Venn diagram, the region representing <m>A \cap  B</m> does not appear empty; however, in some instances it will represent the empty set. The same is true for any other region in a Venn diagram. 
</p>
</example>
<definition  xml:id="set_complement.">
<title>Complement of a set</title>
<statement>Let <m> A</m> and <m> B</m> be sets. The complement of <m> A</m> relative to <m> B</m> (notation
<m>B - A</m>) is the set of elements that are in <m> B</m> and not in <m> A</m>. That is, <m>B-A=\{x: x\in B \textrm{ and } x\notin A\}</m>. If <m>
U</m> is the universal set, then <m>U-A</m> is denoted by <m>A^c</m> and is called simply the complement of <m> A</m>. <m>A^c=\{x\in U : x\notin A\}</m>. 
</statement>
<notation><m>B - A</m>,<m>A^c</m></notation>
</definition>
 <example  xml:id="complements">
<title>Some Complements</title>
<statement>
<ol type="a">
<li> Let <m>U = \{1,2, 3, \text{...} , 10\}</m> and <m>A = \{2,4,6,8, 10\}</m>. Then <m>U-A = \{1, 3, 5, 7, 9\}</m> and <m>A - U= \emptyset</m>
</li>
<li> If <m>U = \mathbb{R}</m>, then the complement of the rational numbers is the irrational numbers. 
</li>
<li> <m>U^c= \emptyset</m> and <m>\emptyset ^c= U</m>. 
</li>
<li> The Venn diagram of <m>B - A</m> is represented in the following figure. 
            <figure xml:id="venn_diagram_complement1">
                    <caption>Venn Diagram for <m>B - A</m></caption>
                    <image xml:id="sageplot-venn-complement1">
                        <description>A Venn Diagram for the complement of <m>A</m> relative to <m>B</m></description>
                        <sageplot>
								m=2
								scale = 1.7
								sx=3
								sy=2
								centers = [(cos(n*2*pi/m), sin(n*2*pi/m)) for n in range(m)]
								clr = ['blue', 'blue', 'green']
								G = Graphics()
								r=lambda x,y:(x-centers[0][0])^2+(y-centers[0][1])^2 &lt; scale^2  and ~( (x-centers[1][0])^2+(y-centers[1][1])^2 &lt; scale^2 )
								G+=region_plot(r,(-sx,sx),(-sy,sy),plot_points=200,incol='lightblue',axes=False)
								for i in range(m):
									G += circle(centers[i], scale)
								for i in range(m):
									G += circle(centers[i], scale)
								G+=line([[-sx,-sy],[sx,-sy],[sx,sy],[-sx,sy],[-sx,-sy]],rgbcolor=(0,0,0))
								G+=text('B',centers[0],fontsize='x-large')
								G+=text('A',centers[1],fontsize='x-large')
								G
                        </sageplot>
                    </image>
                </figure> 
</li>
<li> The Venn diagram of <m>A^c</m> is represented in the figure below. 
            <figure xml:id="venn_diagram_complement2">
                    <caption>Venn Diagram for <m>A^{c}</m></caption>
                    <image xml:id="sageplot-venn-complement2">
                        <description>A Venn Diagram for the complement of a set.</description>
                        <sageplot>
								scale = 1.7
								sx=3
								sy=2
								G = Graphics()
								r=lambda x,y:  x^2+y^2 &gt; scale^2 
								G+=region_plot(r,(-sx,sx),(-sy,sy),plot_points=200,incol='lightblue',axes=False)
								G += circle([0,0], scale)
								G+=line([[-sx,-sy],[sx,-sy],[sx,sy],[-sx,sy],[-sx,-sy]],rgbcolor=(0,0,0))
								G+=text('A',[0,0],fontsize='x-large')
								G                        
                        </sageplot>
                    </image>
                </figure> 
</li>
<li> If <m>B\subseteq A</m>, then the Venn diagram of <m>A- B</m> is as shown in the following figure.   
            <figure xml:id="venn_diagram_complement3">
                    <caption>Venn Diagram for <m>A^{c}</m></caption>
                    <image xml:id="sageplot-venn-complement3">
                        <description>A Venn Diagram for the complement relative to a superset</description>
                        <sageplot>
								m=1
								scale = 1.7
								sx=3
								sy=2
								G = Graphics()
								r=lambda x,y:  x^2+y^2 &lt; scale^2 and (x-0.75)^2+y^2 &gt; 0.75^2
								G+=region_plot(r,(-sx,sx),(-sy,sy),plot_points=200,incol='lightblue',axes=False)
								G += circle([0,0], scale)
								G += circle([0.75,0], 0.75)
								G+=line([[-sx,-sy],[sx,-sy],[sx,sy],[-sx,sy],[-sx,-sy]],rgbcolor=(0,0,0))
								G+=text('A',[-1,0],fontsize='x-large')
								G+=text('B',[0.75,0],fontsize='x-large')
								G
                        </sageplot>
                    </image>
            </figure> 
</li>
<li> In the universe of integers, the set of even integers, <m>\{\ldots  , - 4,-2, 0, 2, 4,\ldots \}</m>, has the set of odd integers as its complement.
</li>
</ol>
</statement>
</example> 
<definition  xml:id="symmetric-difference.">
<title> Symmetric Difference.</title>
 <statement>Let A and B be sets. The symmetric difference of A and B (denoted by <m>A\oplus B</m>) is the set of all elements
that are in AandB but not in both. That is, <m>A \oplus  B = (A \cup  B) - (A \cap  B)</m>. 
</statement>  
<notation><m>A\oplus B</m></notation>
</definition>
<example  xml:id="some_symmetric_differences">
<title>Some Symmetric Differences</title>
<ol type="a">
<li>Let <m>A = \{1, 3, 8\}</m> and <m>B = \{2, 4, 8\}</m>. Then <m>A \oplus  B = \{1, 2, 3, 4\}</m>. 
</li>
<li><m>A \oplus  0 = A</m> and <m>A \oplus  A = \emptyset</m> for any set <m>A</m>. 
</li>
<li><m>\mathbb{R} \oplus  \mathbb{Q}</m> is the set of irrational numbers. 
</li>
<li><p>The Venn diagram of <m>A \oplus  B</m> is represented in the following figure.
            <figure xml:id="venn_diagram_symmetric">
                    <caption>Venn Diagram for the symmetric difference <m>A \oplus  B</m></caption>
                    <image xml:id="sageplot-venn-symmetric">
                        <description>A two set Venn Diagram for the symmetric difference of two sets.</description>
                        <sageplot>
								m=2
								scale = 1.7
								sx=3
								sy=2
								centers = [(cos(n*2*pi/m), sin(n*2*pi/m)) for n in range(m)]
								clr = ['blue', 'blue', 'green']
								G = Graphics()
								r=lambda x,y:((x-centers[0][0])^2+(y-centers[0][1])^2 &lt; scale^2  or (x-centers[1][0])^2+(y-centers[1][1])^2 &lt; scale^2) and ~((x-centers[0][0])^2+(y-centers[0][1])^2 &lt; scale^2  and (x-centers[1][0])^2+(y-centers[1][1])^2 &lt; scale^2)
								G+=region_plot(r,(-sx,sx),(-sy,sy),plot_points=200,incol='lightblue',axes=False)
								for i in range(m):
									G += circle(centers[i], scale)
								for i in range(m):
									G += circle(centers[i], scale)
								G+=line([[-sx,-sy],[sx,-sy],[sx,sy],[-sx,sy],[-sx,-sy]],rgbcolor=(0,0,0))
								G+=text('B',centers[0],fontsize='x-large')
								G+=text('A',centers[1],fontsize='x-large')
								G
                        </sageplot>
                    </image>
                </figure> 
 </p>  
</li>
</ol>
</example>
<subsubsection name="Sage_Note_Sets-1-2">
<title> <m> Sage</m> Note: Sets</title>
<p>To work with sets in Sage, a set is an expression of the form  Set(<em>list</em>).  By wrapping a list with set, the order of elements appearing in the list and their duplication are ignored.  For example, L1 and L2 are two different list, but notice how as sets they are considered equal:</p>
<sage>
<input>
L1=[3,6,9,0,3]
L2=[9,6,3,0,9]
[L1==L2, Set(L1)==Set(L2) ]
</input>
</sage>
<p>The standard set operations are all methods and/or functions that can act on Sage sets. <em>You need to evalute the following cell to use the subsequent cell.</em></p>
<sage>
<input>
A=Set(srange(5,50,5))
B=Set(srange(6,50,6))
[A,B]
</input>
</sage>
<p>
We can test membership, asking whether 10 is in each of the sets:
</p>
<sage>
<input>
[10 in A, 10 in B]
</input>
</sage>
<p>
The ampersand is used for the intersection of sets.  Change it to the vertical bar, |,  for intersection. 
</p>
<sage>
<input>
A &amp; B
</input>
</sage>
<p>Symmetric difference is defined as a &amp;method&amp; in Sage. To compute the symmetric difference of A  with  B, we evaluate the expression <m>\texttt{ A.symmetric_difference(B) }</m>.</p>
</subsubsection>
</subsection>
<exercises xml:id="exercises-1.2">
<title>EXERCISES FOR SECTION 1.2 </title>
<exercisegroup><introduction><p>A Exercises</p></introduction>
<exercise number="1">
<statement> Let <m>A = \{0, 2, 3\}</m>, <m>B = \{2, 3\}</m>, <m>C = \{1, 5, 9\}</m>, and let the universal set be <m>U = \{0, 1, 2, . . . , 9\}</m>. Determine: 
<ol cols="2" style="a">
<li>  <m>A \cap  B</m>  </li>
<li>  <m>A \cup  B</m></li>
<li>  <m>B \cup  A</m>   </li>
<li>  <m>A \cup  C</m> </li>
<li>  <m>A - B</m></li>
<li>  <m>B - A</m></li>
<li>   <m>A^c</m> </li>
<li>   <m>C^c</m></li>
<li>  <m>A\cap C</m></li>
<li>   <m>A\oplus B</m> </li>
</ol>
</statement>
</exercise>
<exercise number="2"><statement>  Let <m> A</m>, <m> B</m>, and <m> C</m> be as in Exercise 1, let <m>D = \{3, 2\}</m>, and let <m>E = \{2, 3, 2\}</m>. Determine which of the
following are true. Give reasons for your decisions. 
<ol cols="2" style="a">
<li>  <m>A = B</m> </li>
<li>  <m>B = C</m> </li>
<li>  <m>B = D</m> </li>
<li>  <m>E=D</m></li>
<li>  <m>A\cap B = B\cap A</m></li>
<li>  <m>A \cup  B = B \cup  A</m> </li>
<li>  <m>A-B = B-A</m> </li>
<li>  <m>A \oplus  B = B \oplus  A</m> </li>
</ol>
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="3"><statement>  Let <m>U= \{1, 2, 3, . . . , 9\}</m>. 
Give examples of sets <m> A</m>, <m> B</m>, and <m> C</m> for which:
<ol cols="2" style="a">
<li>  <m>A\cap (B\cap C)=(A\cap B)\cap C</m> </li>
<li>  <m>A\cap (B\cup C)=(A\cap B)\cup (A\cap C)</m></li>
<li>  <m>(A \cup  B)^c= A^c\cap B^c</m> </li>
<li>  <m>A \cup  A^c = U</m></li>
<li>  <m>A \subseteq A\cup B</m></li>
<li>  <m>A\cap B \subseteq A</m> </li>
</ol>
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="4"><statement>  Let <m>U= \{1, 2, 3, . . . , 9\}</m>. Give examples to illustrate the following facts: 
<ol cols="1" style="a">
<li>  If <m>A \subseteq  B</m> and <m>B \subseteq C</m>, then <m>A\subseteq C</m>.</li>
<li>  <m>A - B \neq  B - A</m> </li>
<li>  If <m>U = A\cup  B</m> and <m>\text{A $\cap $ B = $\emptyset $}</m>, it always follows that <m>A = U - B</m>. </li>
<li>  <m>A \times  (B\cap C) = (A \times  B)\cap  (A \times C)</m>   </li>
</ol>
</statement></exercise>
</exercisegroup>
<exercisegroup><introduction><p>B Exercises</p></introduction>
<exercise number="5"><statement>  What can you say about <m>A</m> if <m>U = \{1, 2, 3, 4, 5\}</m>, <m>B = \{2, 3\}</m>, and (separately) 
<ol cols="1" style="a">
<li>  <m>A \cup B = \{1, 2, 3,4\}</m> </li>
<li>  <m>A \cap  B = \{2\}</m> </li>
<li>  <m>A \oplus  B = \{3, 4, 5\}</m></li>
</ol> 
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="6"><statement> Suppose that <m> U</m> is an infinite universal set, and <m> A</m> and <m> B</m> are infinite subsets of <m> U</m>. Answer the following questions with a brief explanation. 
<ol cols="1" style="a">
<li>  Must <m>A^c</m> be finite? </li>
<li>  Must <m>A\cup B</m> infinite? </li>
<li>  Must <m>A\cap B</m> be infinite? </li>
</ol>
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="7"><statement>  Given that <m> U</m> = all students at a university, <m> D</m> = day students, <m> M</m> = mathematics majors, and <m> G</m> = graduate
students. Draw Venn diagrams illustrating this situation and shade in the following sets: 
<ol cols="1" style="a">
<li>  evening students </li>
<li>  undergraduate mathematics majors </li>
<li>  non-math graduate students </li>
<li>  non-math undergraduate students</li>
</ol> 
</statement></exercise>
<exercise number="8"><statement> Let the sets <m> D</m>, <m> M</m>, <m> G</m>, and <m> U</m> be as in exercise 7.  Let <m>\lvert U \rvert  = 16,000</m>, <m>\lvert D \rvert = 9,000</m>, <m>|M |=
300</m>, and <m>\lvert G \rvert = 1,000</m>. Also assume that the number of day students who are mathematics majors is 250, fifty of whom are graduate students, that there are 95 graduate mathematics majors, and that the total number of day graduate students is 700. Determine the number of students who are: 
<ol cols="1" style="a">
<li>  evening students </li>
<li>  nonmathematics majors </li>
<li>  undergraduates (day or evening) </li>
<li>  day graduate nonmathematics majors </li>
<li>  evening graduate students </li>
<li>  evening graduate mathematics majors </li>
<li>  evening undergraduate nonmathematics majors </li>
</ol>
</statement></exercise>
</exercisegroup>
<!-- 
<exercisegroup number="no"><introduction><p>C Exercises</p></introduction>
<exercise number="9">
	<statement>  Sage exercise?
	</statement>
</exercise>
</exercisegroup>
 -->
</exercises>
</section>
<section xml:id="Cartesian_Products_and_Power_Sets">
<title>Cartesian Products and Power Sets</title>
<definition  xml:id="cartesian-product.">
<title> Cartesian Product.</title><statement> Let <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> be sets. The Cartesian product of <m>A</m> and <m>B</m>, denoted by <m>A\times B</m>, is defined as follows: <m>A\times B = \{(a, b) \mid a \in  A \quad\textrm{ and }\quad b \in  B\}</m>, that is, <m>A\times B</m> is the set of all possible ordered pairs whose first component comes from <m>A</m> and whose second component comes from <m>B</m>.
 </statement>
 </definition>
<example><title>Some Cartesian Products</title>
<p> Notation in mathematics is often developed for good reason. In this case, a few examples will make clear why the symbol $\times $ is used for Cartesian products.</p>
<ul>
<li>  Let <m>A = \{1, 2, 3\}</m> and <m>B = \{4, 5\}</m>. Then <m>A \times  B = \{(1, 4), (1, 5), (2, 4), (2, 5), (3, 4), (3, 5)\}</m>. Note that <m>|A \times B| = 6 = \lvert A \rvert  \times  \lvert B \rvert </m>. </li>
<li>  <m>A \times  A = \{(1, 1), (1, 2), (1, 3), (2, 1), (2, 2), (2, 3), (3, 1), (3, 2), (3, 3)\}</m>. Note that <m>|A \times  A| = 9 = {\lvert A \rvert}^2</m>.</li>
</ul>  </example>
<p>These two examples illustrate the general rule: If A and B are finite sets, then <m>| A \times B | = \lvert A \rvert  \times  \lvert B \rvert </m>.</p>
<p>We can define the Cartesian product of three (or more) sets similarly. For example, <m>A \times  B \times  C = \{(a, b, c):a \in  A, b \in  B, c \in C\}</m>. </p>
<p>It is common to use exponents if the sets in a Cartesian product are the same: 
<me>A^2= A \times  A</me>
<me>A^3=A \times A \times A</me>
and in general, 
<me>A^n =A \times A \times \ldots \times A</me>.</p>
<subsection number="no">
<title>Power Sets</title></subsection>
<definition  xml:id="power-set">
<title> Power Set. </title> 
<statement>If <m> A</m> is any set, the power set of <m>A</m> is the set of all subsets of <m>A</m>, denoted <m>\mathcal{P}(A)</m>.</statement>
<notation>\mathcal{P}(A)</notation>
</definition>
<p>The two extreme cases, the empty set and all of <m>A</m>, are both included in <m>\mathcal{P}(A)</m>.</p>
<example  xml:id="Some_Power_Sets">
<title> Some Power Sets </title>
<ul>
<li><m>\mathcal{P}(\emptyset )=\{\emptyset \}</m> </li>
<li> <m>\mathcal{P}(\{1\}) = \{\emptyset , \{1\}\}</m> </li>
<li> <m>\mathcal{P}(\{1,2\}) = \{\emptyset , \{1\}, \{2\}, \{1, 2\}\}</m>. </li>
</ul>
<p>We will leave it to you to guess at a general formula for the number of elements in the power set of a finite set. In Chapter 2, we will discuss counting rules that will help us derive this formula.</p> 
</example>
<subsubsection name="Sage_Note_Sets-1-3">
<title> <m> Sage</m> Note: Cartesion Products and Power Sets</title>
<p>Here is a simple example of a cartesion product of two sets:</p>
<sage>
<input>
A=Set([0,1,2])
B=Set(['a','b'])
P=cartesian_product([A,B]);P
</input>
</sage>
<p>Here is the cardinality of the cartesian product.</p>
<sage>
<input>
P.cardinality()
</input>
</sage>
<p>
The power set of a set is an iterable, as you can see from the output of this next cell
</p>
<sage>
<input>
U=Set([0,1,2,3])
subsets(U)
</input>
</sage>
<p>
You can iterate over a powerset - here is a trivial example.  
</p>
<sage>
<input>
for a in subsets(U):
    print(str(a)+ " has " +str(len(a))+" elements.")
</input>
</sage>
</subsubsection>
   
<exercises xml:id="exercises-1.3">
<title>EXERCISES FOR SECTION 1.3 </title>
<exercisegroup><introduction><p>A Exercises</p></introduction>
<exercise number="1">
<statement>  Let <m>A = \{0, 2, 3\}</m>, <m>B = \{2, 3\}</m>, <m>C = \{1, 4\}</m>, and let the universal set be <m>U = \{0, 1, 2, 3, 4\}</m>. List the elements of 
<ul>
<li>  <m>A \times B</m> </li>
<li>  <m>B \times  A</m> </li>
<li>  <m>A \times B\times C</m> </li>
<li>  <m>U \times \emptyset</m></li>
 <li>  <m>A \times  A^c</m></li>
 <li>  <m>B^2</m> </li>
 <li>  <m>B^3</m></li>
 <li>  <m>B\times \mathcal{P}(B)</m></li>
 </ul>
</statement> </exercise>
<exercise number="2"><statement> 
Suppose that you are about to flip a coin and then roll a die. Let <m>A = \{HEADS, TAILS\}</m> and  <m>B = {$1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6}</m>. 
<ul>
<li>  What is <m>|A \times  B|</m>? </li>
<li>  How could you interpret the set <m>A \times  B</m> ?   </li>
</ul>
</statement> </exercise>
<exercise number="3"><statement> 
List all two-element sets in <m>\mathcal{P}(\{a,b,c\})</m> 
</statement> </exercise>
<exercise number="4"><statement> 
List all three-element sets in <m>\mathcal{P}(\{a, b, c,d\})</m>. 
</statement> </exercise>
<exercise number="5"><statement> 
How many singleton (one-element) sets are there in <m>\mathcal{P}(A)</m> if <m>\lvert A \rvert =n</m> ? 
</statement> </exercise>
<exercise number="6"><statement> 
A person has four coins in his pocket: a penny, a nickel, a dime, and a quarter. How many different sums of money can he take out if he removes
3 coins at a time? 
</statement> </exercise>
<exercise number="7"><statement> 
Let <m>A = \{+,-\}</m> and <m>B = \{00, 01, 10, 11\}</m>.
<ul>
<li>  List the elements of <m>A \times  B</m> </li>
<li>  How many elements do <m>A ^4</m> and <m>(A \times B)^3</m> have? </li>
</ul>
</statement> </exercise>
</exercisegroup>
<exercisegroup><introduction><p>B Exercises</p></introduction>
<exercise number="8"><statement> 
Let <m>A = \{\bullet,\square ,\otimes \}</m> and <m>B = \{\square ,\ominus ,\bullet\}</m>. 
<ul>
<li> List the elements of <m>A \times  B</m> and <m>B \times  A</m>. The parentheses and comma in an ordered pair are not necessary in cases such as this where the elements of each set are individual symbol. </li>
<li>  Identify the intersection of <m>A \times  B</m> and <m>B \times  A</m>. for the case above, and then guess at a general rule for the intersection of <m>A \times  B</m> and <m>B \times  A</m>. where <m> A</m> and <m> B</m> are any two sets. </li>
</ul>
</statement> </exercise>
<exercise number="9"><statement> 
Let <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> be nonempty sets. When are <m>A \times  B</m> and <m>B \times  A</m>. equal? 
</statement> </exercise>
</exercisegroup>
</exercises>
</section>  
<section xml:id="Binary_Representation_of_Positive_Integers ">
<title>Binary Representation of Positive Integers </title>
<p>Recall that the set of positive integers, <m>\mathbb{P}</m>, is <m>\{1, 2, 3, . . . \}</m>. Positive integers are naturally used to count things. There are many ways to count and many ways to record, or represent, the results of counting. For example, if we wanted to count five hundred twenty-three apples, we might group the apples by tens. There would be fifty-two groups of ten with three single apples left over. The fifty-two groups of ten could be put into five groups of ten tens (hundreds), with two tens left over. The five hundreds, two tens, and three units is recorded as 523. This system of counting is called the base ten positional system, or decimal system. It is quite natural for us to do grouping by tens, hundreds, thousands, <m>\dots</m> since it is the method that all of us use in everyday life. </p>
<p> The term positional refers to the fact that each digit in the decimal representation of a number has a significance based on its position. Of course this means that rearranging digits will change the number being described. You may have learned of numeraton systems in which the position of symbols does not have any significance (e.g., the ancient Egyptian system). Most of these systems are merely curiosities to us now.</p>
<p>The binary number system differs from the decimal number system in that units are grouped by twos, fours, eights, etc. That is, the group sizes are powers of two instead of powers of ten. For example, twenty-three can be grouped into eleven groups of two with one left over. The eleven twos can be grouped into five groups of four with one group of two left over. Continuing along the same lines, we find that twenty-three can be described as one sixteen, zero eights, one four, one two, and one one, which is abbreviated <m>10111_{\textrm{two}}</m>, or simply <m>10111</m> if the
context is clear. </p>
<p>The process that we used to determine the binary representation of <m>23</m> can be described in general terms to determine the binary representation of any positive integer n. A general description of a process such as this one is called an algorithm. Since this is the first algorithm in the book, we will first write it out using less formal language than usual, and then introduce some <q>algorithmic notation.</q></p> 
<p><ol style="1">
	<li> Start with an empty list of bits. </li>
	<li> Step Two: Assign the variable <m>k</m> the value <m>n</m>. </li>
	<li> Step Three: While <m>k</m>'s value is positive, continue performing the following three steps until <m>k</m> becomes zero and then stop. 
	<ol style="a"> 
		<li>divide <m>k</m> by 2, obtaining a quotient <m>q</m> (often denoted <m>k \textrm{ div } 2</m>) and a remainder <m>r</m> (denoted <m>(k \bmod 2)</m>). </li>
		<li>attach <m>r</m> to the left-hand side of the list of bits. </li>
		<li> assign the variable <m>k</m> the value <m>q</m>.</li>   
	</ol></li>
</ol></p>
<example  xml:id="An_example_of_conversion_to_binary">
<title>An example of conversion to binary</title>
<p> To determine the binary representation of 41 we take the following steps:
<ul> 
<li><m>41 = 2 \times  20+ 1 \quad List = 1 </m> </li>
<li><m>20 = 2 \times  10+0 \quad List = 01 </m></li>
<li> <m>10 = 2\times 5 + 0 \quad List = 001 </m></li>
<li><m>5 =\text2\times  2+ 1 \quad List =1001</m> </li>
<li><m>2 =2\times  1+ 0 \quad List = 01001 </m></li>
<li><m>1 =\text2 \times 0\text+1  \quad List = 101001</m> </li>
</ul>   
Therefore, <m>41=101001_{\textrm{two}}</m></p>
</example>
<p>The notation that we will use to describe this algorithm and all others is called pseudocode, an informal variation of the instructions that are commonly used in many computer languages. Read the following description carefully, comparing it with the informal description above. Appendix B, which contains a general discussion of the components of the algorithms in this book, should clear up any lingering questions. Anything after // are comments.</p> 
<algorithm  xml:id="binary_conversion_algorithm">
<title>Binary Conversion Algorithm</title><statement>
<p> An algorithm for determining the binary representation of a positive integer.</p>
<p>Input: a positive integer n.</p> 
<p>Output: the binary representation of n in the form of a list of bits, with units bit last, twos bit next to last, etc.</p> 
<ol style="1">
<li>k := n <m>\qquad  </m>     //initialize k</li>
<li>L := { } <m>\qquad  </m>   //initialize L to an empty list</li>
<li> While k > 0 do 
   <ol style="a">
   	<li> q := k div 2		<m>\qquad  </m>	//divide k by 2</li>
      <li> r:= k mod 2 </li>
   	<li>L: = prepend r to L <m>\qquad  </m> //Add r to the front of L </li>
    	<li> k:= q   			<m>\qquad  </m>	//reassign k</li>
</ol></li>
</ol>
</statement>
</algorithm>
<p>Now that you've read this section, you should get this joke.</p>
            <figure xml:id="onetoten">
                <caption>With permission from Randall Munroe
                </caption>
                <image width="300" source="images/1_to_10.png">
                    <description>Comic from http://xkcd.com.</description>
                </image>
            </figure>

<exercises xml:id="exercises-1.4">
<title>EXERCISES FOR SECTION 1.4 </title>
<exercisegroup><introduction><p>A Exercises</p></introduction>
<exercise number="1"><statement> 
Find the binary representation of each of the following positive integers: 
<ol type="a"><li> 31</li><li> 32</li><li>10</li><li>100 </li></ol>
</statement> </exercise>
<exercise number="2"><statement> 
Find the binary representation of each of the following positive integers: 
<ol type="a"><li> 64</li><li> 67</li><li>28</li><li>256 </li></ol>
</statement> </exercise>
<exercise number="3"><statement> 
What positive integers have the following binary representations?
<ol type="a"><li> 10010</li><li> 10011</li><li>101010</li><li>10011110000 </li></ol>
</statement> </exercise>
<exercise number="4"><statement> 
What positive integers have the following binary representations?
<ol type="a"><li> 100001</li><li> 1001001</li><li>1000000000</li><li>1001110000 </li></ol>
</statement> </exercise>
<exercise number="5"><statement> 
The number of bits in the binary representations of integers increase by one as the numbers double.  Using this fact, determine how many bits the binary representations of the following decimal numbers have without actually doing the full conversion. 
<m> \quad (a) 2011  \quad (b)  4000   \quad (c) 4500   \quad (d) 2^{50}</m> 
</statement> </exercise>
</exercisegroup>
<exercisegroup><introduction><p>B Exercises</p></introduction>
<exercise number="6"><statement> 
Let <m>m</m> be a positive integer with <m> n</m>-bit binary representation: <m>a_{n-1}a_{n-2}\cdots  a_1a_0</m> with <m>a_{n-1}=1</m> What are the smallest
and largest values that <m>m</m> could have? 
</statement> </exercise>
<exercise number="7"><statement> 
If a positive integer is a multiple of 100, we can identify this fact from its decimal representation, since it will end with two zeros. What can
you say about a positive integer if its binary representation ends with two zeros? 
</statement> </exercise>
<exercise number="8"><statement> 
Can a multiple of ten be easily identified from its binary representation? 
</statement> </exercise>
</exercisegroup>
</exercises>
</section>  
<section xml:id="Summation_Notation_and_Generalizations ">
<title>Summation Notation and Generalizations </title>
<p>Most operations such as addition of numbers are introduced as binary operations. That is, we are taught that two numbers may be added
together to give us a single number. Before long, we run into situations where more than two numbers are to be added. For example, if four numbers,
<m>a_1</m>, <m>a_2</m>, <m>a_3</m>, and <m>a_4</m> are to be added, their sum may be written down in several ways, such as<m></m> <m>((a_1+a_2)+a_3)+a_4</m>
or <m>\left(a_1+a_2\right)+\left(a_3+a_4\right)</m>. In the first expression, the first two numbers are added, the result is added to the third number,
and that result is added to the fourth number. In the second expression the first two numbers and the last two numbers are added and the results
of these additions are added. Of course, we know that the final results will be the same. This is due to the fact that addition of numbers is an
associative operation. For such operations, there is no need to describe how more than two objects will be operated on. 
A sum of numbers such as <m>a_1+a_2+a_3+a_4</m>is called a series and is often written <m>\sum _{k=1}^4 a_k</m> in what is called <em> summation notation</em>. </p>
<p>We first recall some basic facts about series that you probably have seen before. A more formal treatment of sequences and series is covered in Chapter 8. The purpose here is to give the reader a working knowledge of summation notation and to carry this notation through to intersection
and union of sets and other mathematical operations. </p>
<p>A <em>finite series</em> is an expression such as <m>a_1+a_2+a_3 +\dots +a_n=\sum _{k=1}^{n} a_k</m></p> 
<p>In the expression <m>\sum _{k=1}^{n} a_k</m>:
<ul>
<li> The variable <m>k</m> is referred to as the <em> index</em>, or the index of summation.</li>
<li> The expression <m>a_k</m> is the <em> general term</em> of the series. It defines the numbers that are being added together in the series.</li>
<li> The value of <m>k</m> below the summation symbol is the <em> initial index</em> and the value above the summation symbol is the <em> terminal index</em>.</li> 
<li> It is understood that the series is a sum of the general terms where the index start with the initial index and increases by one up to and including the terminal index.</li>
</ul></p>
<example  xml:id="some_finite_series">
<title>Some finite series</title>
<p>(a)  <m>\sum _{i=1}^4 a_i= a_1+ a_2+a_3+a_4</m></p>
<p>(b) <m>\sum _{k=0}^5 b_k=b_0+b_1+b_2+b_3+b_4+b_5</m></p>
<p>(c) <m>\sum _{i=-2}^2 c_i=c_{-2}+c_{-1}+c_0+c_1+c_2</m></p>
</example>
<example  xml:id="more_finite_series">
<title>More finite series </title>
<p>If the general terms in a series are more specific, the sum can often be simplified. For example, 
<ol type="a"> 
<li> <m>\sum _{i=1}^4 i^2=1^2+2^2+3^2+4^2=30</m> </li>  
<li> <m>\sum _{i=1}^5 (2i-1)=(2\ 1-1)+(2\ 2-1)+(2\ 3-1)+(2\ 4-1)+(2\ 5-1)\\
\\
\quad \quad =1+3+5+7+9\\
\\
\quad \quad =25</m></li>
</ol>
</p>
</example>
<p>Summation notation can be generalized to many mathematical operations, for example, 
<m>A_1\cap A_2\cap A_3\cap A_4=\underset{i=1}{\overset{4}{\cap }}A_i</m> </p>
<definition  xml:id="generalized-set-operations">
<title> Generalized Set Operations.</title> <statement>Let <m>A_1, A_2, \ldots , A_n</m> be sets. Then: 
<ol type="a"> 
<li>  <m>A_1\cap A_2\cap \cdots \cap A_n=\underset{i=1}{\overset{n}{\cap }}A_i</m></li>
<li>   <m>A_1\cup A_2\cup \cdots \cup A_n=\underset{i=1}{\overset{n}{\cup }}A_i</m></li>
<li>   <m>A_1\times A_2\times \cdots \times A_n=\underset{i=1}{\overset{n}{\times }}A_i</m></li>
<li>   <m>A_1\oplus A_2\oplus \cdots \oplus A_n=\underset{i=1}{\overset{n}{\oplus }}A_i</m></li>
</ol></statement>
</definition>
<example  xml:id="some_generalized_operations">
<title>Some generalized operations</title>
<p>If <m>A_1 = \{0, 2, 3\}</m>, <m>A_2 = \{1, 2, 3, 6\}</m>, and <m>A_3 = \{-1, 0, 3, 9\}</m>, then 
 <me>\underset{i=1}{\overset{4}{\cap }}A_i=A_1\cap A_2\cap A_3=\{3\}</me>
and
<me>\underset{i=1}{\overset{4}{\cup }}A_i=A_1\cup A_2\cup A_3=\{-1,0,1,2,3,6,9\}</me>
With this notation it is quite easy to write lengthy expressions in a fairly compact form. For example, the statement 
    <me>A\cap \left(B_1\cup B_2\cup \cdots \cup B_n\right)= \left(A\cap B_1\right)\cup \left(A\cap B_2\right)\cup \cdots \cup \left(A\cap
B_n\right)</me>
becomes 
   <me>A \cap \left(\underset{i=1}{\overset{n}{\cup }}B_i\right)= \underset{i=1}{\overset{n}{\cup }}\left(A\cap B_n\right)</me></p>
</example> 
<exercises xml:id="exercises-1.5">
<title>EXERCISES FOR SECTION 1.5 </title>
<exercisegroup><title>A Exercises</title>
<exercise number="1"><statement> 
Calculate the following series:
<ol type="a">   
<li>  <m>\sum _{i=1}^3 (2 + 3i)</m></li>
<li>  <m>\sum _{i=-2}^1 i^2</m> </li>
<li>  <m>\sum _{j=0}^n 2^j\text{   }</m> for <m>n= 1, 2, 3, 4</m></li>
<li>  <m>\sum _{k=1}^n (2k-1)</m> for <m>n = 1, 2, 3, 4</m> </li>
</ol>
</statement> </exercise>
<exercise number="2"><statement> Calculate the following series: 
<ol type="a">
<li>  <m>\sum _{k=1}^3 i^n</m> for<m>n = 1, 2, 3, 4</m> </li>
<li>  <m>\sum _{i=1}^5 20</m> </li>
<li>   <m>\sum _{j=0}^3 \left(n^j+1\right)</m> for <m>n = 1, 2, 3,4</m> </li>
<li>   <m>\sum _{k=-n}^n k</m> for <m>n = 1, 2, 3, 4</m> </li>
</ol>
</statement> </exercise>
<exercise number="3"><statement>  
<ol type="a">
<li>  Express the formula <m>\sum _{i=1}^n \frac{1}{i(i+1)}= \frac{n}{n+1}</m>  without using summation notation. </li>
<li>  Verify this formula for <m>n=3</m>. </li>
<li>  Repeat parts (a) and (b) for <m>\sum _{i=1}^n i^3=\frac{n^2(n+1)^2}{4}</m></li>
</ol>
</statement> </exercise>
<exercise number="4"><statement>   Verify the following properties for <m>n = 3</m>.   
<ol type="a">
<li>   <m>\sum _{i=1}^n \left(a_i+ b_i\right) =\sum _{i=1}^n a_i +\sum _{i=1}^n  b_i</m> </li>
<li>    <m>c\left(\sum _{i=1}^n a_i\right) = \sum _{i=1}^n c a_i</m></li>
</ol>
</statement> </exercise>
<exercise number="5"><statement> 
 Rewrite the following without summation sign for <m>n = 3</m>. It is not necessary that you understand or expand the notation <m>\left(
\begin{array}{c}
 n \\
 k \\
\end{array}
\right)</m> at this point. 
  <m>(x + y)^n= \sum _{k=0}^n \left(
\begin{array}{c}
 n \\
 k \\
\end{array}
\right)x^{n-k}y^k</m>
</statement> </exercise>
<exercise number="6"><statement> 
<ol type="a">
 <li>  Draw the Venn diagram for <m>\underset{i=1}{\overset{3}{\cap }}A_i</m>.</li>
 <li> (b) Express in <q>expanded format</q>: 
<m>	A\cup (\underset{i=1}{\overset{n}{\cap }}B_i)= \underset{i=1}{\overset{n}{\cap }}(A \cup B_n)</m>.</li>
</ol>
</statement> </exercise>
<exercise number="7"><statement> 
 For any positive integer <m>k</m>, let <m>A_k = \{x \in \mathbb{Q}:k-1 &lt; x &lt;= k\}</m> and <m>B_k = \{x \in \mathbb{Q}: -k &lt; x &lt; k\}</m>. What are
the following sets? 
<ol type="a">  
<li>  <m>\underset{i=1}{\overset{5}{\cup }}A_i</m></li>
<li>  <m>\underset{i=1}{\overset{5}{\cup }}B_i</m></li>
<li>  <m>\underset{i=1}{\overset{5}{\cap }}A_i</m></li>
 <li>  <m>\underset{i=1}{\overset{5}{\cap }}B_i</m> </li>
 </ol>
</statement> </exercise>
<exercise number="8"><statement> 
 For any positive integer k, let <m>A = \{x \in \mathbb{Q}:\text0 &lt; x &lt; 1/k\}</m> and <m>B _k = \{x \in \mathbb{Q}:\text{   }0 &lt; x &lt; k\}</m>. What
are the following sets? 
<ol type="a">
<li>  <m>\underset{i=1}{\overset{\infty }{\cup }}A_i</m></li>
<li>  <m>\underset{i=1}{\overset{\infty }{\cup }}B_i</m></li>
<li>  <m>\underset{i=1}{\overset{\infty }{\cap }}A_i</m></li>
 <li>  <m>\underset{i=1}{\overset{\infty }{\cap }}B_i</m></li>
 </ol> 
</statement> </exercise>
<exercise number="9"><statement> 
The symbol <m>\Pi</m> is used for the product of numbers in the same way that <m>\Sigma</m> is used for sums. For example,
  <m>\prod _{i=1}^5 x_i=x_1 x_2 x_3 x_4 x_5</m>
Evaluate the following: 
<ol type="a">
<li>  <m>\prod _{i=1}^3 i^2</m></li>
<li>   <m>\prod _{i=1}^3 (2i+1)</m></li>
</ol>
</statement> </exercise>
<exercise number="10"><statement> 
Evaluate
<ol type="a"> 
<li>   <m>\prod _{k=0}^3 2^k</m></li>
<li>   <m>\prod _{k=1}^{100} \frac{k}{k+1}</m></li>
</ol> 
</statement> </exercise>
</exercisegroup>
</exercises>
</section>

</chapter>	