<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="chapter_10" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"><title>Trees</title>
<introduction>
<p>This is a stub for Part 2 of Applied Discrete Structures. To see the whole chapter, visit our web page at http://faculty.uml.edu/klevasseur/ADS2.</p><p>In this chapter we will study the class of graphs called trees. Trees are frequently used in both mathematics and the sciences. Our solution of <xref ref="lunch-possibilies1" text="type-global"/> is one simple instance. Since they are often used to illustrate or prove other concepts, a poor understanding of trees can be a serious handicap. For this reason, our ultimate goals are to: (1) define the various common types of trees, (2) identify some basic properties of trees, and (3) discuss some of the common applications of trees.
</p></introduction>



<example xml:id="lunch-possibilies1"><title>How many lunches can you have?</title><p>A snack bar serves five different sandwiches and three different beverages. How many different lunches can a person order? One way of determining the number of possible lunches is by listing or enumerating all the possibilities. One systematic way of doing this is by means of a tree, as in the following figure.</p>
            <figure xml:id="lunch">
                <caption>Tree diagram to enumerate the number of possible lunches.
                </caption>
                <image width="50%" source="images/lunch.png">
                    <description>Tree diagram to enumerate the number of possible lunches.</description>
                </image>
            </figure>
<p>
 Every path that begins at the position labeled START and goes to the right can be interpreted as a choice of one of the five sandwiches followed by a choice of one of the three beverages. Note that considerable work is required to arrive at the number fifteen this way; but we also get more than just a number. The result is a complete list of all possible lunches. If we need to answer a question that starts with <q>How many . . . ,</q> enumeration would be done only as a last resort. In a later chapter we will examine more enumeration techniques.
</p>
</example>

</chapter>